<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>FiveThirtyEight &#187; Features &#124; FiveThirtyEight</title>
	<atom:link href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com</link>
	<description>FiveThirtyEight, Nate Silver’s newly launched website at ESPN, uses statistical analysis — hard numbers — to tell compelling stories about politics, science, economics, lifestyle, and sports.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2015 00:21:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.com/</generator>
<cloud domain='fivethirtyeight.com' port='80' path='/?rsscloud=notify' registerProcedure='' protocol='http-post' />
<image>
		<url>http://0.gravatar.com/blavatar/cb2459913f2d34a9135edfd3cbae1a15?s=96&#038;d=http%3A%2F%2Fs2.wp.com%2Fi%2Fbuttonw-com.png</url>
		<title> &#187; Features &#124; FiveThirtyEight</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com</link>
	</image>
	<atom:link rel="search" type="application/opensearchdescription+xml" href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/osd.xml" title="FiveThirtyEight" />
	<atom:link rel='hub' href='http://fivethirtyeight.com/?pushpress=hub'/>
	<item>
		<title>2015 NBA Playoffs Preview</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/2015-nba-playoffs-preview/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/2015-nba-playoffs-preview/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 18:12:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[FiveThirtyEight]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2015 NBA Playoffs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Atlanta Hawks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Basketball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Boston Celtics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brooklyn Nets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chicago Bulls]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cleveland Cavaliers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dallas Mavericks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Golden State Warriors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Houston Rockets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Los Angeles Clippers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Memphis Grizzlies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Milwaukee Bucks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[NBA]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Portland Trail Blazers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[San Antonio Spurs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Toronto Raptors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Washington Wizards]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=74461</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The NBA playoffs are finally upon us, and like the 16 teams vying for the Larry O&#8217;Brien trophy, we&#8217;ve come prepared &#8212; not with basketball skills, mind you, but with graphics and numbers. Using the latest (postseason-optimized) version of FiveThirtyEight’s NBA Power Ratings, we simulated the playoff bracket 10,000 times, counting how often each team [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74461&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The NBA playoffs are finally upon us, and like the 16 teams vying for the <a href="http://www1.pictures.zimbio.com/gi/Larry+O+brien+Trophy+Miami+Heat+Victory+Parade+UFUtbUY3kEXl.jpg">Larry O&#8217;Brien trophy</a>, we&#8217;ve come prepared &#8212; not with basketball skills, mind you,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="1" href="#fn-1"><sup id="ss-1">1</sup></a> but with graphics and numbers. Using the latest (postseason-optimized) version of <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-playoff-power/">FiveThirtyEight’s NBA Power Ratings</a>, we simulated the playoff bracket 10,000 times, counting how often each team won its first-round series (as well as tracking which teams won the NBA title most often). We also put together charts highlighting each team&#8217;s key players, along with their multiyear predictive <a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/story/_/id/10740818/introducing-real-plus-minus">Real Plus-Minus</a><a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="2" href="#fn-2"><sup id="ss-2">2</sup></a> ratings, plus a comparison of both teams&#8217; strengths and weaknesses according to the <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/about/factors.html">four factors of basketball</a>. (Note that in some of our write-ups below, we use <a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/statistics/rpm/_/sort/RPM">single-season RPM</a>, so those numbers will be slightly different than the multiyear RPM we list in the charts.) So get settled in, maybe <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HsG5uq9xOKo">throw some chalk in the air</a>, and enjoy the brutal, glorious two-month journey that is the road to the NBA championship.</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><h2>Western Conference</h2><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74471" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/warriors-pelicans-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="warriors pelicans final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>Each team is led by one of the best players in basketball: Stephen Curry on Golden State and Anthony Davis on New Orleans. So why do we think Golden State has a 92 percent chance to advance? Because Curry is better, and has much better teammates. Draymond Green, a top contender for Defensive Player of the Year, rates higher than Davis in the <a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/story/_/id/10740818/introducing-real-plus-minus">Real Plus-Minus</a> player ratings we’re using from <a href="https://twitter.com/jerryengelmann">Jeremias Engelmann</a> and <a href="http://www.researchgate.net/profile/Stephen_Ilardi/publications">Steve Ilardi</a>. Warriors sub Andre Iguodala would be the second-best Pelican. But this might not be a sweep: In their two games against Golden State in New Orleans, the Pelicans won once and forced overtime in the other. But Golden State&#8217;s formidable offense should dominate the Pelicans&#8217; subpar D. The Warriors look a lot more like a team for the ages &#8212; with an impressive 48 percent chance of winning it all &#8212; than like first-round upset fodder. (We were a little stunned by that 48 percent number, but Basketball-Reference.com gives the Warriors <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/friv/playoff_prob.cgi" target="_blank">about the same odds</a>.) <i>&#8212; Carl Bialik</i></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74464" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rockets-mavs-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="rockets mavs final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>It’s current MVP contender versus aging MVP winner (but the current contender is the one with the beard). James Harden versus Dirk Nowitzki. The Beard led the league in WAR, according to <a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/statistics/rpm">ESPN’s Real Plus-Minus metrics</a>. With Harden, Houston has the edge &#8212; a 66 percent chance of prevailing, according to FiveThirtyEight’s projections. Beyond Harden’s consistency, the Rockets have otherwise ridden the injury luck roller coaster. They enter the playoffs having lost two important starters: versatile big man Donatas Motiejunas and the feisty defender Patrick Beverley at the point. On the other hand, Dwight Howard has returned after missing half the season. The Rockets will need him to maintain their solid <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-playoff-power/">+3.2 defensive rating</a>.</p><p>For the Mavs, it’s been a tale of two seasons. After surprising the league with a hot start, Dallas stagnated after the All-Star break, going 14-13. In <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-playoff-power/">FiveThirtyEight’s latest NBA Power Ratings</a>, the Mavs rated as the worst of the Western Conference teams to make the playoffs &#8212; even behind the No. 8 seed New Orleans Pelicans. <em>&#8212; Andrew Flowers</em></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74505" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/clippers-spurs-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="clippers spurs final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>With the latest <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-playoff-power/">FiveThirtyEight Power Ratings</a> ranking the Spurs and Clippers as second and fourth, respectively, this matchup is one of the most compelling first-round matchups in recent memory.</p><p>The defending champion Spurs enter this tournament as the No. 6 seed in the Western Conference &#8212; far lower than the No. 2 seed they could have had <a href="http://www.usatoday.com/story/sports/nba/2015/04/15/final-day-playoff-spots-seeding-pelicans-thunder-pacers-nets/25805765/">if they had won</a> their final game against the Pelicans on Wednesday. Despite that loss, they had a 21-4 record over their last 25 games, reasserting that they’re contenders despite a 19-18 stretch in the middle of the season.</p><p>The story of their year has been the breakout of last year’s surprise finals MVP and zero-time All-Star<a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/l/leonaka01.html"> Kawhi Leonard</a>. The Spurs went 46-18 with him in the lineup, with an average margin of victory of 7.8 points per game &#8212; which would be second to Golden State’s 10.0 and matches the 7.8 they put up last year. Leonard’s 2014-15 <a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/statistics/rpm/_/sort/RPM">Real Plus-Minus</a> of 8.35 was second in basketball behind Stephen Curry’s, ahead of well-known small forward LeBron James’s. Oh, and he <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/leaders/stl_per_g_top_10.html">led the league</a> in <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-hidden-value-of-the-nba-steal/">steals per game</a>.</p><p>The Clippers are no slouches, either &#8212; their SRS<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="3" href="#fn-3"><sup id="ss-3">3</sup></a> of 6.8 is <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/leagues/NBA_2015.html">second-highest in the league</a> behind Golden State’s 10.0 (San Antonio is third, with 6.34). They’ve now <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/teams/LAC/">won either 56 or 57 games</a> in every full season of the Chris Paul/Blake Griffin era, yet their dynamic duo has not made it past the conference semifinals.</p><p>Although the Clippers have home-court advantage, the FiveThirtyEight simulations give the Spurs the edge, with a 53 percent chance of advancing. In fact, despite being projected to play any Game 7 from here on out on the road, San Antonio has the third-best chance of winning the championship, at 12 percent. The model gives the Clippers the fourth-best chance, at 8 percent. &#8212; <i>Benjamin Morris</i></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74509" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/blazers-grizzlies-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="blazers grizzlies final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>Portland won fewer games than Memphis (51 to 55) during the regular season, but because the Blazers won the comparatively weak Northwest division, they are the No. 4 seed in the Western Conference and the Grizzlies are the No. 5. But that seed advantage isn’t worth much. Since the Blazers had fewer wins, they will still be on the road for four of their seven potential games against Memphis. Making matters even more complicated, this series is so close that the question of home court could end up making all the difference. Only a tenth of a rating point separates them in <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-playoff-power/">our most recent power rankings</a>. Our model gives the Grizzlies a 54 percent probability of winning, but that number would flip around to 53 percent for Portland if the Blazers had home court. Of course, the Grizzlies earned their home-court advantage by winning more games (against a <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/leagues/NBA_2015.html#misc::6">tougher schedule</a>, no less), and this arrangement is good for Portland, too &#8212; a 46 percent chance against Memphis is preferable to a 24 percent chance versus the Clippers, which is who they’d face if the conference were seeded purely by record. But this inverted 4-versus-5 matchup is another example of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NBA_playoffs#2006_NBA_playoffs_controversy">how convoluted</a> and arbitrary the seeding process is in the NBA. And it’s another argument that the league should perhaps just <a href="http://grantland.com/the-triangle/abolish-useless-nba-divisions-step-1-of-a-radical-plan/" target="_blank">ditch divisions</a> (<a href="http://grantland.com/the-triangle/searching-for-balance-the-nbas-lopsided-conference-problem/" target="_blank">if not conferences</a>) entirely. &#8212; <i>Neil Paine</i></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><h2>Eastern Conference</h2><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74465" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/hawks-nets-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="hawks nets final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>The Brooklyn Nets will not win the NBA championship. No, really: We ran 10,000 simulations of the playoffs, and the Nets were the only team to never win it all. They have only a 10 percent chance of moving on from their first-round series against the Atlanta Hawks. This is among the most lopsided matchups of the first round. The Nets, ranked No. 22 in <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-playoff-power/">FiveThirtyEight’s Power Ratings</a>, are by far the worst team to make the postseason. With their 38-44 record and -2.9 point differential (<a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/standings">the only playoff team in red</a>), the Nets are lucky they’re in the Eastern Conference &#8212; further momentum for <a href="http://grantland.com/the-triangle/searching-for-balance-the-nbas-lopsided-conference-problem/">reform to the NBA’s postseason structure</a>.</p><p>Atlanta is coming off a franchise-record 60-win regular season; this should be a cakewalk for the Hawks (even after losing defensive stalwart Thabo Sefolosha to injury <a href="http://www.si.com/nba/2015/04/15/thabo-sefolosha-nypd-police-report-chris-copeland-stabbing">after a run-in with the NYPD</a>). Atlanta is well-balanced: +2.9 points <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/introducing-nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds/">per 100 possessions</a> on offense and +2.0 on defense. The Nets have a pedestrian offense (+1.1) but are a disaster on defense: At -4.7, their defensive rating is the fifth-worst in the league. If the Nets avoid a sweep, it’ll be an achievement. <em>&#8212; Andrew Flowers</em></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74519" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cavs-celtics-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="cavs celtics final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>You might think the Celtics should just be happy to be here. After all, in <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds-what-the-trade-deadline-hath-wrought/">late February</a>, they only had a 12 percent probability of making the playoffs, according to the <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/introducing-nba-power-ratings-and-playoff-odds/">FiveThirtyEight NBA Power Ratings</a>. But rather than merely showing up, getting their souvenir T-shirt and accepting a first-round loss, Boston could give LeBron James and the mighty Cavaliers more trouble than they bargained for. While we can&#8217;t derive much meaning from the Celtics&#8217; combined 216-168 margin over Cleveland in their two <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/boxscores/201504100CLE.html">April</a> <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/boxscores/201504120BOS.html">matchups</a> &#8212; the Cavs were mostly resting their key players &#8212; Boston is solid at both ends of the floor, with a great group of guards and a lot of depth. Over the course of the entire season, they were <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/leagues/NBA_2015_ratings.html#ratings::12">better offensively</a> (relative to the league) than the Cavs’ <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/leagues/NBA_2015_ratings.html#ratings::13">defense was</a>, and that only includes <a href="http://www.basketball-reference.com/players/t/thomais02/on-off/2015/">a few months of Isaiah Thomas</a>. Our model says the Celtics are still unlikely to pull the upset, but they have the ingredients to be much more of a pest than they seemed to be a few months ago. &#8212; <i>Neil Paine</i></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74473" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/bulls-bucks-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="bulls bucks final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>Derrick Rose is back in time for the playoffs. Unfortunately for the Bulls, he&#8217;s not the Derrick Rose of four seasons ago, the one who won the MVP award and led the Bulls to their only conference finals since Michael Jordan&#8217;s second retirement. Since then, Rose, slowed by injuries, has played just 100 regular-season games and one playoff game. Now he is the only Bulls starter who rates below league average. That&#8217;s not enough to make Milwaukee the favorite in this series. Two Bucks starters are below league average, and Milwaukee will have trouble scoring with an offense that is well below league average. The Bulls should win this series &#8212; and enjoy the win, because in half of our simulations of the playoffs, they go out in the next round, most likely to LeBron James and the Cavs. &#8212; <i>Carl Bialik</i></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74494" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/raptors-wizards-final.png?w=610&#038;h=703" alt="raptors wizards final" width="610" height="703" /></p><p>This series features two teams that started out the season looking like they might be the next big thing (at least in the Eastern Conference). The fourth-seeded Toronto Raptors began the season 7-1 and made it all the way to 24-7 before a four-game losing streak started their 25-26 finish &#8212; with their final record only a one-win improvement on last year. The Wizards started out 4-1 and made it to 19-6, but have been 27-30 since, ultimately improving on last season’s 44-win campaign by just two wins.</p><p>Both teams are led by All-Star point guards, Toronto’s Kyle Lowry and Washington’s John Wall, with Lowry making the All-Star team for the first time in the eighth year of his career (his third with the Raptors). ESPN’s Real Plus-Minus for this season ranks them as the <a href="http://espn.go.com/nba/statistics/rpm/_/sort/RPM/position/1">fourth- and sixth-best point guards in 2015</a>. Lowry performed a little worse than last year; his RPM dipped slightly from 4.3 to 4.1 and his WAR (wins above replacement) dipped from 11.6 to 9.4. But for Wall, 2014-15 was a big improvement on the year before: His 4.7 RPM and 12.1 WAR were both up from 2.2 and 8.3 last year, respectively.</p><p>The FiveThirtyEight simulations give the Raptors a 60 percent chance of winning this series but don’t see either team as a championship contender. They give the Raptors a 1 percent chance of winning the title and the Wizards an even smaller chance. In the 10,000 simulations we ran, the Raptors or Wizards won the championship only 108 times, the fewest of any of the eight first-round matchups. &#8212; <i>Benjamin Morris</i></p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74461&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/2015-nba-playoffs-preview/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/lebron.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/lebron.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Detroit Pistons v Cleveland Cavaliers</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/a5ffee70795912de4bc78ad6a72a447a?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">micahscohen</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/warriors-pelicans-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">warriors pelicans final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rockets-mavs-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">rockets mavs final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/clippers-spurs-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">clippers spurs final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/blazers-grizzlies-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">blazers grizzlies final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/hawks-nets-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">hawks nets final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cavs-celtics-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">cavs celtics final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/bulls-bucks-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">bulls bucks final</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/raptors-wizards-final.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">raptors wizards final</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Rays&#8217; Radical Reliever Experiment</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-rays-radical-reliever-experiment/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-rays-radical-reliever-experiment/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 10:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Arthur]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Baseball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Relief Pitching]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sabermetrics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tampa Bay Rays]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=74432</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[It’s not easy to be the Tampa Bay Rays these days. Long renowned as a sabermetrically-advanced team, the Rays have seen their strategies copied, imitated and stolen by other teams in search of a tactical edge. That’s why I’m watching the Rays closely this season. One of the most intriguing storylines of the 2015 season [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74432&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It’s not easy to be the Tampa Bay Rays these days. Long renowned as a sabermetrically-advanced team, the Rays have seen their strategies copied, imitated and stolen by other teams in search of a tactical edge. That’s why I’m watching the Rays closely this season. One of the most intriguing storylines of the 2015 season is how the Rays and other small-market teams cope with a league that’s increasingly analytics-savvy. It used to be that sabermetrics were the way small-market teams gained an edge over the competition. But now that analytics is becoming second nature in nearly every front office, its advantages are less pronounced. How will the Rays maintain their edge?</p><p>We saw the hint of an answer last Friday, when the Tampa Bay Rays tried something different. It was only a one-game experiment, but it was the kind of experiment that could hint at the post-post-Moneyball era. It started with a relief pitcher.</p><p>Faced with a depleted rotation &#8212; four starters were hurt &#8212; the Rays decided to have a “bullpen day” and let the relievers have the run of the place, opening the game, closing the game and pitching every inning in between. That’s nothing unusual, other than how early in the year it took place. But instead of deploying a reliever with starting experience &#8212; most likely Erasmo Ramirez &#8212; the team chose Steve Geltz, who hadn’t started a game since he was in high school.</p><p>The Rays’ <a href="https://twitter.com/aastleford/status/586362365408632832">unconventional choice</a> may have been strategically brilliant. While we can only speculate as to the reasoning behind the decision &#8212; the Rays declined my request for comment &#8212; there were two potential advantages to be gained by starting Geltz. By deploying Geltz before Ramirez, the Rays gave themselves the chance to essentially gain a DH in the NL and to keep Ramirez from having to face the toughest part of the opposing lineup.</p><p>Geltz pitched for only two innings, and then a pinch hitter, Mikie Mahtook, batted for him. Bypassing the starting rotation completely allowed the Rays to get the benefit of Mahtook’s bat without sacrificing any pitcher innings. When the replacement reliever came up, a pinch hitter hit for him too &#8212; no pitcher ever batted. The pinch hitters went <a href="http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/gameday/index.jsp?gid=2015_04_10_tbamlb_miamlb_1&amp;mode=box&amp;partnerId=LR_box">3 for 5</a>, but even if they had gone 0 for 5, they surely had a better chance of getting a hit than AL relief pitchers who don’t spend much time in the batting cages.</p><p>So that explains why they went straight to a reliever instead of a spot starter, but it still doesn’t tell us why the Rays decided to start Geltz in particular rather than Ramirez. It may have been an attempt to make the most of their threadbare bullpen. It comes down to matchups: Geltz is likely superior to Ramirez, with a<a href="http://www.fangraphs.com/projections.aspx?pos=all&amp;stats=pit&amp;type=steamer&amp;team=12&amp;lg=all&amp;players=0"> projected</a> 3.43 ERA for 2015 compared to Ramirez’s woeful 4.42. While no bullpen ace, Geltz stood a much better chance of surviving the first few innings intact.</p><p class="p1">That matters because the first inning is when teams score at the highest rate. The first inning sees 0.53 runs cross the plate on average, after which the average drops to 0.40 runs in the second before rebounding to an overall average of 0.46 runs per inning for the rest of the game.</p><p>Some sabermetricians<a href="http://www.beyondtheboxscore.com/2011/7/3/2255959/all-innings-are-not-created-equal-how-run-scoring-varies-by-inning"> believe</a> that more runs are scored in the first because pitchers have to face the top of the order. Competent managers fill the top four or five lineup spots with the best hitters, so pitchers are often running the gauntlet in the first inning.</p><p>This was especially true for the Miami Marlins, the Rays’ opposition last Friday. The top four hitters on the Marlins combine for a projected 121<a href="http://www.fangraphs.com/library/offense/wrc/"> Weighted Runs Created+</a> (wRC+), 12th best in the league. (wRC+ measures the total offensive output of a hitter, on a scale where 100 is roughly average and 120 is 20 percent better than average.)</p><p>And while the Marlins are geared for first-inning run production, the bottom of their lineup offers some easy outs. After the top four sluggers, their offense drops off dramatically: The next five best hitters combine for an 83.2 wRC+, which is almost as far below average as the top of the order is above it. The Marlins have the largest wRC+ gap between the top four and bottom five hitters in the league. Since the Marlins are uniquely unbalanced, the Rays would have risked getting their swingman, Ramirez, knocked out early if they had thrown him to the wolves of the first inning. Better to start with a guy who couldn’t go more than a couple innings anyway.</p><p>Now that I’ve told you how artful and clever the Rays’ maneuver was, I suppose it’s worth sharing the outcome of the game: The Rays lost. After Geltz was lifted in the second inning (he threw 35 pitches and gave up a run), Mahtook, the pinch hitter, promptly lined out, negating the pseudo-DH advantage. Later, Ramirez had to face the tough part of the order and gave up seven runs in his delayed “starting” stint. He lasted just two innings, undoing the second benefit the Rays’ gambit might have yielded. The Rays later managed to tie it up, but ultimately lost in extra innings.</p><p>But, as the saying goes, <a href="https://twitter.com/cantpredictball">you can’t predict baseball</a> (especially one individual game). The Rays’ failure underscores a problem with many modern attempts at in-game tactical<a href="http://www.baseballprospectus.com/article.php?articleid=25011"> optimization</a>: at best, their effect is <a href="http://www.baseballprospectus.com/article.php?articleid=26045">minor</a>. The best-laid plans of Rays and quants can be undone completely with an untimely lineout or bloop single. Still, it’s intriguing to watch the Rays mine every available source to save or gain a run or two here or there.</p><p>This unconventional strategy is emblematic of the cutting edge of modern, in-game sabermetrics. With every team from the small-market Rays to the moneyed Dodgers now employing a host of analysts, all the obviously beneficial tactical techniques are already in use. All that remains are the scraps. So even as the tactics have become unconventional, the margins have become thin and the advantages minute. For clever front offices like the Rays, negotiating the brave new world of saber-equality may mean relying on subtle, trifling tweaks like reliever-first outings.</p><p><b>CLARIFICATION (April 17, 1:00 p.m.): </b>An earlier version of this article said the most runs are scored in the few innings of a baseball game. It&#8217;s since been updated to more accurately reflect what the data makes clear: the first inning has the highest scoring rate of all innings.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74432&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-rays-radical-reliever-experiment/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap668477010714.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap668477010714.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Steven Geltz</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/7ac679b0d20830d2da9e5d0ce9eb99ba?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">chadwickmatlin</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Million Little Boxes</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/dan-feyer-american-crossword-puzzle-tournament/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/dan-feyer-american-crossword-puzzle-tournament/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 10:00:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Oliver Roeder]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[American Crossword Puzzle Tournament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Crossword Puzzles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Crosswords]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dan Feyer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Times Crossword Puzzle]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=74350</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[STAMFORD, Conn. &#8212; The contestants entered the ballroom to roaring applause, like it was a heavyweight prizefight. It was a crossword puzzle tournament. They took their places on stage in front of giant whiteboards with empty crossword grids. Dry erase markers in hand, noise-canceling headphones on their heads, the three men stood in proper puzzling [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74350&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>STAMFORD, Conn. &#8212; The contestants entered the ballroom to roaring applause, like it was a heavyweight prizefight. It was a crossword puzzle tournament.</p><p>They took their places on stage in front of giant whiteboards with empty crossword grids. Dry erase markers in hand, noise-canceling headphones on their heads, the three men stood in proper puzzling stance: right foot in front of left, marker arm crooked, clues in hand at convenient reading height.</p><p>“On your mark. Get set. Dan, begin,” said Will Shortz, New York Times crossword editor and tournament impresario. A tournament judge tapped Dan Feyer on the shoulder, and he began. Feyer, 37, is a professional musician and five-time defending champion.</p><p>Five seconds later: “Tyler, Howard, begin.” Tyler Hinman is the record-holder for youngest champion &#8212; he first won the tournament when he was 20, in 2005. He’s now 30, a grown-up prodigy. And while Howard Barkin has never won, this was his fourth trip to the finals.</p><p>The final puzzle was devilish. There’s wordplay aplenty. “Beat reporter?” is METRONOME. “Professional offers?” is ASSASSINS. “One who’s not committed?” is a SANEPERSON. And plenty of trivia. “Inventor of the spinning jenny” is HARGREAVES. “Four Holy Roman emperors” are OTTOS. “Rhododendron relative” is AZALEA. Whoever finishes first raises his hand and, assuming nothing is wrong in the puzzle, wins the American Crossword Puzzle Tournament.</p><p>After about seven minutes of solving, Feyer and Hinman were neck and neck, filling in their last boxes and checking that they hadn’t left anything blank. Hinman furiously erased a misentry with his left hand and rewrote with his right. Feyer, meanwhile, looked like <a href="http://media-1.web.britannica.com/eb-media/71/99371-004-7B01344F.jpg">Auguste Rodin</a>, calmly &#8212; maybe too calmly! &#8212; surveying his handiwork.</p><p>Then one of them raised his hand.</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">“I</span>t would be a better story if someone else would win,” Feyer said. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Feyer is the best crossword solver on the planet. We first met on a train platform in late March, preparing to go to Stamford for <a href="http://www.crosswordtournament.com/">the tournament</a>, which is the de facto national championship. Feyer has won every year for the last five years. He was heading north in pursuit of a record sixth consecutive title.</p><p>This was the 38th annual tournament, which was founded and is still run by Shortz, the elder statesman of crosswords. Jon Stewart has <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=ii_uTepBJh0C&amp;pg=PA91&amp;lpg=PA91&amp;dq=%22the+errol+flynn+of+crossword%22&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=edFoKXC-FY&amp;sig=bTWev1HtGZzsuzQBUBHWN_TlU08&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=4ywgVb_vA8P1ggTN5oGQCg&amp;ved=0CB4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=%22the%20errol%20flynn%20of%20crossword%22&amp;f=false">called him</a> “the Errol Flynn of crossword puzzling.”</p><p>Five hundred sixty-seven competitors were en route to the ballroom of the Stamford Marriott. They’d be joined by dozens of tournament judges in what is part competition, part convention and part reunion.</p><p>While most of us mere mortals might measure our solving time in cups of coffee or brunch courses &#8212; if we even complete the puzzles we start &#8212; the top solvers at the tournament measure it in split seconds. Points are awarded for correctness, of course, but also for speed.</p><p>Over the next 72 hours, Feyer will be challenged by the puzzle-solving elite as he tries to defend his title. (Not all the challengers will be human.) And he’ll face a final puzzle that he suspects may have been designed to dethrone him.</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">F</span>eyer came to crosswords late in life. If he ran across a New York Times Magazine in college, he’d take a crack at the Sunday puzzle. But as recently as 2006, he was oblivious to any of their finer points, he said.</p><p>“I didn’t know anything about them. I didn’t understand different constructors, I didn’t even really know the day of the week,” he said. Crosswords are well known to get tougher as the week goes on. Feyer had “a book of New York Times daily puzzles, and like every sixth one I wasn’t really finishing. It was like a year later I was like, ‘Ooh! Those were the Saturday puzzles.’”</p><p>The only way to get good at crosswords is to do lots of crosswords. And Dan Feyer has done lots of crosswords. By his back-of-the-envelope calculations, he’s spent “just” 4,000 hours of his life solving. Feyer started puzzling in earnest after seeing the crossword documentary “<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0492506/">Wordplay</a>” in the fall of 2007.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="4" href="#fn-4"><sup id="ss-4">4</sup></a> Now he routinely does 10 crosswords a day, and he used to regularly do 20. He’s done all of the nearly 8,000 puzzles in the New York Times’ online database, and routinely whips through puzzles from The Los Angeles Times, Newsday, The Chronicle of Higher Education, <a href="http://www.crossynergy.net/">CrosSynergy</a>, and others. There’s no guidebook to becoming a master crossworder, like <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-scrabble-dictionary-disrepects-the-game/">there is for, say, Scrabble</a>. The doing is the training.</p><figure id="attachment_74359"class="wp-caption alignnone full-width"style="max-width: 1024px"><img class="full-width size-full wp-image-74359" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross2.jpg?w=610" alt="Dan Feyer, puzzling."   /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text caption"><p>Dan Feyer, puzzling.</p><p class="credits">Oliver Roeder</p></figcaption></figure><p>By day, Feyer is a pianist and music director in San Francisco.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="5" href="#fn-5"><sup id="ss-5">5</sup></a> The tournament elite aren’t poets or Shakespeare scholars or <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copy_editing">copy editors</a>; for the most part they’re musicians, programmers and the mathematically inclined. Jon Delfin, a seven-time champion, is also a pianist. These folks can quickly make sense of a lot of coded information.</p><p>While he recently moved to the West Coast, Feyer spent 14 years in New York City &#8212; he still covets his 212 cell phone number. The city was central to fostering his crossword mastery: He did crosswords on the subway and in the orchestra pit when he was working an off-Broadway show. When he was starting out, he kept a stack of hard-copy puzzles he’d done in his apartment. It reached to roughly the height of a kitchen table. He even entered his first ACPT because of its convenient Brooklyn location. (The tournament moved back to its original Stamford home this year. Going into this year’s tournament, Feyer hadn’t won a title outside of New York.)</p><p>On the train, Feyer alerted me to some of his could-be challengers. They sound like the beginnings of an upstart think tank. There’s Joon Pahk, the Harvard physics preceptor and seven-time “Jeopardy!” <a href="http://j-archive.com/showplayer.php?player_id=7490">champion</a>; Andy Kravis, the Columbia Law grad who won $2.6 million on the now-defunct <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Million_Second_Quiz">Million Second Quiz</a>; and David Plotkin, the entomology &#8212; no, not etymology &#8212; Ph.D. student. Plotkin often matches Feyer on speed, and can sometimes outpace him. “He’s still on the rise,” Feyer said.</p><table class="viz" style="font-size:.75em;"><thead><tr><th class="first text" style="text-align:center;">YEAR</th><th class="number" style="width:30%;">FEYER</th><th class="number" style="width:30%;">HINMAN</th><th class="number" style="width:30%;">DR. FILL</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2005</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2006</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2007</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2008</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">45th</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2009</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">4th</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2010</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">4th</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2011</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">2nd</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">—</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2012</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">2nd</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">141st</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2013</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">3rd</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">92nd</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="text-align:center;">2014</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">1st</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">2nd</td><td class="number" style="width:30%;">67th</td></tr></tbody></table><p>There’s also a computer. Dr. Fill is a software program whose creator proved to be a terrible crossword solver, but a brilliant computer scientist.</p><p>And then there’s Hinman, a game designer for <a href="http://www.lumosity.com/">Lumosity</a>. Hinman plays the baby-faced, redheaded Apollo Creed to Feyer’s bearded, bald Rocky Balboa. I met him in the hotel lobby and he was &#8212; what else? &#8212; solving a crossword.</p><p>Before Feyer won five in a row, Hinman completed his own five-year run of victories. For the last decade, these are the only two people who have tasted crossword glory.</p><p>Hinman and Feyer are amiable enough &#8212; they’re in such a small circle of elite solvers that they almost have to be &#8212; but there’s a tension; a person can’t play second fiddle for too long without getting frustrated.</p><figure id="attachment_74391"class="wp-caption alignnone full-width"style="max-width: 1024px"><img class="full-width wp-image-74391 size-full" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross3.jpg?w=610" alt="CROSS3"   /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text caption"><p>Tyler Hinman, second from right, is disappointed after finishing a puzzle.</p><p class="credits">Oliver Roeder</p></figcaption></figure><p>&nbsp;</p><p>“He definitely enjoys his recent dominance, over me in particular,” Hinman said. “And there’s definitely a bloodthirsty streak that really wants to rip it away from him.”</p><p>Over the past few years, Feyer has been religious about tracking his solving times. On <a href="http://dandoesnotblog.blogspot.com/">his blog</a>, he posts a spreadsheet every day in which he records the time it takes him to solve various puzzles and invites other top solvers to add their own scores.</p><p>“Can I use the phrase ‘dick-measuring contest’?” Hinman asked. “I don’t feel like I need to do that. It’s for me, you know? If I want to prove it to people, this is where I go,” he said, gesturing to the tournament taking place around us.</p><p>And Hinman also lives in San Francisco, where Feyer recently moved. The town ain’t big enough for the both of ’em.</p><p>“That was really great, not to even be the top-ranked crossword puzzler in my own city,” Hinman joked. “We struck a bargain: I’m the best solver in the country east of <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Divisadero+St,+San+Francisco,+CA/@37.7864131,-122.4400331,13z/data=!4m2!3m1!1s0x808580c990439687:0xa3e7508fbea4e364">Divisadero Street</a>. Which is a pretty big swath, so I feel pretty good about that.”</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">S</span>ince late 2011, Feyer has finished over 95 percent of the New York Times puzzles in less than six minutes. He polishes off 88 percent of the Saturday puzzles &#8212; the hardest of the week &#8212; in less than five minutes.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74421 full-width" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/roeder-feature-crosswords-1.png?w=610" alt="roeder-feature-crosswords-1"   /></p><p>Let the speed wash over you. Grab a puzzle, any puzzle. Solve it. Compare your time to Feyer’s. I’d be lucky to find a pen in my desk drawer before he finished. For New York Times puzzles, his average solve times, Monday to Sunday, are 1:40, 1:55, 2:10, 3:09, 3:17, 4:03 and 5:38.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="6" href="#fn-6"><sup id="ss-6">6</sup></a></p><p><img class="wp-image-74414 alignright" style="margin-left:20px;" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/roeder-feature-crosswords-2.png?w=305&#038;h=434" alt="roeder-feature-crosswords-2" width="305" height="434" />To the exasperation of many tournament solvers, puzzles at the ACPT are still solved on paper, so Feyer will have to use his trusty <a href="http://www.bicworld.com/us/products/details/284/pencil-bic-matic">Bics</a> for the next few days. As the tournament approaches, Feyer and many other solvers switch from the computer (which is a more efficient way to tear through a bunch of puzzles) to writing it all down. It’s physical training more than anything. They have to train their eyes to scan a physical list of clues and train their hands to write fast while they process what’s coming next. But even on paper, Feyer flies.</p><p>Over drinks the night before the action begins, I tried to get some assembled crossword constructors to handicap the field for me. One thing was clear: Feyer was a huge favorite &#8212; although the group couldn’t agree whether his odds of winning were 3-to-5 or 4-to-5. Six others, including Hinman, had a shot, they said. The entire rest of the field? 70-to-1.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="7" href="#fn-7"><sup id="ss-7">7</sup></a></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">T</span>hat same night, Matt Ginsberg walked me deep into the belly of the Stamford Marriott, to a room with a sign on the door that read “Do Not Enter.” We entered.</p><p>The room was filled with machines &#8212; printers, scanners, laptops. On one particular machine lived Dr. Fill, the artificial intelligence crossword solver.</p><p>Ginsberg loaded up that week’s Saturday New York Times puzzle &#8212; the hardest day of the week, and one Dr. Fill had never seen. At the click of a button, the doctor got to work. The grid flickered and filled. Black, blue, purple and green letters came to life. In no more than five seconds, the grid was full. Ginsberg gave it a once over. It was correct.</p><p>Ginsberg, 59, is Dr. Fill’s creator and something like The Most Interesting Man in Crosswords. He got his Ph.D. in relativistic astrophysics from Oxford when he was 24, and he moved in the same circles as Stephen Hawking and Richard Feynman, he said. He runs three software companies. He’s a stunt pilot and amateur magician. He wrote a play that was produced. He created GIB, a former computer bridge world champion.</p><p>“Dr. Fill is my attempt to get revenge on the crossword constructors because I’m such an awful solver,” Ginsberg said.</p><p>Dr. Fill<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="8" href="#fn-8"><sup id="ss-8">8</sup></a> knows millions of crossword clues and answers.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="9" href="#fn-9"><sup id="ss-9">9</sup></a> It knows the title of every Wikipedia article, as well the articles’ lengths and when they were last edited &#8212; trendier is better in crossword answers. It’s memorized the complete works of Shakespeare, the Bible and Bartlett’s quotations. It knows the number of Google hits for 15 million different queries. While Ginsberg has an agreement with Shortz that Dr. Fill won’t access the Internet during competition, its offline database, compressed, is just shy of a gigabyte.</p><p>Here it is solving the 2013 tournament puzzles:</p><p><span class='embed-youtube' style='text-align:center; display: block;'><iframe class='youtube-player' type='text/html' width='610' height='374' src='http://www.youtube.com/embed/Ii7B1QcURsw?version=3&#038;rel=1&#038;fs=1&#038;showsearch=0&#038;showinfo=1&#038;iv_load_policy=1&#038;wmode=transparent' frameborder='0' allowfullscreen='true'></iframe></span></p><p>Ginsberg closed his MacBook Pro and put Dr. Fill to sleep until tomorrow. Also in that Marriott basement room was a stack of boxes, ready to be opened the next morning. In all caps, in bold red Sharpie, they read: “TOURNAMENT PUZZLES.” Dr. Fill had no idea.</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">I</span>t was a few minutes after 11 a.m. on Saturday. “Ready. Set. Go,” declared tournament impresario Shortz. We were underway.</p><p>With pencils at the ready, the 500-plus solvers flipped over their face-down puzzles. It sounded like Shortz had frightened a flock of birds out of the ballroom. But for the next 15 minutes, the competitors worked in library-like silence.</p><p>They’d do this seven times over the next two days &#8212; and an eighth time for the three finalists. All told, nearly one million little boxes would be filled in. For the majority of the contestants, it’s a lark &#8212; a chance to solve puzzles and be among friends. But for a handful, it’s also a mad dash to qualify for the final.</p><p>Some of the puzzles (No. 1 and No. 6) are easy &#8212; Monday- or Tuesday-level. Some (No. 3) are tougher. Some (No. 7) have larger grids, like the one you&#8217;d find in Sunday&#8217;s New York Times Magazine. And some (No. 5) are infamous. We’ll get to that.</p><p><img class="alignleft wp-image-74408 size-medium" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/140-1-scan.jpg?w=300&#038;h=298" alt="140-1-scan" width="300" height="298" /></p><p>Feyer brought his A-game. He ripped into Puzzle 1 (see image at left) like a kid on Christmas morning. The final time was 1:55, which was the first sub-two-minute puzzle ever completed in the tournament. It was less than a commercial break’s worth of time into the competition, and I’d already witnessed crossword puzzles’ equivalent of the first four-minute mile. (“Hashtag <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roger_Bannister#Sub-4-minute_mile">Bannister</a>,” Feyer joked.) To make sense of his time, I conducted a little experiment. I wrote my first name over and over again in the same grid, as fast as I could while maintaining legibility. It took me 1:40.</p><p>Shortz took the mic between rounds to introduce each puzzle and offer regular updates on Dr. Fill’s performance. When Shortz announced that Dr. Fill finished the first puzzle in under a minute, the humans groaned &#8212; some combination of resignation and annoyance. But, Shortz added, it finished with one mistake! An eruption of applause and laughter followed. Dr. Fill was unaware of the “Parks and Recreation” actress <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Retta">Retta</a> (47 across). Humans 1, Computer 0.</p><figure id="attachment_74392"class="wp-caption alignnone full-width"style="max-width: 1024px"><img class="wp-image-74392 size-full full-width" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross4.jpg?w=610" alt="CROSS4"   /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text caption"><p>Matt Ginsberg operates Dr. Fill, an artificial intelligence crossword puzzle solver.</p><p class="credits">Oliver Roeder</p></figcaption></figure><p>&nbsp;</p><p>This fraught relationship between humans and machine continued throughout the weekend. What makes crosswords difficult for Dr. Fill is precisely what makes them fun for humans &#8212; themes, gimmicks, neologisms and wordplay. And the humans &#8212; except for Ginsberg, perhaps &#8212; would like to keep it that way.</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">W</span>hile crossword construction is unavoidably linguistic, constructors these days rely heavily on data and programming. Take, for instance, Puzzle 5, always the hardest of the tournament. This year, Jeff Chen was the sadist behind the curtain. An aspiring novelist from Seattle, he runs the crossword database <a href="http://www.xwordinfo.com/">XWord Info</a> and has <a href="http://www.xwordinfo.com/Thumbs?author=Jeff+Chen">authored</a> or co-authored 37 New York Times puzzles.</p><p>Chen’s Puzzle 5 was titled “Attention, Newbies!” The conceit was adding new B’s (get it?) to familiar phrases. “Vocalist” became “vocab list,” “alloy” became “ballboy,” and so on. To find workable and interesting phrases like this, Chen wrote a Python script and applied it to his master word and phrase list. Using this program, he realized “caroms” could become “car bombs,” for example.</p><p>Chen’s master list has about 230,000 entries, each with a quality score attached.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="10" href="#fn-10"><sup id="ss-10">10</sup></a> The higher the score, the better it would be to include in a puzzle. Much of the scoring is automated, largely based on phrases’ previous puzzle appearances, but some take a human touch. Because three-, four- and five-letter words come up so often in puzzles, Chen decided to score them all by hand.</p><figure id="attachment_74393"class="wp-caption alignnone full-width"style="max-width: 1024px"><img class="wp-image-74393 size-full full-width" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross5.jpg?w=610" alt="CROSS5"   /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text caption"><p>Jeff Chen, standing in the back, watches competitors solve a puzzle he created.</p><p class="credits">Oliver Roeder</p></figcaption></figure><p>Constructors’ databases are their livelihoods. In his book “<a href="http://books.google.com/books/about/Gridlock.html?id=xQJT2iBMh4wC">Gridlock</a>,” Matt Gaffney described how <a href="http://www.xwordinfo.com/Thumbs?author=Frank+Longo">constructor</a> Frank Longo would mail a CD copy of his crossword entry database to an “undisclosed location” each month. It helped him sleep better at night.</p><p>Feyer wasn’t too bothered by Chen’s construction, though &#8212; the mind-melting puzzle took him a tidy 7:35. He remained in first. Dr. Fill finished fastest &#8212; but made one mistake. Oh, the humanity!</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">O</span>n Saturday evening, the day’s puzzling was complete and things were going according to script. Feyer was in first, with a three-minute lead over the field. He could take his time on the next morning’s Puzzle 7 and still coast into the final.</p><p>Hinman had struggled. He just missed the time cutoffs on Puzzles 4 and 5, finishing seconds too slow and not earning crucial bonus points. He’d have to tear through Puzzle 7 the next morning to qualify to face Feyer.</p><p>Dr. Fill, meanwhile, was faster than anyone &#8212; but error-prone. On Puzzle 3, constructed by <a href="http://www.sundaycrosswords.com/">Merl Reagle</a>, it made 12 mistakes, to the utter delight and hearty applause of the human solvers. But while it was nowhere near Feyer, it was on pace for its best-ever finish.</p><p>Feyer wasn’t concerned with who his competition would be in the final, but he was a bit concerned about the puzzle itself. Gretchen Margaroli, Feyer’s fiancée, told me later that Feyer had never worried about a final more than this year’s.</p><p>Feyer had a hunch &#8212; later proved right &#8212; that the final puzzle’s constructor was Byron Walden. Walden is a <a href="http://math.scu.edu/~bwalden/">professor</a> of math and computer science at Santa Clara University and is prone to using science-related crossword fill &#8212; not Feyer’s strongest suit. He prefers the constructor <a href="http://www.patrickblindauer.com/">Patrick Blindauer</a>, for example, and his penchant for musical theater clues.</p><p>In the tournament packet, Feyer also noticed that the final puzzle, the one that would decide the champion the next afternoon, would have only 60 words &#8212; a minuscule number. According to XWord Info, only 29 New York Times crossword puzzles have had fewer words during Shortz&#8217;s reign as editor. That meant it would be a wide-open grid with few black squares. Long words weaving through long words.</p><p>“This makes it a lot harder to solve,” Feyer said. “It also increases variance. It makes it easier to get stuck. They may be trying to take me down.”<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="11" href="#fn-11"><sup id="ss-11">11</sup></a></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><span class="drop-cap">H</span>inman had steeled himself by Sunday morning. His new motto: “<a href="https://twitter.com/thatpuzzleguy/status/581911638435098625">#SolveAngry</a>.” He flew through puzzles 6 and 7 faster than anyone in the field, meeting key time cutoffs. He earned enough points to make the final.</p><p>Right before his showdown with Feyer began, Hinman tweeted:</p><div class="embed-twitter"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" width="550"><p>Live by the second, die by the second. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ACPT?src=hash">#ACPT</a></p><p>&mdash; Tyler Hinman (@thatpuzzleguy) <a href="https://twitter.com/thatpuzzleguy/status/582229529386737664">March 29, 2015</a></p></blockquote><p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div><p>Feyer was still in first, and according to tournament rules, that earned him a five-second head start.</p><p>But surely that wouldn’t matter, right?</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><figure id="attachment_74394"class="wp-caption alignnone full-width"style="max-width: 1024px"><img class="wp-image-74394 size-full full-width" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross6.jpg?w=610" alt="CROSS6"   /><figcaption class="wp-caption-text caption"><p>Clockwise from top left, Tyler Hinman solving the final puzzle, Dan Feyer solving the final puzzle, and the crowd cheers them on.</p><p class="credits">Oliver Roeder</p></figcaption></figure><p>&nbsp;</p><p><span class="drop-cap">I</span>t was Sunday, lunchtime, and the three finalists &#8212; Feyer, Hinman and Barkin &#8212; were sequestered in an oversize storage closet. If they so much as used the restroom, they were required to have an escort. The tense atmosphere, strained small talk and unexplained Christmas tree in the corner turned this into a sort of surreal waiting room.</p><p>“We have an hour to shit our pants,” Feyer said.</p><p>Finally, there was a knock on the door.</p><p>The finalists entered the ballroom and climbed onstage. Grids were empty, markers were uncapped. “Is everybody ready?” Shortz asked.</p><p>After seven minutes of tense solving, we join the action in the video below.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="12" href="#fn-12"><sup id="ss-12">12</sup></a> Hinman is solving on the left, Feyer on the right:</p><p><a href="https://instagram.com/p/00f06gNLUU/" title="View on Instagram"><img src="http://instagr.am/p/am.com/media/?size=l" alt="Instagram Photo" /></a></p><p>&nbsp;</p><p>Feyer finished, gave his grid a once-over, and calmly raised his left hand. A second later, after filling in his last letter, Hinman shot his right hand up. He glanced at Feyer and realized he was too late.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="13" href="#fn-13"><sup id="ss-13">13</sup></a> The five-second head start had made the difference.</p><p>After a million boxes had been filled in, the champion was decided by just one. It was a record sixth consecutive victory for Feyer. And another silver for Hinman &#8212; his fourth in the last five years.</p><p>“I was on the floor after Georgia State <a href="https://vine.co/v/OYuxbmb0H1b">hit that shot</a>,” said sportswriter Adesina Koiki. “And that was nothing like this.”</p><p>I spotted Ginsberg, Dr. Fill’s creator, outside the hotel a few minutes later. Best final ever? I asked. “Best final ever,” he said. Dr. Fill did solve the final puzzle, but not on stage. It finished in just over two minutes &#8212; five minutes quicker than Feyer &#8212; but it made two mistakes. Nevertheless, the auto-solver still placed 55th, its best-ever result.</p><p>Feyer said it’d be a better story if someone else won. For once that weekend, the unflappable Dan Feyer was wrong.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74350&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/dan-feyer-american-crossword-puzzle-tournament/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/crossword-lede.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/crossword-lede.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">crossword lede</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/7ac679b0d20830d2da9e5d0ce9eb99ba?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">chadwickmatlin</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross2.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Dan Feyer, puzzling.</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross3.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">CROSS3</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/roeder-feature-crosswords-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">roeder-feature-crosswords-1</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/roeder-feature-crosswords-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">roeder-feature-crosswords-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/140-1-scan.jpg?w=300" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">140-1-scan</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross4.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">CROSS4</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross5.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">CROSS5</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/cross6.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">CROSS6</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Where Your State Gets Its Money</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-your-state-gets-its-money/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-your-state-gets-its-money/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 20:03:39 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ben Casselman]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Gambling Tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Income Tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sales Tax]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[State Tax Revenue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tax Revenue]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Taxes]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=74335</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Vermont and New Hampshire are similar in a lot of ways &#8212; they’re both small, heavily rural New England states that root for the Red Sox. But when it comes to taxes, they could hardly be more different. Vermont is one of the nation’s highest-tax states on a per capita basis; New Hampshire is the [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74335&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Vermont and New Hampshire are similar in a lot of ways &#8212; they’re both small, heavily rural New England states that root for the Red Sox. But when it comes to taxes, they could hardly be more different. Vermont is one of the nation’s highest-tax states on a per capita basis; New Hampshire is the lowest. Where they get that tax revenue is different, too: Vermont relies heavily on broad-based income and property taxes. New Hampshire gets much of its revenue from targeted taxes on cigarettes, gasoline and other items, as well as taxes on businesses.</p><p>Across the country, states vary widely in both the amount and the source of their tax revenue, as <a href="http://www.census.gov/govs/statetax/">new data from the Census Bureau</a> makes clear. States collected an average of about $2,700 per person in tax revenue in 2014. (That’s all taxes &#8212; regardless of who paid them &#8212; divided by total population, including children.) But there was a huge range, from $1,700 per person in New Hampshire to more than $8,000 per person in North Dakota.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="14" href="#fn-14"><sup id="ss-14">14</sup></a></p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74347 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/casselman-datalab-statetaxes.png?w=610&#038;h=987" alt="casselman-datalab-statetaxes" width="610" height="987" /></p><p>It might be surprising to see deep-red North Dakota at the top of the list. But that revenue isn’t coming from everyday citizens. It’s coming from oil companies: More than half of North Dakota’s tax revenue comes from so-called severance taxes, the result of the state’s oil boom. It’s a similar story in Alaska, which had the nation’s third-highest per capita tax revenue in 2014 (Vermont was No. 2). Severance taxes account for a whopping 72 percent of Alaska’s tax revenues.</p><p class="p1"><span class="s1">For states that can’t rely on oil booms, there’s tremendous variation in where they get their revenue.</span> Washington, for example, collects no income tax and relies on sales taxes for more than 60 percent of its tax revenue; neighboring Oregon is an almost perfect mirror image. Alaska and New Hampshire are the only states with<b> </b>neither an income nor a sales tax. (New Hampshire does tax dividends and interest.)<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="15" href="#fn-15"><sup id="ss-15">15</sup></a></p><p>There are several interesting outliers. Nevada, perhaps unsurprisingly, is the king of the “sin taxes,” thanks largely to the 13 percent of state revenue that comes from casinos and other “amusements.” Delaware, whose <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/07/01/business/how-delaware-thrives-as-a-corporate-tax-haven.html">business friendly laws</a> have made it home (at least on paper) to thousands of corporations, gets 40 percent of its revenue from corporate taxes and fees. And while property taxes are mostly a local matter in most states, Vermont gets more than a third of its tax revenue from property taxes.</p><p>A few less significant tidbits from the data: Wyoming leads the nation with $59 per person (man, woman and child) in hunting license revenue. New Hampshire is tops in tobacco revenue, at $162 per person. And North Dakota hits up its residents for the most in gas taxes: $308 per person.</p><p>To those of us in New York, meanwhile, it will come as no surprise that the Empire State collects a most-in-the-nation $2,176 per person in income tax.</p><p>See how your state ranks in major categories in our sortable table below, or see the full data set at the <a href="http://www.census.gov/govs/statetax/">Census Bureau website</a>. (The table below excludes some categories, so the rows won&#8217;t add up to 100 percent.)</p><hr /><div id="framediv"></div><script>jQuery(document).ready(function() {var framediv = new pym.Parent('framediv', '//projects.fivethirtyeight.com/mid-levels/state-taxes/index.html' + window.location.search + window.location.hash, {});jQuery('.fte-expandable').on('click', function () {framediv.sendMessage('width', false);});// listen to hash changes and modify URLframediv.onMessage('urlHash', function (value) {window.location.hash = value;});// listen to search changes and modify URLframediv.onMessage('urlSearch', function (value) {window.location.search = value;});});</script><hr /><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74335&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/where-your-state-gets-its-money/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/13db07ba6ab6ace11b892eaf664a2185?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">bencasselman</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/casselman-datalab-statetaxes.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">casselman-datalab-statetaxes</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Red Sox Are On The Wildest Roller-Coaster Ride In Modern MLB History</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-red-sox-are-on-the-wildest-roller-coaster-ride-in-modern-mlb-history/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-red-sox-are-on-the-wildest-roller-coaster-ride-in-modern-mlb-history/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 12:39:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Neil Paine]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Baseball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Boston Red Sox]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MLB]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=74283</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Before the 2015 season started last week, the Boston Red Sox were projected by both Fangraphs and Baseball Prospectus to win nearly 90 games this season, with the best expected record in the American League East according to each method. At a glance, that wasn&#8217;t incredibly notable. After all, Boston had won 90 or more [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74283&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Before the 2015 season started last week, the Boston Red Sox were projected by both <a href="http://www.fangraphs.com/blogs/division-preview-al-east/" target="_blank">Fangraphs</a> and <a href="http://www.camdenchat.com/2015/4/6/8343447/orioles-win-total-projections-vegas-pecota" target="_blank">Baseball Prospectus</a> to win nearly 90 games this season, with the best expected record in the American League East according to each method.</p><p>At a glance, that wasn&#8217;t incredibly notable. After all, Boston <a href="http://www.baseball-reference.com/teams/BOS/" target="_blank">had won</a> 90 or more games in 11 of the 17 seasons leading up to 2015. But the Red Sox are coming off a 91-loss, last-place season that ranked as <a href="http://www.baseball-reference.com/teams/BOS/#franchise_years::6" target="_blank">one of the worst in franchise history</a>. Since Major League Baseball expanded its schedule to 162 games in 1962, only 18 teams have transitioned from 90 losses in one season to 90 wins the next.</p><p>Then again, one of the last two teams<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="16" href="#fn-16"><sup id="ss-16">16</sup></a> to pull off that feat was &#8212; you guessed it &#8212; the Red Sox, who in 2013 won 97 games (and the World Series) just a season after losing 93. From 2011 to 2014, Boston&#8217;s win totals have moved by a total <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Absolute_value" target="_blank">absolute value</a> of 75 games, which ties the Seattle Mariners of 2007-10 for the highest such mark since 1962. Record-wise, the Red Sox have been all over the place.</p><p>Statistical projections haven&#8217;t been much of a guide to which Red Sox team will show up. In 2012, Baseball Prospectus projected the Red Sox to win 89 games; instead, they won 69. And remember 2013, that year they put up 97 wins? They were only projected to win 85. Then, in 2014, they were projected to win 88 games but in reality won 71. (This year, BP projected 88 wins, for whatever <em>that&#8217;s</em> worth.) To hear the projections tell it, little has changed about Boston&#8217;s talent over the past four years, despite the wild swings in wins and losses.</p><p>It&#8217;s not just a case of misfortune in the injury department, either, or a case of the &#8220;wrong&#8221; players otherwise playing. Even if we somehow knew ahead of time exactly which Red Sox players would play (and how much) before the season, a statistical projection would still have been wrong about the team&#8217;s records by an average of about 13 wins per season since 2012.</p><p>To measure just how much Boston&#8217;s individual performances varied from what could have been projected even if future playing time was known, I reconstructed Phil Birnbaum&#8217;s <a href="http://apbagames.com/wp-content/uploads/apbahistory/BRJ-2005.pdf" target="_blank">seminal study</a> (pdf) about player and team luck, this time using a <a href="http://www.tangotiger.net/marcel/" target="_blank">Marcel</a>-style projection of a player&#8217;s <a href="http://www.baseball-reference.com/about/war_explained.shtml" target="_blank">WAR runs above average</a>.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="17" href="#fn-17"><sup id="ss-17">17</sup></a></p><p>The basic gist is this: A player&#8217;s batting, baserunning,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="18" href="#fn-18"><sup id="ss-18">18</sup></a> fielding and pitching runs were projected as <a href="http://www.fangraphs.com/library/principles/counting-v-rate/" target="_blank">rate statistics</a> for each season based on his age<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="19" href="#fn-19"><sup id="ss-19">19</sup></a> and a weighted average of his performances over the previous three seasons. Those rates were then applied to his actual playing time during the season in question, to get the number of runs above average he&#8217;d have been expected to provide if you knew beforehand how much he&#8217;d play. The sum of a team&#8217;s individual projections could be construed as its talent, then, in the sense of how much production it theoretically had to work with on its roster.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74294 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/paine-datalab-redsox-2.png?w=610&#038;h=1489" alt="paine-datalab-redsox-2" width="610" height="1489" /></p><p>For the Red Sox, their hitters undershot expectations by a total of 140 runs at the plate in the team&#8217;s down 2012 and 2014 seasons, with 197 more runs of disappointment coming from Boston&#8217;s pitching staff. Conversely, the team was 88 runs better at the plate and 25 runs better on the mound than projected during the team&#8217;s championship-winning 2013 campaign. All told, these projections say there were about 85 wins of talent on both the 2012 and 2013 Red Sox &#8212; despite the two teams&#8217; <em>vastly</em> different results &#8212; and 81 wins of talent on last year&#8217;s 71-win Boston squad.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-74298 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/paine-datalab-redsox-1.png?w=610&#038;h=621" alt="paine-datalab-redsox-1" width="610" height="621" /></p><p>What could be driving these differences?<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="20" href="#fn-20"><sup id="ss-20">20</sup></a> It might be tempting to point to managerial influences (the 2012 Red Sox were infamously managed by the <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/sport/blog/2012/oct/04/boston-red-sox-bobby-valentine-fired" target="_blank">much-maligned</a> Bobby Valentine), but <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/most-managers-are-headed-to-the-hall-of-mediocrity/" target="_blank">very few managers</a> in baseball history have shown any persistent ability to exceed these types of expectations. The uneasy answer might instead simply be luck, the same reason we have to <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/how-to-predict-mlb-records-from-early-results/" target="_blank">regress teams&#8217; records</a> heavily <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regression_toward_the_mean" target="_blank">toward the mean</a> to better estimate their true talent.</p><p>Most great teams combine luck with skill. According to the method outlined above, the typical World Series winner since 1962 possessed about 88 wins of talent but posted an actual win total of 96 on average. Conversely, few teams with poor records are ever quite as bad as the loss column suggests. The 2012 and 2014 Red Sox are particular outliers in this regard, but even the average team to win between 69 and 71 games in a season since 1962 had 77 wins of talent on its roster.</p><p>What does that mean for this year&#8217;s Red Sox, then? They&#8217;ve <a href="http://www.baseball-reference.com/teams/BOS/2015-schedule-scores.shtml" target="_blank">started the season 6-3</a>, which is good for first place in the AL East, but that doesn&#8217;t mean much fewer than two weeks into the season. Perhaps more telling is that most teams who undershoot their talent projections by a wide margin tend to improve a lot the following season.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="21" href="#fn-21"><sup id="ss-21">21</sup></a> Also, a team&#8217;s preseason talent projection from the year before tells you more about how it&#8217;ll do this season than its actual record from the previous season itself.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="22" href="#fn-22"><sup id="ss-22">22</sup></a> Between regression to the mean, superior projections and a fast start, the Red Sox are <a href="http://www.fangraphs.com/coolstandings.aspx" target="_blank">currently on pace</a> for 89.7 wins, according to Fangraphs&#8217; playoff odds simulations.</p><p>So to the extent that you can say anything for sure about the Red Sox these days, they&#8217;re tracking for another good season in 2015. And if it holds up, it would continue the franchise&#8217;s ongoing roller-coaster ride in the standings, completing the most extreme up-and-down-and-up-and-down-and-up-again stretch in modern MLB history.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=74283&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-red-sox-are-on-the-wildest-roller-coaster-ride-in-modern-mlb-history/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/nationals-red-sox-baseball-featured.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/nationals-red-sox-baseball-featured.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Nationals Red Sox Baseball</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://0.gravatar.com/avatar/356adb5db97ece0eba870611c079f604?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F0.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">sportsrefneil</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/paine-datalab-redsox-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">paine-datalab-redsox-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/paine-datalab-redsox-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">paine-datalab-redsox-1</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>New York&#8217;s Complicated Teacher Evaluation Proposal Is The Exception, Not The Rule</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-yorks-complicated-teacher-evaluation-proposal-is-the-exception-not-the-rule/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-yorks-complicated-teacher-evaluation-proposal-is-the-exception-not-the-rule/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2015 11:53:37 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hayley Munguia]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gates Foundation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Measures of Effective Teaching Project]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Teacher Evaluations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[T-Vals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Teacher Evaluations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Test Scores]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73981</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This week, millions of students across New York will begin taking the state&#8217;s annual round of standardized tests, starting with the Common Core English Language Arts test on Tuesday. But it’s not just students’ performance that will be graded &#8212; teachers are being evaluated just as much, if not more. While 30 states require test [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73981&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This week, millions of students across New York will begin taking the state&#8217;s annual round of standardized tests, starting with the Common Core English Language Arts test on Tuesday. But it’s not just students’ performance that will be graded &#8212; teachers are being evaluated just as much, if not more.</p><p>While 30 states require test scores to be considered in teacher evaluations, New York stands out in just how much weight it may soon be putting on the scores. In March, the state legislature approved a hotly contested measure backed by Gov. Andrew Cuomo that takes away district control of teacher evaluations and could allow the education commissioner to use test scores to determine as much as half of a teacher’s evaluation, giving test scores and observations the same weight. Legislators <a href="http://www.capitalnewyork.com/article/albany/2015/04/8565544/education-officials-role-evaluations-appears-limited">seem confused</a> about the practical implications of the bill and are investigating the language. The education department has until June 30 to finalize the evaluation system.</p><p>The bill is just the latest in a flurry of teacher evaluation policy reforms that have been implemented across the country in recent years. New York had already <a href="http://www.gothamgazette.com/index.php/about/888-cuomo-tries-out-a-new-role-the-education-governor">reformed</a> its teacher evaluations in 2012, but after <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/01/nyregion/cuomo-gets-deals-on-tenure-and-evaluations-of-teachers.html">96 percent</a> of teachers were deemed effective last year, Cuomo is looking to rework the system again.</p><p>According to the Center on Great Teachers and Leaders at American Institutes for Research, a nonprofit behavioral and social science research organization, every state but California has developed plans for a new system to be implemented at some point between 2011 and 2019. These new models of teacher evaluation include state tests, district tests, classroom observations, student and parent surveys, self-assessments from teachers, lesson-plan reviews, measures of professional learning, and more.</p><p>All these attempts to reform teacher evaluations are happening as the research on how best to assess teacher quality remains in its earliest stages, and teachers and students are being affected with every shift in policy. “We’re in the Wright brothers stage,” said Jim Hull, a senior policy analyst for the Center for Public Education. “We’re getting these policies in the air, and they’re not designed to be as effective as they probably could be. There’s still a lot to learn.”</p><p>One New York principal, Carol Burris of South Side High School in Rockville Centre, who is also a fellow with the nonprofit National Education Policy Center and who has been an <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/answer-sheet/wp/2015/04/03/what-the-thoughtless-n-y-government-just-did-to-teachers/">outspoken opponent</a> of high-stakes testing, said that New York’s policy will affect students for the worse.</p><p>“It puts the test scores in a pre-eminent position, which will have a bad effect on kids,” she said. “We’ve already seen the effects that this has &#8212; a narrowing of curriculum and teaching to the test &#8212; and that will just become an even more prevalent practice.”</p><p>In Burris’s ideal world, test scores would play at most a secondary role in teacher evaluations. “I think the role of test scores should be outside the model. Teachers should be evaluated by their principal, and if for some reason that evaluation is way off the mark, then decent test scores can be used as a form of protection to challenge that evaluation,” she said.</p><p>Hull understands her anxiety about the new policy. “There’s definitely room for concern when you talk about 50 percent of an evaluation being based on test scores,” he said. “Especially if it’s not a high-quality assessment [of the students] and doesn’t assess a broad range of knowledge.” The quality of student tests is a particularly sticky issue in New York, where the first two years of Common Core <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/bw/articles/2014-08-15/common-core-new-york-test-scores-show-little-improvement">test results</a>, which have shown outsized gaps between demographic groups, have done little to ease <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/answer-sheet/wp/2014/08/17/a-painful-analysis-of-new-common-core-tests-and-the-n-y-results/">critics’ concerns</a> that scoring well on the tests requires skills that are irrelevant to the subject matter being tested.</p><p>There are competing views on the best way to approach incorporating student test scores into teacher evaluations. The model that’s currently accepted as the most accurate is known as the “value-added model” because it’s supposed to measure exactly how much of a student’s progress made over the course of the year is thanks to her teacher. It compares each student’s test scores to their own past scores and to other students’ scores. “It’s not perfect, but there is no other measure as good as [the value-added model],” Hull said. “But that’s not to say that other measures shouldn’t be used as well. You really want to have multiple measures of student outcomes.”</p><p>The <a href="http://www.metproject.org/">Measures of Effective Teaching (MET) Project</a>, the magnum opus of teacher-evaluation studies &#8212; every expert I spoke with on this topic pointed me to it &#8212; confirms the idea that student growth, often in the form of test scores, should be included in evaluations, along with other metrics. The project, which was funded by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, was a three-year research partnership between 3,000 teacher volunteers and dozens of independent research teams who together developed and tested multiple measures of teacher evaluations to help better identify effective teaching. It didn’t recommend one specific model, given that every district has its own needs, but it did highlight the fact that “heavily weighting a single measure may incentivize teachers to focus too narrowly on a single aspect of effective teaching and neglect its other important aspects.”</p><p>The project found that an evaluation model heavily weighting standardized test scores was more effective than other models in predicting improvements in how students performed on those tests, but was the least predictive of how students performed on supplemental higher-order tests (usually given at the district or school level), and also produced the least reliable results, based on year-to-year consistency in teachers’ scores. Here are the results, from the project&#8217;s <a href="http://www.metproject.org/reports.php">research brief</a>:</p><p><a href="http://www.metproject.org/reports.php" target="_blank"><img class="size-full wp-image-73996 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-13-15-05-04.png?w=610&#038;h=732" alt="Screenshot 2015-04-13 15.05.04" width="610" height="732" /></a></p><p>Texas is in the process of overhauling its evaluation system, and it will value test scores at a maximum of 20 percent &#8212; even less than the MET Project’s Model 4. Specifically, Texas’s new model will count “student growth” as 20 percent of a teacher’s score. “But there are four options that districts have for measuring student growth, and just one of them ties back to test scores,” said Tim Regal, the director of educator evaluation and support for the Texas Education Agency.</p><p>Texas’s new model, which will replace a 17-year-old system, is in its pilot year and being implemented in 57 districts. Next year, it will expand to 200 districts before the final statewide implementation in 2016-2017.</p><p>But rather than just changing the way different factors are weighted, the overhaul is an attempt to transform the way teacher evaluations are used and understood. “Right now, when you talk to teachers in Texas about appraisal, they have a certain mindset because it’s always been used just to determine renewal and nonrenewal,” he said, referring to the common practice of using evaluations solely to determine which teachers to let go. “The only thing that mattered was their score. A lot of our focus during the pilot year has been about how to change that mindset to be about a process of professional development and growth for all teachers.”</p><p>In addition to the 20 percent of teachers’ evaluations that will be based on student growth, another 70 percent will be based on observations from principals, assistant principals and other campus leaders, and 10 percent will be based on self-assessment.</p><p>According to Angela Minnici, director of the Center on Great Teachers and Leaders, a change in mindset about how teacher evaluations are used is necessary. “We need to move away from thinking about evaluation systems as only ways to dismiss underperformers,” she said. “We really should be thinking about evaluations as a source of power and investment for moving teachers to a better level of performance overall.”</p><p>While New York is putting even more emphasis on testing, most states are moving toward a system more like the one in Texas.</p><p>“States are definitely making a big step forward,” Hull said. “Over a short period of time, evaluation systems have gone basically from an exercise in bureaucracy to being given immediate feedback and information on how to improve performance. That type of feedback is how we get the best doctors, best lawyers, and it’s also how we’ll get the best teachers.”</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73981&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/new-yorks-complicated-teacher-evaluation-proposal-is-the-exception-not-the-rule/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/538_teachers.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/538_teachers.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">538_TEACHERS</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/b978cfde8b5b6d6d1580f80b271c8e7f?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">landonsimone</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-13-15-05-04.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Screenshot 2015-04-13 15.05.04</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Official 2016 GOP Field Gets Its First Real Contender: Marco Rubio</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/marco-rubio-announcement-2016/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/marco-rubio-announcement-2016/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 10:18:10 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Harry Enten]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Presidential Election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Republican Primary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jeb Bush]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marco Rubio]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rand Paul]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scott Walker]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ted Cruz]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73844</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Florida Sen. Marco Rubio&#8217;s campaign, which officially kicks off Monday, has so far attracted paltry support from Republican voters, according to polls in Iowa and New Hampshire, as well as nationally. He&#8217;s down near Chris Christie! Yet, when we talk about him in the FiveThirtyEight office, we usually put Rubio in the top tier, in [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73844&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Florida Sen. Marco Rubio&#8217;s campaign, which officially kicks off Monday, has so far attracted paltry support from Republican voters, according to polls in <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-iowa-presidential-republican-primary" target="_blank">Iowa</a> and <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-new-hampshire-presidential-republican-caucus" target="_blank">New Hampshire</a>, as well as <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-national-gop-primary" target="_blank">nationally</a>. He&#8217;s down near Chris Christie! Yet, when we <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/watch-totally-subjective-presidential-odds-ny1-edition/" target="_blank">talk about him in the FiveThirtyEight office</a>, we usually put Rubio in the top tier, in front of everyone except Jeb Bush and Scott Walker, the two candidates at the top of the polls.</p><p>Why? Rubio is both <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/marco-rubio-the-electable-conservative/" target="_blank">electable and conservative</a>, and in <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/marco-rubio-and-the-pareto-frontier/" target="_blank">optimal proportions</a>. He&#8217;s <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/romney-and-the-gops-five-ring-circus/" target="_blank">in a position</a> to satisfy the GOP establishment, tea party-aligned voters and social conservatives. In fact, Rubio&#8217;s argument for the GOP nomination looks a lot like Walker&#8217;s, and Rubio is more of a direct threat to the Wisconsin governor than he is to fellow Floridian Bush.</p><p>To win a presidential nomination, you need to make it past the party actors (i.e., elected officials and highly dedicated partisans). You can have all the strong early poll numbers in the world (hello, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sJ9bqcWYsjk" target="_blank">Rudy Giuliani</a>), and your candidacy can still fail if party bigwigs come out against you. Rubio has a real chance of surviving &#8212; or even winning &#8212; the invisible (or endorsement) primary.</p><p>Rubio doesn&#8217;t have the flaws the other two official GOP candidates have. He&#8217;s a hawk on foreign policy (with an 89 percent conservative foreign policy score in <a href="https://votesmart.org/candidate/evaluations/1601/marco-rubio#.VSiQ4pTF9TN" target="_blank">National Journal&#8217;s vote ratings</a>), so he&#8217;ll be able to avoid the pitfalls of <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/rand-paul-is-losing-his-fathers-base/" target="_blank">Rand Paul&#8217;s candidacy</a>. And Rubio <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/lets-be-serious-about-ted-cruz-from-the-start-hes-too-extreme-and-too-disliked-to-win/" target="_blank">isn&#8217;t anywhere near as extreme</a> as Ted Cruz and has not alienated his fellow senators, so we shouldn&#8217;t expect mainstream party members coming out of the woodwork to stop Rubio. But he&#8217;s a solid conservative; statistical ideological ratings put him right in line with the average Republican in the 113th Congress.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73899 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-rubio-21.png?w=610&#038;h=967" alt="enten-datalab-rubio-2" width="610" height="967" /></p><p>Unlike another <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/post-politics/wp/2014/05/07/marco-rubio-does-spanish-language-tv-ad-for-cory-gardner/" target="_blank">Chamber of Commerce favorite</a>, <a href="http://townhall.com/columnists/michellemalkin/2014/12/17/jeb-bush-the-us-chamber-of-commerces-waterboy-n1932835/page/full" target="_blank">Bush</a>, who is expected to face resistance from the right of his party, Rubio was a <a href="http://www.teapartyexpress.org/4852/senator-marco-rubio-tea-party-choice-for-vice-president" target="_blank">darling of the tea party movement</a> in 2010. Although Bush and Rubio are both from Florida, Rubio&#8217;s record suggests that he could be a more conservative alternative to Bush, rather than a direct challenger to Bush for the moderate/liberal wing of the GOP.</p><p>Remember when Rubio ran Charlie Crist out of the party in his 2010 Senate bid? He did so thanks, in part, to support from conservative stalwarts <a href="http://liveshots.blogs.foxnews.com/2010/03/31/coburn-endorsing-marco-rubio-for-senate/?test=latestnews" target="_blank">Sen. Tom Coburn</a>, <a href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0609/23754.html" target="_blank">Sen. Jim DeMint</a> and <a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/washwire/2010/01/06/floridas-rubio-gets-endorsement-from-wisconsins-rep-ryan/" target="_blank">Rep. Paul Ryan</a>. Rubio has a 93 percent lifetime rating from <a href="https://votesmart.org/candidate/evaluations/1601/marco-rubio#.VSlPxJTF9TO" target="_blank">the Club for Growth</a>. He has a real chance of winning the backing of <a href="http://www.weeklystandard.com/blogs/marco-rubio-winning-mike-lee-primary_915297.html" target="_blank">tea party leaders such as Sen. Mike Lee</a>. He has even managed to <a href="http://www.glennbeck.com/2015/03/30/does-marco-rubio-have-a-chance-in-2016/" target="_blank">stay acceptable to Glenn Beck</a>.</p><p>And yet, Rubio has some decent electability credentials. He isn&#8217;t <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/latino-decisions/rubios-standing-with-lati_b_7041734.html" target="_blank">polling particularly well</a> with Hispanics right now, but Rubio pulled <a href="https://www.americanprogress.org/issues/immigration/news/2012/01/27/10928/the-top-10-things-you-should-know-about-floridas-latinos-and-immigrants/" target="_blank">40 percent of the non-Cuban Hispanic vote</a> in a three-way contest in his 2010 Senate bid. Mitt Romney, by contrast, won only 27 percent among them in the <a href="http://www.foxnews.com/politics/elections/2014/exit-polls?year=2012&amp;type=president&amp;filter=US" target="_blank">two-way presidential race</a> in 2012.</p><p>In part because he did so well with Hispanics, Rubio vastly over-performed most other Republican senatorial candidates in 2010, as well as those who ran in 2014.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="23" href="#fn-23"><sup id="ss-23">23</sup></a> Rubio won his race by 11 percentage points more than you would have expected <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-election-map-alone-doesnt-explain-the-2014-republican-wave/" target="_blank">controlling for the past presidential vote of the state and incumbency</a>.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="24" href="#fn-24"><sup id="ss-24">24</sup></a></p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73911 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-marcorubiopotential.png?w=610&#038;h=714" alt="enten-datalab-marcorubiopotential" width="610" height="714" /></p><p>Only nine of 72 Republican senatorial candidates in 2010 or 2014 performed better against expectations than Rubio. That&#8217;s a stronger claim to electability than Walker has made in Wisconsin (and Walker&#8217;s claim is <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/scott-walkers-electoral-record-is-just-as-impressive-as-it-looks/" target="_blank">pretty strong</a>).</p><p>So Rubio can credibly tell Republican activists that he&#8217;s one of them ideologically and tell the establishment that he can win. But making it through the invisible primary merely means Rubio will get a chance in the actual primary, and he&#8217;s barely registering any support &#8212; doesn&#8217;t that tell us something?</p><p>It may, but there is other polling data that suggests Rubio has a lot more upside than the other potential candidates polling in the mid-single digits with him.</p><p>For one, Republican voters like Rubio. In an average of live interview polls taken since the beginning of the year, Rubio&#8217;s average net favorable rating is second only to Mike Huckabee&#8217;s.</p><table class="viz"><thead><tr><th class="first text" style="width:40%;">CANDIDATE</th><th class="number">AVERAGE NET FAVORABLE RATING</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Mike Huckabee</td><td class="number">+43</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#f0f0f0;"><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Marco Rubio</td><td class="number">+34</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Scott Walker</td><td class="number">+33</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Ted Cruz</td><td class="number">+31</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Jeb Bush</td><td class="number">+29</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Ben Carson</td><td class="number">+28</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Rand Paul</td><td class="number">+27</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Rick Perry</td><td class="number">+26</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Rick Santorum</td><td class="number">+14</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;">Chris Christie</td><td class="number">+3</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Rubio and Christie may be neck-and-neck in horse race polls, but GOP voters <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/everybody-hates-chris-christie/" target="_blank">don&#8217;t like</a> Christie. They like Rubio.</p><p>You&#8217;ll note, though, that Rubio isn&#8217;t blowing away the rest of the field. He has a similar net favorable rating to a lot of the other candidates. Indeed, as I found previously, having a strong early net favorable rating <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/10-of-the-biggest-presidential-primary-busts-in-recent-history/" target="_blank">doesn&#8217;t guarantee future success</a>. It&#8217;s one thing to like a candidate, and it&#8217;s another to want him to be president. Being well-liked is a necessary but not sufficient condition to winning a presidential primary.</p><p>But what separates Rubio from a number of his well-liked opponents, including Cruz, Paul and Rick Perry, is that Republican voters have signaled more of a willingness to vote for Rubio.</p><p><img class="show-mobile show-tablet alignnone wp-image-56783 size-full" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-12-12-28-52.png?w=610" alt=""   /></p><table class="viz full hide-mobile hide-tablet"><thead><tr><th class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">CANDIDATE</th><th class="number" style="width:25%;">CAN SUPPORT</th><th class="number" style="width:25%;">CAN’T SUPPORT</th><th class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">DIFFERENCE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Jeb Bush</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;">50%</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;">27%</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+24</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Scott Walker</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">33</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">9</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+24</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#f0f0f0;"><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Marco Rubio</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">38</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">17</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+22</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Mike Huckabee</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">44</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">25</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+20</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Ben Carson</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">30</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">13</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+18</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Ted Cruz</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">30</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">22</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+9</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Rand Paul</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">35</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">27</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+8</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Rick Perry</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">32</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">26</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+6</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Bobby Jindal</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">20</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">16</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+4</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Rick Santorum</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">28</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">26</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">+3</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Chris Christie</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">28</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">43</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">-15</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:40%;padding-left:4px;">Lindsey Graham</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">10</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:.6em;">33</td><td class="number" style="width:25%;padding-right:4px;">-23</td></tr></tbody></table><p>According to an average of <a href="http://cbsnews2.cbsistatic.com/hub/i/2015/03/27/650245c4-9301-464e-8cae-e948a2462c42/522e50ae276fa04e8f5497966e6a2d2c/would-you-consider-voting-for-each-for-the-republican-nomination-1.jpg" target="_blank">2015 CBS News surveys</a>, 38 percent of Republican voters say they could support Rubio, compared with just 17 percent who say they couldn&#8217;t. The margin (+22 percentage points due to rounding) between those puts Rubio right alongside Bush and Walker. In other words, Rubio is up with the top candidates again. In a campaign in which no one is consistently polling above 15 percent, Rubio remains a candidate who looks like he can be a lot of people&#8217;s second or third choice.</p><p>Part of the reason Rubio remains so well-liked is that he is ideologically in line with Republican voters, just as he is with Republican officeholders. According to <a href="https://today.yougov.com/publicopinion/archive/?year=&amp;month=&amp;category=economist" target="_blank">March YouGov polling</a>, Republicans are more likely to say Rubio is &#8220;about right&#8221; on the issues than &#8220;too conservative&#8221; or &#8220;not conservative enough&#8221; by a 34 percentage point margin.<br /><img class="show-mobile show-tablet alignnone wp-image-56783 size-full" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-12-12-41-30.png?w=610" alt=""   /></p><table class="viz full hide-mobile hide-tablet"><thead><tr><th class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">CANDIDATE</th><th class="number" style="width:20%;">TOO CONSERVATIVE</th><th class="number" style="width:20%;">NOT CONSERVATIVE ENOUGH</th><th class="number" style="width:20%;">ABOUT RIGHT</th><th class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">ABOUT RIGHT EDGE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Scott Walker</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;">6%</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;">9%</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;">54%</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+40</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#f0f0f0;"><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Marco Rubio</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">6</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">11</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">50</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+34</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Rick Perry</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">11</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">8</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">51</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+33</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Bobby Jindal</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">4</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">42</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+32</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Ben Carson</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">45</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+31</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Ted Cruz</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">16</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">46</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+24</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Mike Huckabee</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">14</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">10</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">47</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+24</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Rick Santorum</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">14</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">9</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">44</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+21</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Rand Paul</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">14</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">13</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">45</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+18</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Carly Fiorina</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">3</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">11</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">29</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+15</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">John Kasich</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">2</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">9</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">25</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+14</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Jeb Bush</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">6</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">31</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">45</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">+9</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Lindsey Graham</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">22</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">24</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">-5</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:24%;padding-left:4px;">Chris Christie</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">4</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">36</td><td class="number" style="width:20%;padding-right:.6em;">33</td><td class="number" style="width:16%;padding-right:4px;">-8</td></tr></tbody></table><p>That&#8217;s the second-widest margin of any Republican candidate. Rubio is well ahead of Bush and just behind Walker.</p><p>Which brings us back to Rubio&#8217;s path to the GOP nomination: It looks a lot like Walker&#8217;s &#8212; pulling together conservative and establishment Republicans. Neither Rubio nor Walker has the appeal with moderate and liberal Republicans that Bush does at this moment. Here are net favorability numbers from a <a href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/182000/huckabee-bush-well-known-well-rated-among-republicans.aspx" target="_blank">March Gallup survey</a> (which were similar to <a href="http://www.quinnipiac.edu/news-and-events/quinnipiac-university-poll/2016-presidential-swing-state-polls/release-detail?ReleaseID=2182" target="_blank">state-level Quinnipiac polls</a>):</p><p><a href="http://www.gallup.com/poll/182000/huckabee-bush-well-known-well-rated-among-republicans.aspx"><img class="alignnone wp-image-73876 size-full" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/1yqdqluyy0q7go6vvcm6la.png?w=610" alt="1yqdqluyy0q7go6vvcm6la"   /></a></p><p>Moderates and liberals make up about 30 percent of Republican primary voters. They account for closer to 35 percent in states that President Obama carried in 2012. These states hold half of the Republican primary delegates, as The New York Times&#8217;s Nate Cohn <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/01/upshot/the-surprising-power-of-blue-state-republicans.html" target="_blank">previously pointed out</a>. It&#8217;s how John McCain and Romney were able to win the GOP nomination despite weak standings among very conservative voters.</p><p>So while the press usually lumps Rubio and Bush together because they&#8217;re both from Florida, Rubio and Walker are more likely to be in direct competition. Current polling aside, Bush&#8217;s bumper sticker reads something like &#8220;Very electable, and kind of conservative.&#8221; Rubio&#8217;s and Walker&#8217;s read &#8220;Conservative, and electable.&#8221;</p><p>In the early stages of the 2016 campaign, Walker has gotten more mileage out of that argument. But Rubio is in a good position to take advantage of any Walker missteps. Of the candidates to officially declare so far, Rubio is the first with a good shot at the nomination.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73844&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/marco-rubio-announcement-2016/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rubiocandidatehp.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rubiocandidatehp.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">RubioCandidateHP</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/a26fad23742e906c3f881ae92c6178cb?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">poughies</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-rubio-21.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-datalab-rubio-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-marcorubiopotential.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-datalab-marcorubiopotential</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-12-12-28-52.png" medium="image" />

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-12-12-41-30.png" medium="image" />

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/1yqdqluyy0q7go6vvcm6la.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">1yqdqluyy0q7go6vvcm6la</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Clinton Begins The 2016 Campaign, And It&#8217;s A Toss-up</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/clinton-begins-the-2016-campaign-and-its-a-toss-up/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/clinton-begins-the-2016-campaign-and-its-a-toss-up/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 19:10:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nate Silver]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Democratic Primary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Presidential Election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hillary Clinton]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73852</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[There’s already plenty of bad punditry regarding the chances of Hillary Clinton &#8212; who officially announced her candidacy on Sunday &#8212; to become the 45th president. You can find Democrats boasting about their “blue wall” in the Electoral College and how hard this will make it for any Republican to win. Or Republicans warning that [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73852&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There’s already plenty of bad punditry regarding the chances of Hillary Clinton &#8212; who officially announced her candidacy on Sunday &#8212; to become the 45th president. You can find Democrats boasting about their “blue wall” in the Electoral College and how hard this will make it for any Republican to win. Or Republicans warning that the Democratic Party rarely wins three elections in a row.</p><p>Most of this analysis is flimsy. So is the commentary about the ups-and-downs in early swing state polls. And when you see some pundit declaring a minor misstep to be a “game changer,” find someone else to follow on Twitter.</p><p>The truth is that a general election win by Clinton &#8212; <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-hillary-clinton-steamroller-rumbles-to-life/">she’s very likely to become the Democratic nominee</a> &#8212; is roughly a 50/50 proposition. And we’re not likely to learn a lot over the rest of 2015 to change that. Here’s why:</p><p><b>Incumbency and Obama’s Approval Rating.</b> Start with the fact that there’s no incumbent president running. There actually haven’t been a lot of cases that precisely meet the circumstances voters will face next year: Barack Obama, assuming he serves out the rest of his term, will become just the fifth president limited by the 22nd Amendment from seeking an additional term in office.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="25" href="#fn-25"><sup id="ss-25">25</sup></a> This is slightly different from the case where an incumbent voluntarily declines to run again.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="26" href="#fn-26"><sup id="ss-26">26</sup></a> Still, <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-white-house-is-not-a-metronome/">the evidence we have</a> from presidential elections and from other contexts like gubernatorial elections is that these cases default to being toss-ups.</p><p>Clinton’s chances will be affected by Obama’s popularity as he exits office. The relationship between the popularity of the previous president and the performance of the new nominee from his party isn’t perfect &#8212; Al Gore (narrowly) lost in 2000 despite Bill Clinton’s popularity, for example &#8212; but it certainly matters some, especially given that Clinton served in Obama’s cabinet.</p><p>However, Obama currently has an approval rating of about 45 percent, and a favorability rating of 48 percent &#8212; about average, in other words. If those numbers decline into the low 40s or climb into the 50s, they could matter more, producing either a “hangover effect” or “halo effect” for Clinton. But don’t bet on this: Obama’s approval ratings have been <a href="http://www.realclearpolitics.com/epolls/other/president_obama_job_approval-1044.html">extraordinarily stubborn for most of his presidency</a>, rarely deviating much from the mid-40s.</p><p><b>The Economy. </b>I’d warn against simplistic economic “fundamentalism,” the notion that the economy is pretty much the <i>only</i> thing that matters. We’ll save the technical discussion for later, but because of a problem known as <a href="http://people.duke.edu/~mababyak/papers/babyakregression.pdf">overfitting</a>, statistical models that claim to make remarkably precise predictions about election outcomes from economic variables alone (without looking at polls) <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/models-based-on-fundamentals-have-failed-at-predicting-presidential-elections/">have a mediocre track record</a>.</p><p>Still, the economy will matter a lot to voters, and a better economy will help Clinton, the candidate from the incumbent party. As Byron York <a href="http://www.washingtonexaminer.com/will-2016-really-be-a-foreign-policy-election/article/2562793">points out</a>, you should be wary of claims that 2016 will be a “foreign policy election.”<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="27" href="#fn-27"><sup id="ss-27">27</sup></a></p><p>Like Obama’s approval ratings, however, the performance of the American economy has been about average recently. GDP <a href="https://www.bea.gov/newsreleases/national/gdp/gdpnewsrelease.htm">grew by 2.4 percent in 2014</a>, adjusted for inflation, close to the historical average. Furthermore, we know relatively little about what economic growth will look like a year from now, when the general election campaign heats up. Historically, economists have shown almost no ability to predict the rate of economic growth more than six months in advance.</p><p><b>The Electoral College And The “Emerging Democratic Majority.” </b>What about that “blue wall” &#8212; the supposed advantage that Democrats hold in the Electoral College?</p><p>Mostly, the “blue wall” was the effect of Obama’s success in 2008 and 2012, not the cause of it. If the economy had collapsed in the summer of 2012, Obama would probably have lost the election, and most of those blue states would have turned red.</p><p>It’s true that in both elections, the “<a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/arizona-is-probably-not-a-swing-state/">tipping-point state</a>” (in both years it was Colorado) was slightly more Democratic than the country as a whole. That implies Obama would have won if the popular vote had been very close. But it would have had to be very close indeed &#8212; within a percentage point or two.</p><p>That advantage is small enough that it might have been the result of circumstances peculiar to Obama and his campaign. If Clinton has an ever-so-slightly different coalition &#8212; say more working-class whites vote for her but fewer African-Americans &#8212; this small advantage could evaporate or reverse itself. (The Electoral College favored Republicans as recently as 2000, after all.) The same might be true if she isn’t as effective as Obama at mobilizing voters in swing states.</p><p>Another theory &#8212; the so-called “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Emerging-Democratic-Majority-John-Judis/dp/0743254783">Emerging Democratic Majority”</a> &#8212; holds that demographic trends favor the Democratic Party. We’ll have a lot more to say about this theory between now and next November, but it’s probably dubious too.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="28" href="#fn-28"><sup id="ss-28">28</sup></a> As Sean Trende has <a href="http://www.realclearpolitics.com/articles/2015/02/04/emerging_democratic_majority_--_rip_125492.html">pointed out</a>, it relies on a selective reading of the evidence &#8212; emphasizing 2012, 2008 and 2006 but ignoring 2014, 2010, and 2004. Perhaps more important, predictions made on the premise of “emerging” majorities have a miserable track record: Republicans were bragging about their “permanent” majority in 2004, for instance, only to get their butts kicked in 2006 and 2008.</p><p><b>Clinton and the Republican Candidates. </b>The factors I’ve described so far are sometimes referred to as the “fundamentals” &#8212; those things that matter regardless of the candidates and their campaigns. The closer these basic factors are, the more difference the candidates could make.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="29" href="#fn-29"><sup id="ss-29">29</sup></a></p><p>Nonetheless, the candidates matter less in U.S. presidential elections than in just about any other type of electoral contest. The reason is that the arduous, 50-state nomination process (and the <a href="http://www.cjr.org/campaign_desk/how_to_understand_the_invisibl.php?page=all">“invisible primary” before it</a>) screens out most candidates who would be huge liabilities to their party. An underqualified or unvetted or politically extreme or profoundly unpopular candidate might win one primary or caucus, but voters and the political parties will move to stop him in his tracks after that, as <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2012/03/12/life-of-the-party-ryan-lizza">Republicans did to Newt Gingrich in 2012</a>.</p><p>Consider <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-the-fivethirtyeight-senate-forecast-model-works/">the three measurable factors</a> that our U.S. Senate model uses to evaluate candidates. One of them is their qualifications on a 4-point scale as measured by their highest elected office, where the highest rating goes to those candidates previously elected as governors or senators. Almost all presidential candidates &#8212; including Hillary Clinton and the viable Republican candidates this cycle &#8212; rate as extremely well qualified by that standard.</p><p>Another factor is fundraising, which is important unto itself, but also as a proxy for a candidate’s organizational strength. We’re not breaking any news here, but Clinton and the Republican nominee are going to raise oodles of money &#8212; probably in excess of $1 billion each, beyond what <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2012/12/barack-obama-mitt-romney-both-topped-1-billion-in-2012-84737.html">Obama and Mitt Romney did in 2012</a>. That’s well past the point of diminishing returns. The candidates may struggle to make good use of all the money they’ve raised, in fact, and if one brings in 10 or 20 percent more than the other, it’s not likely to matter very much at the margin.</p><p>The third factor is a candidate’s ideology as measured on a left-right scale. “Extreme” candidates (like Barry Goldwater) suffer an electoral penalty, while moderate ones (like Dwight Eisenhower) usually perform well.</p><p>But nominees like Goldwater (or George McGovern) are rare. So are those like Eisenhower, for that matter. Usually a party nominates a candidate <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/marco-rubio-the-electable-conservative/">closer to the median</a> of its voters and elected officials.</p><p>That’s part of why Clinton is such a safe bet to be the Democratic nominee. Her political positions are essentially those of a “generic Democrat.” She’s neither a true centrist, nor extremely far to the left, so <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/hillary-clinton-doesnt-have-a-problem-on-her-left/">she’s not especially vulnerable to a challenge</a> from either flank of her party.</p><p>Republicans have a choice between <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/jeb-bush-president-republican-primary-2016/">more moderate and more conservative candidates</a>. Jeb Bush’s positions might be just moderate enough to give Republicans a slight advantage next November, other factors held constant, while Scott Walker’s might be conservative enough that they could harm Republicans.</p><p>But the positions of the Republican candidates are likely to converge toward one another. Bush, in the primaries, will seek to prove his conservative credentials, while Walker, should he become the frontrunner after the first few primaries and caucuses, will work to reassure GOP elites that he’s an “electable” alternative and not the next Goldwater. By next November, the difference might boil down to the equivalent of couple of percentage points on the general-election ballot. It could matter in an a close election, but not one where the fundamentals have shifted strongly to one party by then.</p><p>Finally we can look at what the polls say right now. If you’re going to do this, you should take the polls with whole tablespoons full of salt. And it’s probably best to look at the favorability ratings for each candidate rather than head-to-head polls, since favorability polls allow voters to say they don’t know enough about the candidates to have formulated an opinion. (Head-to-head polls taken this far out from the election will tend to favor candidates like Clinton with strong name recognition, by contrast.)</p><p>In the chart below, I’ve compiled favorability rating averages for each candidate based on polls conducted since Jan. 1.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="30" href="#fn-30"><sup id="ss-30">30</sup></a> The chart plots the candidates in two dimensions: the vertical axis indicates how popular the candidate is (how much the candidate’s favorable rating exceeds his or her unfavorable rating) while the horizontal axis plots how well-known the candidate is.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73866" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/silver-feature-hrcpop-new.png?w=610&#038;h=732" alt="silver-feature-hrcpop-NEW" width="610" height="732" /></p><p>Hillary Clinton is extremely well-known, but her favorability ratings are now only break-even: 46 percent favorable and 45 percent unfavorable. These are nearly identical to President Obama’s ratings, which are 48 percent favorable and 46 percent unfavorable.</p><p>Clinton’s ratings are down sharply from her tenure as Secretary of State. However, as we’ve been <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-hillary-clinton-would-be-strong-in-2016-its-not-her-favorability-ratings/">warning Democrats for a long time</a>, a <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/a-predictable-decline-in-hillary-clintons-popularity/">lot of this was predictable</a>. Clinton’s numbers have often been about break-even when she’s been a highly partisan figure &#8212; during the early stages of the 2008 campaign, for example &#8212; and better only when she’s been above the fray of day-to-day partisan politics.</p><p>Break-even favorability ratings don’t look so bad, however, when compared to some of the alternatives. Vice President Biden’s are net-negative, for instance. On the Republican side, Walker and Marco Rubio aren’t all that well-known yet, but their ratings are also about break-even. Chris Christie’s are terrible (28 percent favorable, 46 percent unfavorable). Jeb Bush’s are quite poor too. His unfavorable rating is already as high as Clinton’s, 45 percent, but his favorable rating is just 31 percent.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="31" href="#fn-31"><sup id="ss-31">31</sup></a></p><p>Clinton is so well-known, in fact, that it’s almost as if voters are dispensing with all the formalities and evaluating her as they might when she’s on the ballot next November. About half of them would like to see her become president and about half of them wouldn’t. Get ready for an extremely competitive election.</p><p><strong>Editor&#8217;s note:</strong> <em>This article was updated to reflect Clinton&#8217;s announcement of her candidacy this afternoon.</em></p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73852&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/clinton-begins-the-2016-campaign-and-its-a-toss-up/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/84455352.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/84455352.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">84455352</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/ba67d4b1aeec9f6635774b8410a317ad?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">nrsilver</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/silver-feature-hrcpop-new.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">silver-feature-hrcpop-NEW</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How FiveThirtyEight&#8217;s NCAA Tournament Forecasts Did</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-ncaa-tournament-forecasts-did/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-ncaa-tournament-forecasts-did/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 20:09:27 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Reuben Fischer-Baum]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2015 Men's NCAA Tournament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015 NCAA Basketball Tournament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2015 NCAA Women's Basketball Tournament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Basketball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[March Madness]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73825</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[We love making predictions at FiveThirtyEight, but we know that they’d be meaningless if we didn’t check to see how accurate they turned out to be. Over the past month, we forecast every NCAA college basketball game for the women’s and men’s tournaments, updating our numbers almost a hundred times as 132 teams were pared [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73825&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We love making predictions at FiveThirtyEight, but we know that they’d be meaningless if we didn’t check to see how accurate they turned out to be. Over the past month, we forecast every NCAA college basketball game for the women’s and men’s tournaments, updating our numbers almost a hundred times as 132 teams were pared down to two champions.</p><p>So let’s relive the NCAA tournament not through “One Shining Moment” but through a vetting of FiveThirtyEight’s forecasts.</p><h2>MEN’S</h2><p>One way to assess our accuracy is to pit ourselves against Vegas, the gold standard of sports predictions. We took our final probabilities from before each March Madness game &#8212; converted to a point spread<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="32" href="#fn-32"><sup id="ss-32">32</sup></a> &#8212; and used them to place hypothetical bets on the <a href="http://www.vegasinsider.com/college-basketball/scoreboard/scores.cfm/game_date/04-6-2015">final Vegas line</a>. For example: Vegas had Texas at -2.5 over Butler, but we gave the Longhorns just a 54 percent chance of winning. This implied a line of -1, so we bet on Butler to cover. (<a href="http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/recap?gameId=400785346">And we won!</a>)</p><p>Here’s how our hypothetical bets did through the round of 64. Note that if our implied line matched Vegas’s exactly, we wouldn’t place a hypothetical bet on that game.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73824" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-1.png?w=610&#038;h=1168" alt="rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-1" width="610" height="1168" /></p><p>A 17-13 record is strong &#8212; enough to maybe make some money. More importantly, our model performed well when it differed significantly from Vegas. In seven games, marked in gray above, our model had a perceived edge of three points or more &#8212; a sizable gap in forecasting between the two basketball forecasts. In these games, our bets went 5-2.</p><p>After the round of 64, things didn’t go so great:</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73822" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-2.png?w=610&#038;h=1044" alt="rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-2" width="610" height="1044" /></p><p>Through these last 31 games, our spreads tracked Vegas <i>very</i> closely. We disagreed on the favorite just once (correctly picking Notre Dame to beat Wichita State), and there were no games where our perceived edge was three points or greater. In 21 games, our edge was half a point to a point, a relatively small advantage to place actual money on. Luckily we didn’t, as these hypothetical bets went 6-15. When our perceived edge was greater than a point, our bets went 3-3. That gave us an overall March Madness record of 26-31, with 10 no bets.</p><p>Betting against Vegas is great, but we’re aware that many of our readers stopped looking at our forecasts the moment they turned in their bracket. This means that the performance of our first, pre-tourney predictions was especially important.</p><p>If you built a men’s bracket using <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/the-odds-of-a-perfect-march-madness-bracket/">only FiveThirtyEight’s initial numbers</a>, you would have gotten 70 percent of the games correct. It’s hard to tell if we should be happy with that number &#8212; it’s certainly not going to impress <a href="http://games.espn.go.com/tournament-challenge-bracket/2015/en/entry?entryID=1587514">sammyholtz16</a> or anyone else on top of the ESPN Bracket Challenge leaderboard. A better way to assess probabilistic forecasts is a calculation known as a Brier score, which we can use to compare ourselves to other models like <a href="http://kenpom.com/blog/index.php/weblog/entry/ncaa_tournament_log5">Ken Pomeroy</a>’s, <a href="http://sagarin.com/sports/cbsend.htm">Jeff Sagarin</a>’s,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="33" href="#fn-33"><sup id="ss-33">33</sup></a> <a href="http://thepowerrank.com/visual/NCAA_Tournament_Predictions">The Power Rank</a>, <a href="http://espn.go.com/blog/statsinfo/post/_/id/103785/ncaa-tournament-viewed-via-bpi">ESPN BPI</a>, and <a href="https://www.numberfire.com/ncaab/march-madness">numberFire</a>.</p><p>A short, but still mathy, example of how Brier scores work: Our initial predictions gave No. 6 seed Xavier a 26.5 percent chance of advancing to the Sweet 16, while Ken Pomeroy’s log5 model gave them a 24.8 percent chance.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="34" href="#fn-34"><sup id="ss-34">34</sup></a> Xavier did advance, so our Brier score for that event was (1 &#8211; 0.265)^2, or 0.54, while Pomeroy scored a 0.57. Being closer to zero is better, so we were (slightly) more accurate for that prediction.</p><p>We calculated each model’s average Brier score for each round of the tournament. To benchmark all the results, we added a “chalk” model that assigned a 100 percent probability to the higher seed winning each game.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="35" href="#fn-35"><sup id="ss-35">35</sup></a> Here are the results, including an overall average:</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73821" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-3.png?w=610&#038;h=372" alt="rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-3" width="610" height="372" /></p><p>FiveThirtyEight came in third, and all the models beat the chalk. Our forecasts started strong, with the lowest Brier score for the round of 64. We assigned the highest probabilities to Georgia State’s and Dayton’s upset chances &#8212; 24 and 38 percent, respectively. The Dayton pick &#8212; calculated before the play-in games began &#8212; was a coup for <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/march-madness-predictions-2015-methodology/">the geographic component of our calculations</a>: Dayton had a home game against Boise State for its play-in, and then had to travel just a <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/Columbus,+OH/Dayton,+OH/@39.9005267,-83.7263052,9z/data=!4m13!4m12!1m5!1m1!1s0x883889c1b990de71:0xe43266f8cfb1b533!2m2!1d-82.9987942!2d39.9611755!1m5!1m1!1s0x884080d5aedd1403:0xa640e392f20e4ce4!2m2!1d-84.1916069!2d39.7589478">few dozen miles</a> for its round of 64 matchup.</p><p>NumberFire came in second, leaning heavily on favorites throughout the tournament. This killed numberFire early on &#8212; it gave Iowa State a 96 percent change over UAB &#8212; but this confidence paid off as the bracket became chalkier and chalkier. Other models, like Pomeroy’s, consistently underrate the favorites’ probability of winning, leading to weaker Brier scores.</p><p>Once Duke started rolling, The Power Rank pulled away. Among the models we looked at, the site gave the Blue Devils the highest probability of advancing to the Sweet 16 (88 percent), Elite Eight (71 percent), Final Four (46 percent), and Championship game (27 percent). Duke was given a 12 percent chance to win the title at the tournament’s start. To compare, our model and numberFire each put Duke at six percent, while BPI had it at just three percent. Given that Duke is traditionally <a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/sports/sports_nut/2010/03/how_to_win_your_ncaa_pool.html">undervalued</a> in bracket pools, fans who built their brackets on The Power Rank’s numbers likely had a pretty good tournament.</p><h2>WOMEN’S</h2><p>Vegas might be the gold standard of sports predictions over in the men’s tournament, but unfortunately we couldn’t find a <a href="http://www.sportbet.com/lines/basketball_college_women">reliable source of betting lines</a> for the women’s NCAA tournament (nor could we find them for any games other than the championship). This year was the first time we made <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-we-made-our-forecasts-for-the-womens-ncaa-tournament/">March Madness predictions for the women’s tournament</a>, and we knew there would be less data available for making the women’s model.</p><p>Because there’s no major alternative we can use to judge our forecast, we were left with an imperfect measure: Did it do better than if we had just picked favorites? It’s a draw! if you built a women’s bracket using <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/the-odds-of-a-perfect-march-madness-bracket/">only FiveThirtyEight’s initial numbers</a>, you would have gotten 84 percent of games correct, compared to … 84 percent if only favorites won.</p><p>But Brier scores can help settle the tie. Here’s what happened when we compared our probabilistic results to the all-favorites picks.</p><p><img class="alignleft wp-image-73820" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-4.png?w=305&#038;h=396" alt="rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-4" width="305" height="396" /></p><p>Our model outperformed the chalk model in the opening rounds (as it should have), but in some matchups it did more than just outperform. We gave DePaul, a No. 9 seed, a 77 percent chance of upsetting Minnesota, a No. 8 seed, and the Blue Demons won by seven. In the Spokane region, we gave Gonzaga a 48 percent chance of upsetting George Washington, nearly a coin toss, and sure enough, Gonzaga made a strong run all the way to the third round.</p><p>We didn’t predict the Dayton upset of Kentucky (we gave them only a 22 percent chance of making it that far), and by the Sweet 16, the chalk model began to outperform us. Perhaps our model’s biggest oversight was placing too much weight on South Carolina making it to the national championship over Notre Dame, which was due in part to the geographical advantages we assigned to their playing in Greensboro. Both teams were No. 1 seeds, but Notre Dame was the higher 1 seed. We gave South Carolina a 40 percent chance of making it to the finals, and Notre Dame only a 34 percent chance. This was a very chalky tournament to begin with, however, with heavy, heavy favorites like <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/dont-expect-a-no-16-seed-to-win-in-the-womens-tournament-ever-again/">UConn and the rest of the No. 1 seeds dominating the bracket.</a></p><p>In total, however, we outperformed the chalk, and we’re pleased with how our first women’s March Madness predictions did. We’ll have more data to build on for next year, plus a better understanding of the <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-we-made-our-forecasts-for-the-womens-ncaa-tournament/">fat-tailed distributions</a> particular to the women’s tournament &#8212; and we’ve got a pretty good idea of <a href="http://bigstory.ap.org/article/20cd6a29cc85407da1ecc53930937993/uconn-women-will-be-favorites-win-11th-title-next-year">who our model will favor again</a>.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73825&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fivethirtyeights-ncaa-tournament-forecasts-did/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap745125968450.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap745125968450.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">NCAA Duke Wisconsin Final Four Basketball</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://0.gravatar.com/avatar/c7715a603259ff561084804363b33a07?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F0.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">reuben538</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-1</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-3.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-3</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-4.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">rfbmcann-feature-madness-accuracy-4</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Hillary Clinton Steamroller Rumbles To Life</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-hillary-clinton-steamroller-rumbles-to-life/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-hillary-clinton-steamroller-rumbles-to-life/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 18:26:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Harry Enten]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Democratic Primary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Presidential Election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Endorsements]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hillary Clinton]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Invisible Primary]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73661</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Let&#8217;s do something a little unusual. Instead of going through all the reasons that Hillary Clinton is so likely to win the Democratic nomination (and she is) and then tucking a caveat-laden paragraph at the bottom of this article, let&#8217;s start with one big caveat: Presidential elections aren&#8217;t baseball. They take place just once every [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73661&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Let&#8217;s do something a little unusual. Instead of going through all the reasons that Hillary Clinton is so likely to win the Democratic nomination (and she is) and then tucking a caveat-laden paragraph at the bottom of this article, let&#8217;s start with one big caveat:</p><p>Presidential elections aren&#8217;t baseball. They take place just once every four years, so we don&#8217;t have thousands of at-bats to analyze. Clinton, who will reportedly officially announce her campaign Sunday, could lose the primary. Perhaps there&#8217;s some scandal we&#8217;re unaware of. Perhaps she&#8217;ll have to drop out because of some health issue. Maybe Martin O&#8217;Malley will straight-up beat her; stranger things have &#8230; well, OK, maybe not.</p><p>Clinton&#8217;s primary campaign is by far the most dominant for a non-incumbent president since nominations began to be determined by caucuses and primaries in 1972. The best predictors we have all say Clinton is going to be the Democrats&#8217; 2016 presidential nominee.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="36" href="#fn-36"><sup id="ss-36">36</sup></a></p><h2>Endorsements</h2><p>Clinton has pretty much already won the endorsement primary, the all-important pre-voting race to lock up party establishment support.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="37" href="#fn-37"><sup id="ss-37">37</sup></a> Last time she ran for president, Clinton lost the endorsement primary. By this point in the 2008 campaign, she had <a href="http://www.gwu.edu/~action/2008/cands08/endorse08el.html" target="_blank">only one senator</a> endorse her publicly. According to a <a href="http://edition.cnn.com/2015/02/02/politics/hillary-clinton-2016-endorsements/" target="_blank">CNN</a> count in February, Clinton has already secured endorsements from 27 of 46 Democratic senators. That&#8217;s a ton of support so early in the campaign.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73793 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-hillaryclintondominant-2.png?w=610&#038;h=424" alt="enten-hillaryclintondominant-2" width="610" height="424" /></p><p>Clinton&#8217;s strength is unique. Most years, the campaign is barely underway in early April. And in the years in which endorsements come quickly, elected officials usually wait at least until a candidate formally declares.</p><p>But here&#8217;s the more amazing thing about those 27 endorsements: That total would still be impressive even if no one else were to endorse Clinton. Only George W. Bush&#8217;s 2000 machine picked up more senator endorsements (33), and it took him the <em>entire</em> primary campaign. He didn&#8217;t reach 27 until November 1999. The only other two campaigns to come close to 27 were Bob Dole&#8217;s in 1996 and Al Gore&#8217;s in 2000; each picked up 26. Like Bush, Dole and Gore rolled over the competition.</p><p>Just as important as the number of endorsements is where they are coming from on the ideological spectrum. Clinton is earning endorsements from the left, center and right of the Democratic caucus. In this kernel density function of endorsers plotted against <a href="http://www.voteview.com/SENATE_SORT113.HTM" target="_blank">their congressional voting record</a>, we see that the senators who have endorsed Clinton look ideologically very similar to those who haven&#8217;t (<a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/lets-be-serious-about-ted-cruz-from-the-start-hes-too-extreme-and-too-disliked-to-win/" target="_blank">more negative scores</a> are more liberal):</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73795 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-hillaryclintondominant-1.png?w=610&#038;h=506" alt="enten-hillaryclintondominant-1" width="610" height="506" /></p><p>Unlike in 2008, Clinton has her left flank well-covered. She has the endorsement of liberal stalwarts such as Sens. Tammy Baldwin and Elizabeth Warren. Clinton also has the endorsement of moderate senators such as Joe Manchin and Claire McCaskill.</p><h2>Polling</h2><p>Clinton also has the most dominant poll numbers of any candidate at this point in the election cycle in the modern era. Early primary polling is not the be-all and end-all, but candidates who are polling very well across the board early tend to win their nominations. In an average of polls taken since the beginning of the year, Clinton is above 50 percent in <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-iowa-presidential-democratic-primary" target="_blank">Iowa</a>, <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-new-hampshire-presidential-democratic-caucus" target="_blank">New Hampshire</a> and <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-national-democratic-primary" target="_blank">nationally</a>. No other non-incumbent in the modern era has done that in the first half of the year before the primaries began.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73798 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-hillaryclintondominant-3.png?w=610&#038;h=567" alt="enten-hillaryclintondominant-3" width="610" height="567" /></p><p>It&#8217;s only in Iowa where Clinton doesn&#8217;t have an outright claim to the strongest polling average in recent history. But she&#8217;s still in a strong position at 62 percent &#8212; about where Gore was in early 1999. Gore went on to win Iowa with 63 percent of the vote and every single primary after that. Dole was the only candidate besides Clinton and Gore to hit at least 40 percent in early Iowa, New Hampshire and national polling. He won 44 states and easily took the 1996 GOP nomination.</p><p>Clinton is in a far stronger position than she was last time around. Back in 2008, she was trailing in early Iowa polls. She earned only a third of the vote in early New Hampshire polls and was below 40 percent nationally.</p><p>Nor are there any real holes in her support. According to <a href="https://today.yougov.com/publicopinion/archive/?year=&amp;month=&amp;category=economist" target="_blank">YouGov polling</a> conducted in March, 68 percent of Democrats believe she is &#8220;about right&#8221; ideologically.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="38" href="#fn-38"><sup id="ss-38">38</sup></a> Only 12 percent of Democrats would not consider voting for her, according to a February <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/news/election-2016-who-would-you-consider-voting-for/" target="_blank">CBS News</a> survey. In the latest <a href="http://maristpoll.marist.edu/wp-content/misc/usapolls/us150301/2016/Complete%20March%202015%20McClatchy_Marist%20Poll_2016_Tables.pdf#page=4" target="_blank">Marist College survey</a>, she earns more than 60 percent among liberal,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="39" href="#fn-39"><sup id="ss-39">39</sup></a> moderate and conservative Democratic primary voters.</p><p>Clinton&#8217;s early polling tells the same story as the endorsements: Democrats don&#8217;t seem open to other options. It&#8217;s not a situation likely to tempt a formidable Democrat to jump into the race. Which brings us to the third point &#8230;</p><h2>The (lack of) competition</h2><p>Clinton looks like she&#8217;ll have perhaps four competitors for the nomination: <span>O&#8217;Malley, </span>Lincoln Chafee, Bernie Sanders and Jim Webb. Sanders is the only one who currently holds elected office. Only O&#8217;Malley has ever been elected as a Democrat to any office for more than one term.</p><p>Chafee, who is from Rhode Island, has never won a Democratic primary for any office. He served in the U.S. Senate as a Republican and was an independent governor. The only time he could have won a Democratic primary (for governor), he <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/09/04/why-lincoln-chafees-decision-not-to-run-for-reelection-is-more-good-news-for-democrats/" target="_blank">bowed out</a> because he faced a bruising campaign. He frequently had <a href="http://wpri.com/2014/09/08/gov-chafee-endorses-clay-pell-for-ri-governor/" target="_blank">an approval rating</a> of around 30 percent in blue Rhode Island.</p><p>O&#8217;Malley&#8217;s turn as governor of deep-blue Maryland went so far south that a Republican succeeded him, which is a fate that didn&#8217;t even befall Chafee. As I&#8217;ve <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/martin-omalley-shouldnt-try-to-out-liberal-hillary-clinton/" target="_blank">written previously</a>, O&#8217;Malley&#8217;s ideological record and donor base do not suggest that he can successfully challenge Clinton from the left.</p><p>Although Sanders caucuses with Democrats in the Senate, he&#8217;s a self-described socialist. If he ends up running, he&#8217;ll win some plaudits on the left, but that&#8217;s about it.</p><p>Webb, like Chafee, is a former Republican with little history with the Democratic Party. That might be forgivable if he were actually a mainstream Democrat, but he was the <a href="http://www.voteview.com/SENATE_SORT112.HTM" target="_blank">fourth-most-conservative Democratic senator</a> during his final term in Congress.</p><p>When you look at the board, there is no Barack Obama waiting in the wings. Warren has endorsed Clinton and has given every indication that she is not going to run.</p><p>At this point, Clinton&#8217;s path to the nomination looks easier than anything we&#8217;ve seen before.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73661&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-hillary-clinton-steamroller-rumbles-to-life/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/hillarycandidatehp.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/hillarycandidatehp.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">HillaryCandidateHP</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/a26fad23742e906c3f881ae92c6178cb?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">poughies</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-hillaryclintondominant-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-hillaryclintondominant-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-hillaryclintondominant-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-hillaryclintondominant-1</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-hillaryclintondominant-3.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-hillaryclintondominant-3</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spring Training Matters</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/spring-training-matters/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/spring-training-matters/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2015 11:37:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Arthur]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Baseball]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Exhibitions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mike Trout]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[MLB]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[New York Mets]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Opening Day]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spring Training]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73683</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On opening day, every team has playoff dreams. Early on, the potential of the season outweighs our knowledge of each team’s quality. While our best predictions are modestly useful, they can’t tell us which team is destined for greatness with much certainty or which early-season trends to trust or disregard. That makes it tough for [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73683&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On opening day, every team has playoff dreams. Early on, the potential of the season outweighs our knowledge of each team’s quality. While our best predictions are <a href="http://www.foxsports.com/mlb/just-a-bit-outside/story/mlb-baseball-projections-problems-120714">modestly useful</a>, they can’t tell us which team is destined for greatness with much certainty or which early-season trends to trust or disregard. That makes it tough for a baseball columnist &#8212; a pitiable lot, us &#8212; to write about anything with any certainty.</p><p>But we do have spring training. <a href="http://ftw.usatoday.com/2015/03/spring-training-stats-never-forget-jake-fox-mlb">Conventional</a><a href="http://yankees.lhblogs.com/2015/04/04/meaningless-awards-best-worst-yankees-spring-training/"> wisdom</a> holds that what happens in March is meaningless. But conventional wisdom can’t use <a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R</a>. Spring training results aren’t entirely worthless &#8212; either for players, as FiveThirtyEight’s own Neil Paine <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/when-spring-training-matters/">showed last year</a>, or for teams. And I’m particularly interested in this idea that a team’s spring training may offer some indicators of how its season will go. What are the limits of its powers? And what is its potential?</p><p>We know that spring training isn’t incredibly predictive. I gathered data on each team’s spring-training and regular-season performances in the last five years (2010-2014), checking to see whether there was any correlation between a team’s offensive performance in spring<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="40" href="#fn-40"><sup id="ss-40">40</sup></a> and its average regular-season on-base plus slugging percentage (OPS). Just as with<a href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/gametheory/2015/03/baseball-statistics"> other spring statistics</a>, there was a weak but consistent<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="41" href="#fn-41"><sup id="ss-41">41</sup></a> relationship between the two. The teams that bash in spring tend to continue doing so through the summer.</p><p>Even so, spring training results were somewhat faintly reflected in the regular season &#8212; teams have to bash <i>a lot</i> before the trend is noticeably continued once the season starts. But we’re not just interested in how spring training correlates to the regular season; we’re interested in whether spring training should make us adjust our expectations of what’s to come.</p><p>If we look at spring training performances and then compare them against what sabermetric projections<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="42" href="#fn-42"><sup id="ss-42">42</sup></a> have to tell us, these preseason games become a lot more telling. So rather than just see whether offensive stats from spring training correlate to regular-season stats, let’s tally up all of a team’s player projections (I used PECOTA projections from <a href="http://www.baseballprospectus.com/">Baseball Prospectus</a>), average them, and combine <i>that</i> with spring training stats.</p><p>Once I added in the projections, I had a workable system for estimating a team’s regular-season OPS &#8212; much better than the one based solely on spring training data.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="43" href="#fn-43"><sup id="ss-43">43</sup></a> This isn’t so far-fetched &#8212; we make these kind of calculations in our heads all the time. If a team is terrible on paper but slugs like the <a href="http://m.rockies.mlb.com/news/article/1798476/">pre-humidor</a> Colorado Rockies in spring training, we assume it’s likely to end up somewhere between those extremes in the regular season.</p><p>After factoring in the projected performance, a 100-point increase in spring training OPS raises a team’s expected regular-season OPS by 15 points. While that’s not a huge increase, it’s also a much stronger relationship than what <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/when-spring-training-matters/">we find for individual players</a>, where a hitter whose OPS is 100 points better than expected in the spring improves their expected regular-season OPS by only six points.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="44" href="#fn-44"><sup id="ss-44">44</sup></a></p><p>There’s a reason spring training has more to tell us about teams than individual players. It’s about signal versus noise. For an individual player, any set of 50 plate appearances (in spring training or otherwise) is extremely volatile and doesn’t say much about them individually. But bring together all the plate appearances of the nine players who make up a batting order and the volatility begins to cancel itself out. All of a sudden we have some sense of how good the nine are in aggregate.</p><p>For example, New York Mets center fielder Juan Lagares hit much better than expected for the past month, and there was probably some luck involved in his .359 spring training batting average. But Mets catcher Travis d’Arnaud hit much worse (.212/.226/.288) than PECOTA would have predicted. If we gather together Lagares’s lucky singles and d’Arnaud’s unfortunate strikeouts, we get a decent measure of the average ability of Lagares and d’Arnaud together &#8212; even if we aren’t sure how much of the difference between the average and their individual numbers will come from d’Arnaud improving or Lagares regressing.</p><p class="p1">Speaking of the Mets, they led all of baseball with an .817 <a href="http://mlb.mlb.com/stats/sortable.jsp#elem=%5Bobject+Object%5D&amp;tab_level=child&amp;click_text=Sortable+Team+hitting&amp;game_type=%27S%27&amp;season=2015&amp;season_type=ANY&amp;league_code=%27MLB%27&amp;sectionType=st&amp;statType=hitting&amp;page=1&amp;ts=1428249124317&amp;team_id=121&amp;playerType=ALL&amp;sortColumn=ops&amp;sortOrder=%27desc%27&amp;extend">average spring training OPS</a> despite mediocre projections. Such a performance is good enough to raise their expected regular season OPS by 11 points, which ought to be worth something like two wins over the course of the season.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="45" href="#fn-45"><sup id="ss-45">45</sup></a> That should bolster the fans’ dark-horse World Series hopes (or at least their hopes of making the playoffs for the first time in nine years).</p><p>The success of other top spring performers had little effect on their OPS projections because they were already so high. The Los Angeles Dodgers, Los Angeles Angels and Oakland Athletics were already expected to field excellent offenses, and so their spring performances only confirm what we already believed.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="46" href="#fn-46"><sup id="ss-46">46</sup></a></p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73790" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/arthur-springtraining-table1.png?w=610&#038;h=406" alt="arthur-springtraining-table" width="610" height="406" /></p><p>On the other side, teams like the Rockies,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="47" href="#fn-47"><sup id="ss-47">47</sup></a> Minnesota Twins and Texas Rangers showed unexpectedly anemic offenses in spring training, which drags down their regular-season projections. None of these teams had more than a faint hope at the playoffs anyway, but the third- and fourth-biggest decreases in expected offense belong to two potential playoff contenders &#8212; the St. Louis Cardinals and the Chicago White Sox &#8212; which may now find their paths more difficult.</p><p>So you don’t have to wait months to begin worrying (or in the case of Mets fans, hoping) about the fate of your team. Once combined with a dose of projections, spring training results go a long way toward predicting how well a team will hit.</p><p><strong>CORRECTION (April 10, 2:56 p.m.): </strong>An earlier version of this article included a table with incorrect information on teams&#8217; spring training OPS averages. It has since been updated.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73683&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/spring-training-matters/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/468240650.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/468240650.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Baltimore Orioles v Detroit Tigers</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/7ac679b0d20830d2da9e5d0ce9eb99ba?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">chadwickmatlin</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/arthur-springtraining-table1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">arthur-springtraining-table</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why The SNP Is Poised To Win In Scotland</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-snp-is-poised-to-win-in-scotland/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-snp-is-poised-to-win-in-scotland/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 13:19:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[John Curtice]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Scotland]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Scottish National Party]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SNP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.K. Election]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73271</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[At first glance, it undoubtedly seems very odd. Last September, the Scottish National Party (SNP) invited people in Scotland to vote to leave the United Kingdom and become an independent country. The proposition was clearly rejected, with just over 55 percent voting against and fewer than 45 percent in favor. Yet far from heralding a [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73271&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>At first glance, it undoubtedly seems very odd.</p><p>Last September, the Scottish National Party (SNP) invited people in Scotland to vote to leave the United Kingdom and become an independent country. The proposition was clearly rejected, with just over 55 percent voting against and fewer than 45 percent in favor.</p><p>Yet far from heralding a period of nationalist anguish and introspection, little more than six months later, the SNP is looking forward to the prospect of winning an electoral landslide in the U.K. general election scheduled for May 7. According to the latest polls, the party could win <span><a href="http://blog.whatscotlandthinks.org/2015/04/poll-of-polls-westminster-vote-intentions-2-april-revised/">as many as 47 of the 59 Scottish seats</a></span> in the 650-seat House of Commons.</p><p>Moreover, because neither the Conservative nor the Labour Party appears likely to win an overall majority, and because support for the Liberal Democrats has imploded throughout the U.K., the SNP not only could be the third-largest party in the next House of Commons but also could play a decisive role in determining the partisan color of the next government.</p><p>How can a party that so recently failed to persuade voters to back its principal raison d’être now be apparently heading for what would be a stunning success &#8212; and perhaps significant influence on the U.K.-wide stage?</p><p>There are three main parts to the answer. The first is that May’s election is being held under very different rules from the referendum. Second, the question of what Scotland’s constitutional status should be now matters more to voters than it did in the past. And third, the SNP has come to be regarded by many voters as the party keenest on creating a more equal society.</p><p>At 45 percent, the average level of support for the SNP in current Scotland-wide polls matches the percentage that the “yes” side won in the referendum. Indeed, it also equals the 45 percent that the SNP won in the election to the devolved Scottish Parliament held in May 2011. The crucial difference is that whereas 45 percent is always insufficient to win a referendum, it can be enough to win a landslide in an election that is held under the <span><a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/a-glossary-of-uk-politics-from-ashcroft-to-whips/">first-past-the-post</a></span> electoral system and in which a multitude of parties are in contention.</p><p>However, that still means that we need to explain why the SNP has been able to retain the 45 percent level of support that the &#8220;yes&#8221; side secured in last year’s referendum. After all, the party has until now performed relatively poorly in elections to the House of Commons. Such elections invite voters to focus on which party is best able to provide effective government for the U.K. as a whole, a position to which, given that Scotland constitutes a relatively small part of the U.K., the SNP can never aspire.</p><p>As a result, many voters who back Scottish independence have hitherto not voted for the SNP in a U.K. general election. According to the <a href="http://www.natcen.ac.uk/our-research/research/scottish-social-attitudes/">Scottish Social Attitudes survey</a>, only 55 percent did so in the last election in 2010, for example. Consequently, the SNP won only 20 percent of the total vote in Scotland (and six seats) on that occasion, well below the 45 percent it was to achieve in the devolved election just 12 months later. Labour, in contrast, maintained its dominant position in the 2010 election, with 42 percent of the vote and 41 seats.</p><p>However, the referendum has served to make support for independence and backing the SNP more or less synonymous, even in the context of a U.K.-wide election. Last September’s ballot focused voters’ minds &#8212; and especially the minds of those who voted for independence &#8212; on the future of Scotland. The question of who might be best able to govern Britain as a whole has been put in the shade. Consequently, supporters of independence see little reason why they should not follow up their &#8220;yes&#8221; vote with a vote for the SNP in May’s general election.</p><p>Recent polling evidence suggests that as many as 84 percent of those who voted &#8220;yes&#8221; in September (and who are willing to indicate how they will vote in May) now say they intend to vote for the SNP on May 7.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="48" href="#fn-48"><sup id="ss-48">48</sup></a> Included among these “yes” supporters are the 40 percent <span><a href="http://blog.whatscotlandthinks.org/2014/10/labour-worried/">or so</a></span> of 2010 Labour voters who voted for independence, over three-quarters of whom are now backing the SNP.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="49" href="#fn-49"><sup id="ss-49">49</sup></a> Conversely, only around one in 10 of those who voted &#8220;no&#8221; in September are now backing the nationalists &#8212; though that is still more or less enough to compensate for the limited number who voted &#8220;yes&#8221; in September but are now not backing the SNP.</p><p>However, the increased salience of the independence debate in voters’ minds is not the only reason that many former Labour supporters have switched to the SNP. During the referendum campaign, the SNP was also able to lay out its vision for the country, claiming that an independent Scotland could be a more equal Scotland. This argument directly challenged Labour’s position that it was better able to bring about greater social justice, not least by using the resources and the institutions of the U.K.</p><p>It is an argument that seems to have hit home.</p><p>Those who have switched from backing Labour in 2010 to supporting the SNP now are not only in favor of independence, they are also politically on the left. For example, according to the <span><a href="http://www.britishelectionstudy.com/">British Election Study</a></span>, three-quarters of them want the government to engage in greater efforts to make people’s incomes more equal, a markedly higher proportion than the equivalent figure of three-fifths among Scots as a whole.</p><p>At the same time, these voters are more likely to believe that the SNP shares their outlook on this issue than they are to think that Labour does. Whereas slightly less than half (48 percent) believe Labour wants to make incomes more equal, no less than three-quarters reckon the SNP does. For this crucial group of voters, the SNP has won not only the argument about how Scotland should be governed but also the debate about which party has the stronger commitment to equality.</p><p>Of course, also central to the SNP’s apparent ability to win a landslide is the fact that those voters who want to stay in the U.K. are divided in their political loyalties. Only 45 percent of them propose to vote Labour, while 27 percent are currently backing the Conservatives. But could a division of the anti-SNP vote be avoided? Might Conservative supporters be willing to vote Labour in those constituencies where Labour is better placed to defeat the SNP &#8212; and vice versa &#8212; thereby perhaps denying the SNP victory in some constituencies?</p><p>It seems unlikely that many voters will take this path. Given the relative strength of the two parties, the suggestion is more or less tantamount to inviting Conservative voters to back Labour in most seats in Scotland. Yet, of course, across the U.K. as a whole, it is Labour that is the Conservatives’ principal opponent in the battle for power. It seems unlikely that many Conservative voters will be willing to do anything that might assist Labour in that endeavor, however much they might view the prospect of SNP electoral success with trepidation and distaste.</p><p>When four years ago the U.K. government accepted that the SNP&#8217;s success in the 2011 Scottish Parliament election had given the SNP the moral right to hold a referendum on independence, it did so with the expectation that a clear vote in favor of staying in the U.K. would stop the nationalist bandwagon in its tracks. Scotland may have voted to stay in the U.K., but the nationalist bandwagon seems to have just as much momentum as ever.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73271&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-the-snp-is-poised-to-win-in-scotland/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/467468996crop1.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/467468996crop1.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">SNP Open A Campaign Shop In Former Prime Minister&#039;s Constituency</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/b978cfde8b5b6d6d1580f80b271c8e7f?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">landonsimone</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How Fishing Pros Finally Caught George Perry&#8217;s Miracle Bass</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fishing-pros-finally-caught-george-perrys-miracle-bass/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fishing-pros-finally-caught-george-perrys-miracle-bass/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 15:33:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[David Goldenberg]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Extremes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Fishing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Go Fish]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Largemouth Bass]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=72563</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In late 2009, two men walked into a room somewhere in Japan and found a fisherman hooked up to a polygraph. His name was Manabu Kurita, and he was there to answer some questions. The 32-year-old fishing guide had claimed to have caught a bass that weighed just under 22 pounds, 5 ounces &#8212; a [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=72563&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In late 2009, two men walked into a room somewhere in Japan and found a fisherman hooked up to a polygraph. His name was <a href="http://tacklegem.jimdo.com/">Manabu Kurita</a>, and he was there to answer some questions. The 32-year-old fishing guide had claimed to have caught a bass that weighed just under 22 pounds, 5 ounces &#8212; a weight that would make it co-world-record holder in <a href="http://wrec.igfa.org/WRecordsList.aspx?lc=AllTackle&amp;cn=Bass,%20largemouth">the all-tackle weight category for largemouth bass</a>, the most hallowed class in all of fishing. The other men in the room were representatives from the International Game Fish Association (IGFA) and, with the polygraph running, they asked Kurita about the precise position of his boat on Japan’s Lake Biwa and the tackle he used to haul in his catch. His answers from the hourlong session evidently passed muster; six months after he hauled the fish in, the catch was certified as the IGFA’s co-world-record holder.</p><p>The fish Kurita tied is known simply as George Perry’s miracle bass. For almost 80 years, anglers have been chasing that record, and with the help of environmental planners and biologists, they finally equalled it. Or Kurita did. But to understand why it took so long, it’s worth starting at the beginning, on a boat with George Perry, somewhere in rural Georgia.</p><p>In 1932, Perry, then a 20-year-old farmer playing hooky from the fields, pulled a huge-bellied beast with eyes the size of Ping-Pong balls out of a small oxbow lake in Georgia. He knew his fish was huge, but he had no idea it could be a world record. In fact, there were no official world records at the time. But because he stopped by the post office to weigh it before he took it home for dinner (<a href="http://www.bassmaster.com/news/george-perrys-world-record-bass#">it took his six-person family two nights to eat the whole fish</a>), there was documentation when he submitted his entry to the big fish contest in Field &amp; Stream later that year. When the magazine started certifying world records two years later, they realized that at 22 pounds, 4 ounces,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="50" href="#fn-50"><sup id="ss-50">50</sup></a> Perry’s fish far outweighed any other largemouth bass ever caught.</p><p>For a long time, it looked like Perry’s fish was a unique specimen. For the next half century, no angler got within a pound and a half of his mark. “A lot of us didn’t believe a 22-pound bass could live naturally,” says Jon Storm, the former editor of BassFan.com. “A fish that size was off the map; it wasn’t even part of the cluster.”</p><p>But in 1980, Raymond Easley caught a 21-pounder in a manmade reservoir near Santa Barbara, Calif., called Lake Casitas. Over the next three decades, as Monte Burke describes in his book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Sowbelly-Obsessive-Quest-World-Record-Largemouth/dp/0452287154/ref=asap_bc?ie=UTF8" target="_blank">“Sowbelly: The Obsessive Quest for the World-Record Largemouth Bass,”</a> modern-day Ahabs fixated on the record, many of them devoting incredible amounts of time and money in monomaniacal pursuit.</p><p>As the anglers’ mania increased, the sport’s popularity rose. During the 1980s, the fledgling Bassmasters professional tour grew into an ESPN-owned and corporate-branded behemoth.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="51" href="#fn-51"><sup id="ss-51">51</sup></a> Winners of its two-day classic &#8212; the Super Bowl of bass fishing &#8212; won half a million dollars at its peak in 2006. (In 2011, ESPN sold the Bass Anglers Sportsman Society, which owns the tour, but it still televises the event.)</p><p>And while uniformed pros in hundred-thousand-dollar boats outfitted with the latest fish-catching technology competed against each other in timed events on television, amateurs everywhere headed out to their local lakes to try to haul in a goliath. “Not only is the largemouth easily accessible, the tackle required to catch it is pretty straightforward,” says Jack Vitek, the world records coordinator for the IGFA. “It’s open to all demographics.”</p><p>Over the next 30 years, every one of the IGFA’s records for largemouth bass &#8212; save for the all-tackle one owned by Perry &#8212; was rewritten by anglers using all sorts of lines and rods. For a while, it looked like Perry’s record would fall any day. One fish &#8212; known as Dottie for the prominent black mark near her gills &#8212; weighed close to 22 pounds when she was caught and released in 2003. When she was caught again in 2006, she weighed even more than Perry’s fish &#8212; but she wasn’t eligible for the record because Mac Weakley had set his hook in her side, not her mouth.</p><p>Dottie, along with 15 of those 20 new record fish, was caught in one of just a few reservoirs within a hundred miles of Los Angeles. Something was going on in Southern California, and that something was a potent brew of favorable conditions for super fish.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73349 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/goldenberg-feature-superbass1.png?w=610&#038;h=611" alt="goldenberg-feature-superbass" width="610" height="611" /></p><p>Dottie &#8212; along with all the other monster fish caught recently &#8212; is a Florida bass, which biologists recognize as a different species from the other largemouth bass that populate Alabama, Louisiana and the rest of the fish’s natural habitat. “The Florida bass is genetically and behaviorally different from the largemouth bass,” said <a href="http://sfrc.ufl.edu/allenlab/">Mike Allen</a>, a professor of fisheries and aquatic sciences at the University of Florida who specializes in bass. And while Florida bass and other largemouth bass usually grow to about the same size, only Florida bass have the potential to get truly huge. (Allen speculates that Perry’s fish was a hybrid, based on its location between the ranges of the Florida bass and the largemouth bass.)</p><p>Big fish attract more fishermen, which is why fishery managers have introduced Florida largemouths not just to California, but also to lakes all over the world, including Mexico, South Africa and &#8212; yes &#8212; Japan. The Florida transplants have often found that their new environments offer access to a new, highly caloric food source: rainbow trout. While the two fish do not usually coexist in the same areas, the 12-inch trout stocked in these lakes (also to entice fishermen) have proven to be a perfect food for the mega-bass, which pack on weight far more quickly than they would hunting other prey. Bass introduced into new environments overseas have also found new prey to be good eating &#8212; in Lake Biwa, Japan, for example, the bass have taken to gorging themselves on carp.</p><p>The Southern California environment &#8212; newly formed reservoirs in a mild climate &#8212; also helped with the record bass growth. Cold-blooded animals don’t have to spend as much energy metabolizing in stable temperatures, and Allen says the sweet spots for the stable-temperature zone are in Southern California and Japan.</p><p>The role the reservoirs play, though, remains somewhat mysterious. “Lakes go through a natural aging process,” says Allen, who explains that trophy fish usually appear relatively soon after lakes have been formed. Perhaps that explains why far fewer giant bass have been caught in Southern California since the early 2000s.</p><p>While Lake Biwa, the place Kurita nabbed his record bass, has been around for millions of years, Kurita thinks a change in management practices in Japan led to a window for world-record bass that may now be closing as well. “Old days of Lake Biwa fishing, I could catch a lot, but could not get over 10 pounds,” he said. Then, around 2001, Japanese authorities started to treat bass less as a trophy fish and more as a foreign organism to exterminate, he said. As their numbers dropped, the size of the bass Kurita caught grew &#8212; for a time. Since 2010, new extermination strategies, including electrification of spawning bass, has made all sizes of bass harder to find, he says.</p><p>Fishing records are different from human athletic records. While people will almost surely continue to get bigger, faster and stronger, a record fish requires discovery. After years where a confluence of factors produced a run of huge fish, Perry’s record still stands. Almost everyone I spoke to for this article, though, thinks that there is a record fish still out there. Kurita claims he’s seen a 25-pounder paddling through Lake Biwa. Burke says a few monsters may lurk in the lakes of Cuba, where they have been off-limits to many record-focused bass fishermen for dozens of years. Allen thinks there might be a title contender in Zimbabwe, where recently introduced bass are growing freakishly fat. And in parts of the American South, officials have started aggressive management policies &#8212; like draining and repopulating lakes with Florida bass &#8212; in an effort to bring the record back home.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=72563&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-fishing-pros-finally-caught-george-perrys-miracle-bass/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/eg6haf.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/eg6haf.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">Manabu Kurita shows off the 22.5-pound (10.12-kilo) Largemouth Bass he caught at Lake Biwa in Shiga prefecture in western Japan on July 2, 2009. Kurita, the 33-year-old self-employed worker caught what was a world record equalling bass at the country&#039;s la</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/7ac679b0d20830d2da9e5d0ce9eb99ba?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">chadwickmatlin</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/goldenberg-feature-superbass1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">goldenberg-feature-superbass</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>How To Be Funnier</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-be-funnier/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-be-funnier/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2015 14:42:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[FiveThirtyEight]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[FiveThirtyEight Films]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Good Humor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Humor]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Collectors]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73386</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[What makes something funny? Can you make yourself funnier? University of Colorado professor Peter McGraw is trying to answer those questions and solve other mysteries in humor. The latest &#8220;Collectors&#8221; film from FiveThirtyEight and ESPN Films, &#8220;Good Humor,&#8221; directed by Jamie Schutz, follows McGraw as he tries to help David, an unfunny brewery owner, become [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73386&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What makes something funny? Can you make yourself funnier?</p><p>University of Colorado professor Peter McGraw is trying to answer those questions and solve other mysteries in humor. The latest &#8220;<a href="https://fivethirtyeight.com/tag/the-collectors/" target="_blank">Collectors</a>&#8221; film from FiveThirtyEight and ESPN Films, &#8220;Good Humor,&#8221; directed by Jamie Schutz, follows McGraw as he tries to help David, an unfunny brewery owner, become funnier. But this isn&#8217;t all a big joke &#8212; as McGraw said: &#8220;To understand what makes things funny is actually to understand people.&#8221;</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73386&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/how-to-be-funnier/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/goodhumor4.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/goodhumor4.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">GoodHumor4</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/a5ffee70795912de4bc78ad6a72a447a?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">micahscohen</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Billionaire Baron Who Has Transformed How We Understand The U.K. Election</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-billionaire-baron-who-has-transformed-how-we-understand-the-u-k-election/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-billionaire-baron-who-has-transformed-how-we-understand-the-u-k-election/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 22:41:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carl Bialik]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Constituency Polling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord Ashcroft]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Lord Michael Ashcroft]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Michael Ashcroft]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Polling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.K. Election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[U.K. Polling]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=72952</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A conservative British tycoon and aristocrat is not the typical profile of a man of the people. But Lord Michael Ashcroft has done more than anyone else to find out who the people want to represent them in Parliament. In the lead-up to next month&#8217;s big national election in the U.K., Ashcroft has surveyed people [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=72952&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A conservative British tycoon and aristocrat is not the typical profile of a man of the people. But Lord Michael Ashcroft has done more than anyone else to find out who the people want to represent them in Parliament. In the lead-up to next month&#8217;s big national election in the U.K., Ashcroft has surveyed people in more than 100 electoral districts about who they&#8217;ll vote for and why. That may not sound radical, but in British polling, it is. Even more radical: Ashcroft isn’t doing it to bolster his own campaign (he just resigned from his unelected office) or because someone is paying him to do it. Instead, he&#8217;s shelling out millions mainly, observers think, because he&#8217;s curious.</p><p>The U.K. has 650 constituencies, each with about 100,000 people &#8212; less than one-seventh the population of the average U.S. congressional district. Each one has its own set of candidates running in the May 7 general election. Until now, British pollsters concentrated on regions, not constituencies, because they considered conducting surveys in so many small places to be too complicated and expensive. If the public wanted to know how much support the candidates in a given constituency had, it usually had to wait until the votes were counted. Most election watchers simply assumed that across regions, voters all moved in lockstep.</p><p>Ahead of this year’s election, all that has changed. Ashcroft has shined light on this dark corner of U.K. politics by sponsoring polls in roughly 150 of the most closely contested constituencies, from Airdrie &amp; Shotts to Wyre Forest &#8212; some more than once. The British press has dubbed him the <a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2015/01/commons-confidential-no-respect-pollfather">Pollfather</a>, <a href="http://uk.reuters.com/article/2015/02/23/uk-britain-election-polls-idUKKBN0LR14120150223">Lord of the Polls</a> and <a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/politics/2013/02/leader-lord-ashcroft%E2%80%99s-public-service">Pollster-in-Chief</a>. His finding that Nick Clegg, the deputy prime minister and leader of the Liberal Democrats, could lose his seat <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/politics/nick-clegg/11509807/Nick-Clegg-could-lose-his-seat-to-Labour.html">made</a> <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2015/apr/01/nick-clegg-on-course-to-lose-seat-at-election-according-lord-ashcroft-poll">headlines</a> <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/politics/generalelection/labours-plan-to-decapitate-nick-clegg-is-working-lib-dem-leader-in-real-danger-of-losing-his-seat-10149061.html">in</a> the U.K. this month.</p><p>Ashcroft, 69, is a member of the Conservative Party and until last week represented it in the House of Lords.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="52" href="#fn-52"><sup id="ss-52">52</sup></a> Despite his avowed partisanship, political scientists and other pollsters respect his polls and consider them unbiased. And they&#8217;ve influenced forecasts, <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/interactives/uk-general-election-predictions/">including the one FiveThirtyEight is publishing</a>, in dozens of races. All told, if Ashcroft weren&#8217;t polling locally, <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/interactives/uk-general-election-predictions/">our forecast</a> as of Sunday would have shown the most likely leader to be different in 46 races. The polls also highlight the surprising resilience of individual Liberal Democrat candidates despite the party&#8217;s collapse in national polls. Without Ashcroft’s polls, our latest forecast would have predicted the Lib Dems to win just 15 seats, a dozen fewer than their projected total when incorporating Ashcroft polls. Ashcroft&#8217;s biggest impact could come on election day if people make tactical decisions about who to vote for based on the poll findings.</p><p>The rise in constituency polling &#8212; fueled by Ashcroft, along with a couple of dozen surveys from pollster <a href="http://survation.com/">Survation</a> &#8212; &#8220;really has changed the forecasting game,&#8221; said Will Jennings, a political scientist at the University of Southampton. &#8220;But we don&#8217;t yet know how much noise they have added as well as the important extra information.&#8221;</p><p>But so far, Ashcroft&#8217;s track record &#8220;seems to be very good,&#8221; said Robert Ford, who is a senior lecturer in politics at the University of Manchester and <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/robert-ford/labour-20-seats-ahead-19-3-2015_b_6874222.html">is forecasting the election</a> with Jennings. &#8220;He uses reputable pollsters, asks the questions in a sensible way, and the polls have performed pretty well in <a href="http://www.parliament.uk/about/how/elections-and-voting/by-elections/">by-elections</a>, which are actually harder to poll than general elections due to low turnout and unpredictable local dynamics.&#8221;</p><p>Constituency-level polling is expensive &#8212; too expensive for most U.K. media organizations. &#8220;Telephone polling on this scale does not come cheap; otherwise everyone would be doing it,&#8221; said John Curtice, professor of politics at the University of Strathclyde. Chris Hanretty, a political scientist at the University of East Anglia who is helping produce our forecast with<a href="http://electionforecast.co.uk/"> electionforecast.co.uk</a>, estimated that a single constituency poll costs £5,000 to £7,000 (about $7,400 to $10,400). Combine that with Ashcroft&#8217;s national polling, and &#8220;he&#8217;s probably spent about £2 million on polling in the past 12 to 18 months,&#8221; Hanretty said in an email last month.</p><p>That cost is a small fraction of Ashcroft’s fortune. <a href="http://www.forbes.com/profile/michael-ashcroft/?list=billionaires">Forbes</a> estimates that Ashcroft, who spent most of his career acquiring and turning around businesses in various industries, is worth $1.5 billion. In return for investing a few million quid on polling, Ashcroft gets broad media coverage, a platform from which to influence U.K. politics, and the opportunity to satisfy his curiosity about the British electorate, including to answer questions such as <a href="http://lordashcroftpolls.com/2015/02/ashcroft-national-poll-con-30-lab-31-lib-dem-9-ukip-16-green-8/">which actor should star in a hypothetical biopic</a> about each candidate’s life.</p><p>&#8220;I don’t think there&#8217;s any great mystery,&#8221; Curtice said. &#8220;He&#8217;s got a boatload of money, and he&#8217;s got the ability to spend money doing it. I think he genuinely wants to understand what&#8217;s going on.&#8221;</p><p>Ashcroft began sponsoring polling a decade ago. In speeches and rare media interviews,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="53" href="#fn-53"><sup id="ss-53">53</sup></a> Ashcroft says he became a pollster to fact-check Conservative Party leadership on what he saw as unearned confidence ahead of the 2005 election.</p><p>&#8220;I suspected that the party I supported was going to delude itself into thinking it was doing better than it really was &#8212; and might, as a result, do worse than it would do if it had a realistic grasp of the situation,&#8221; <a href="http://lordashcroftpolls.com/2015/03/polling-how-i-started-and-why-its-a-force-for-good-my-anglia-ruskin-lecture/">Ashcroft said</a> in a recent speech. He eventually became the party&#8217;s deputy chairman with a special focus on opinion research, a position he held until after the 2010 election, when <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/politics/2010/sep/27/lord-ashcroft-tax-conservative">he stepped down</a> following a scandal over his choice to retain a residency status that sheltered much of his wealth from U.K. taxes. He has since spent even more of his time and money on polling and on his news commentary site, <a href="http://www.conservativehome.com/">ConservativeHome</a>. In his statement announcing that he would step down from his position in the House of Lords, Ashcroft said: &#8220;My other activities do not permit me to devote the time that membership of the Lords properly requires.&#8221;<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="54" href="#fn-54"><sup id="ss-54">54</sup></a> Soon after, Ashcroft signaled his excitement about focusing on polling via Twitter, announcing a new spate of constituency polls with the words, &#8220;OK back to fun!!”</p><div class="embed-twitter"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" width="550"><p>Ok back to fun!! Write up on 8 marginal seats completed and will release tomorrow Wednesday at noon with quite a commentary at <a href="https://twitter.com/ConHome">@ConHome</a></p><p>&mdash; Lord Ashcroft (@LordAshcroft) <a href="https://twitter.com/LordAshcroft/status/583003502089138176">March 31, 2015</a></p></blockquote><p><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div><p>Professional pollsters and political scientists praise Ashcroft for disclosing the details of his polls and for fessing up when he errs. &#8220;He regards transparency as an essential element of polling, which is why all his data is published in full,&#8221; his spokeswoman Angela Entwistle said.</p><p>Ashcroft&#8217;s avowed commitment to transparency doesn&#8217;t extend to revealing who conducts his polls for him. Several people in the polling industry said it&#8217;s an open secret that the U.K. research company <a href="http://www.populus.co.uk/">Populus</a> conducts most of his polls.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="55" href="#fn-55"><sup id="ss-55">55</sup></a> Most, but not all: Ashcroft&#8217;s usual pollster didn&#8217;t do three polls that turned out to have <a href="http://lordashcroftpolls.com/2015/02/sheffield-hallam-doncaster-north-thanet-south/">major methodological errors</a> and that Ashcroft apologized for while vowing never again to use the pollster behind them.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="56" href="#fn-56"><sup id="ss-56">56</sup></a></p><p>Entwistle didn’t answer a question about who conducted the polls. Inquiries to Populus and Survation went unanswered. At a London political event last month, I asked Rick Nye, who directs Populus&#8217;s political work, about his firm’s rumored work for Ashcroft, just after Nye had given a speech about the election aided by slides that featured lots of Ashcroft polling. &#8220;I really don&#8217;t want to get into all that,&#8221; Nye responded.</p><p>Curtice, who in addition to his academic job is the president of the British Polling Council,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="57" href="#fn-57"><sup id="ss-57">57</sup></a> said it is common practice in the U.K. for the sponsor of a poll not to reveal who carried it out. &#8220;He is doing the polling,&#8221; Curtice said. &#8220;He is taking responsibility.&#8221; When Ashcroft found out about the three flawed polls, &#8220;he put his hand up and said he screwed up,&#8221; Curtice said.</p><p>The big question that we can&#8217;t answer for at least another month is how good Ashcroft&#8217;s polls are. When they zoomed in on voting intention at the local level, did they get the right picture?</p><p>Ashcroft himself, like many pollsters, disavows any role as a forecaster. &#8220;As he has often said, his polls are snapshots not predictions, and he is not making a forecast as to which party will control the government after the election,&#8221; Entwistle said.</p><p>There&#8217;s an intriguing possibility that the polls could prove to be bad predictors of voting outcomes without being flawed. That depends on whether the act of observing local voters itself changes their behavior &#8212; a sort of <a href="https://www.aip.org/history/heisenberg/p08.htm">uncertainty principle</a> for U.K. politics. The hypothetical scenario goes like this: Voters who favor a hopeless U.K. Independence Party candidate in their constituency might decide to back the Conservative candidate instead if polls suggest that the Conservative candidate is trailing her Labour opponent by just a percentage point or two. That could cost Labour a seat &#8212; and not punish the UKIP candidate, who had no real chance of winning.</p><p>Ashcroft himself <a href="http://lordashcroftpolls.com/2015/01/lord-ashcroft-tells-sky-news-that-the-snp-surge-is-real/">has acknowledged</a> the likelihood that his polls will spur tactical voting.</p><p>Political scientists aren&#8217;t sure how big an effect this could have. Several pointed to studies of how the Observer newspaper affected the 1997 general election when it polled 16 constituencies. The studies showed that the polls affected <a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/1467-9248.00349/abstract">few races</a> and that many people who tried to vote tactically <a href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2127621">had their votes backfire</a> &#8212; casting their lots with a candidate who turned out to be less viable than another candidate they could have tolerated. Some also pointed out that many voters are dissatisfied with parties they aren&#8217;t planning to vote for and therefore are unlikely to find an alternative candidate they&#8217;re willing to back for tactical reasons.</p><p>&#8220;Many voters seem to have taken a pretty clear view on the government and/or other parties,&#8221; Jennings said.</p><p>Others say the biggest tactical effect that Ashcroft polls will have is on how parties devote resources to individual constituencies &#8212; and <a href="https://twitter.com/jamgly/status/579360723442262016">how they communicate with voters</a> about the importance of backing their candidates to avoid the likely outcomes suggested by the polls. &#8220;Will enough learn about the poll results?&#8221; Ford asked. &#8220;Will enough believe them? Will learning of them change enough minds? These could be critical questions on May 7, but it&#8217;s impossible to say right now.&#8221;</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=72952&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-billionaire-baron-who-has-transformed-how-we-understand-the-u-k-election/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/153665380crop1.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/153665380crop1.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">The Conservative Party Annual Conference Continues In Birmingham</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/8ad964fadb65d0fa24c9b1bcd71355c3?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">bialikc</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why Millennials Are Less Urban Than You Think</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-millennials-are-less-urban-than-you-think/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-millennials-are-less-urban-than-you-think/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 18:30:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jed Kolko]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[City Living]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hyper-Urban]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Millennials]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moving]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Urban]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Urban Millennials]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=72885</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Are millennials increasingly living in cities? If you’re a young college graduate in Brooklyn, that sounds like a stupid question. Between 2000 and 2013, the share of adults living in Brooklyn who were 25 to 34 years old and had bachelor’s degrees rose 50 percent. Same in Washington, D.C. Does this mean that millennials, more [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=72885&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Are millennials increasingly living in cities? If you’re a young college graduate in Brooklyn, that sounds like a stupid question. Between 2000 and 2013, the share of adults living in Brooklyn who were 25 to 34 years old and had bachelor’s degrees rose 50 percent. Same in Washington, D.C. Does this mean that millennials, more than earlier generations, <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/think-millennials-prefer-the-city-think-again/">want dense, walkable neighborhoods, rather than a house in the suburbs</a> &#8212; especially after watching <a href="http://www.trulia.com/trends/2014/07/recessions-lost-generation/">Gen Xers suffer</a> in the foreclosure crisis after last decade’s housing bubble burst?</p><p>While 25- to 29-year-olds are the age group most likely to live in urban neighborhoods, followed by people in their early 20s, that’s hardly a new phenomenon. To see whether millennials are different from earlier generations, we have to compare them with the same age group in the past. College graduates in the highest-density neighborhoods turn out to be a poor guide to whether there’s been a broader generational shift toward city living. Most urban neighborhoods are not Brooklyn, and most 25- to 34-year-olds don’t have bachelor’s degrees.</p><p><img class="alignleft wp-image-73156" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-1.png?w=305&#038;h=457" alt="kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-1" width="305" height="457" />The millennial generation as a whole is not especially urban, <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/think-millennials-prefer-the-city-think-again/">as FiveThirtyEight economics writer Ben Casselman pointed out last month</a>. According to the most recent detailed census data available, covering the years 2009 to 2013, 25- to 34-year-olds are slightly <i>less</i> likely to live in urban neighborhoods than 25- to 34-year-olds in 2000. That share dropped 0.3 percentage points &#8212; a 1 percent decline &#8212; as the chart shows.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="58" href="#fn-58"><sup id="ss-58">58</sup></a></p><p>To see the Brooklyn &#8212; or Logan Circle (Washington), or LoDo (Denver), or downtown Los Angeles &#8212; effect, look only at 25- to 34-year-olds<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="59" href="#fn-59"><sup id="ss-59">59</sup></a> with at least a bachelor’s degree and at the subset of urban neighborhoods with the highest population density &#8212; the hyper-urban neighborhoods. The share of college-educated millennials living in these city neighborhoods rose 1.7 percentage points, a 17 percent increase &#8212; a big jump. But only 32 percent of 25- to 34-year-olds have bachelor’s degrees. The two-thirds of millennials who lack a bachelor’s degree are becoming less likely to live in urban neighborhoods (-8 percent) and even less so in hyper-urban neighborhoods (-10 percent).<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="60" href="#fn-60"><sup id="ss-60">60</sup></a></p><p><img class="alignleft wp-image-73155" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-2.png?w=305&#038;h=458" alt="kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-2" width="305" height="458" />Even the movement of college-educated millennials toward high-density neighborhoods is less dramatic than it appears. Two broader shifts make it easy to overstate that trend. First is that 25- to 34-year-olds with bachelor’s degrees are a growing share of the adult population, up from 5.2 percent of all adults in 2000 to 5.6 percent in 2013. Second is that <a href="http://www.trulia.com/trends/2015/01/cities-vs-suburbs-jan-2015/">older adults</a> &#8212; especially those 65 and older &#8212; are notably less likely to live in urban neighborhoods now than in 2000, as they <a href="http://www.trulia.com/trends/2014/06/baby-boomer-downsizing/">stay longer in single-family homes</a>. So the adult you randomly bump into in a hyper-urban neighborhood is 30 percent more likely to be a college-educated 25- to 34-year-old now than a decade ago (or 50 percent more likely if you&#8217;re in Brooklyn), but the odds that a randomly selected college-educated 25- to 34-year-old American lives in a hyper-urban neighborhood is up only 17 percent. The composition of cities is changing more than the behaviors of college-educated young adults are.</p><p>And then there’s the interpretation. College-educated millennials aren&#8217;t living in cities just because their tastes are urbanizing &#8212; other demographic factors also play a role. Almost half of the increase is explained by their being less likely to be married or to have children today than educated young adults were a decade ago. Add in a few more factors, like race and ethnicity, and we can attribute more than half the post-2000 increase in college-educated young adults living in hyper-urban neighborhoods to changes in their cohort&#8217;s demographic composition.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="61" href="#fn-61"><sup id="ss-61">61</sup></a></p><p>Millennials overall, therefore, are not increasingly living in urban neighborhoods. Rather, the most educated one-third of young adults are increasingly likely to live in the densest urban neighborhoods. That’s great news for cities trying to attract young graduates and a sign that urban neighborhoods have become more desirable for those who can afford them. But the presence of more smart young things in Brooklyn is not evidence that millennials are a more urban generation.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=72885&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/why-millennials-are-less-urban-than-you-think/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/522774237crop.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/522774237crop.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">522774237crop</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/b978cfde8b5b6d6d1580f80b271c8e7f?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">landonsimone</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-1</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">kolko-feature-urbanmillenials-2</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rand Paul Is Losing His Father&#8217;s Base</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/rand-paul-is-losing-his-fathers-base/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/rand-paul-is-losing-his-fathers-base/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2015 12:20:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Harry Enten]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2016]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Presidential Election]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2016 Republican Primary]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rand Paul]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73192</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Kentucky Sen. Rand Paul&#8217;s presidential campaign is less than a day old but already suffers from an identity crisis. Paul wants to win, but he can only do so if he is seen as more mainstream than his father, Ron Paul, who ran for president in 2008 and 2012. At the same time, Paul can’t [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73192&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kentucky Sen. Rand Paul&#8217;s presidential campaign is less than a day old but already suffers from an identity crisis. Paul wants to win, but he can only do so if he is seen as more mainstream than his father, Ron Paul, who ran for president in 2008 and 2012. At the same time, Paul can’t completely jettison the far-left and far-right positions that have made him a hero to the substantial number of Republican libertarians who made up his father&#8217;s base.</p><p>In Paul&#8217;s dream world, he&#8217;ll satisfy everyone. In the most likely real world, he&#8217;ll end up satisfying no one.</p><p>The most obvious path for Paul to win the GOP nomination is to build on the 21 percent of the vote his father earned in Iowa in 2012, and the 23 percent Paul Sr. picked up in New Hampshire that year. In a divided primary field, that might not seem so difficult; 25 percent might be enough to win both states. And with wins in the first two contests, Paul might be able to ride the Big Mo&#8217; to the nomination.</p><p>But right now, Paul isn&#8217;t anywhere close to where his father ended up in either state in 2012. Paul is polling at a little less than 9 percent <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-iowa-presidential-republican-primary" target="_blank">in Iowa</a> and nearly 11 percent in <a href="http://elections.huffingtonpost.com/pollster/2016-new-hampshire-presidential-republican-caucus" target="_blank">New Hampshire</a>. That&#8217;s far closer to the percentage of the vote earned by Paul Sr. in both states during his 2008 bid for the presidency, which was far less relevant than his 2012 run.</p><p>In fact, Paul is losing support across the board. While he was initially able to outpace his father&#8217;s 2012 success, his national numbers have been dropping over the last year.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73262" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-randpaulliberalconservative.png?w=610&#038;h=526" alt="enten-datalab-randpaulliberalconservative" width="610" height="526" /></p><p>We&#8217;ll see a lot of ups and downs in the 2016 campaign, but there&#8217;s reason to read more into Paul&#8217;s recent polling slide, as he&#8217;s spent the last year trying to increase his appeal with the GOP establishment, particularly on foreign policy.</p><p>When was the last time you heard Paul accused of being an <a href="http://www.newrepublic.com/article/119466/rand-pauls-foreign-policy-evolution-isolationist-realist" target="_blank">isolationist</a>? He used to advocate for <a href="http://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/statements/2014/aug/07/rand-paul/did-rand-paul-propose-cutting-aid-israel/" target="_blank">cutting foreign aid to Israel</a>, but now he offers pro-Israeli bill after pro-Israeli bill <a href="http://www.nationaljournal.com/congress/rand-paul-introduces-another-pro-israel-bill-to-cut-palestinian-aid-20150106" target="_blank">to cut off funding to the Palestinians</a>. He once <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/politics/articles/2015-03-11/is-rand-paul-guilty-of-a-flip-flop-on-iran-by-signing-tom-cotton-s-letter-" target="_blank">seemed to favor</a> President Obama&#8217;s diplomatic overtures to Iran, but he signed Sen. Tom Cotton&#8217;s letter aimed at hurting those negotiations. Paul was once reluctant to get involved in fighting the Islamic State, but he now wants <a href="http://www.msnbc.com/msnbc/rand-paul-epic-isis-flip-flop" target="_blank">more airstrikes</a>.</p><p>There really isn&#8217;t good public data on the views of libertarian Republican voters, but interviews and internal polls suggest that Paul&#8217;s evolution on foreign policy has been <em>too</em> successful in separating him from his father, and has eroded his libertarian credentials. Ron Paul&#8217;s 2012 Iowa campaign chairman <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/rand-pauls-delicate-balancing-act/2015/04/05/6e38af6c-d946-11e4-8103-fa84725dbf9d_story.html" target="_blank">Drew Ivers would</a> &#8220;prefer if [Rand Paul] had a different strategy&#8221; than &#8220;meeting [mainstream Republicans] in the middle.&#8221; Aaron Day of the libertarian Free State movement in New Hampshire <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2015/03/ron-paul-leave-rand-paul-camp-116439.html" target="_blank">sees less enthusiasm</a> for Rand Paul than for his dad.</p><p>To get to 25 percent in the two early states, Paul can&#8217;t afford many libertarian defections in either. A recent <a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2015/03/ron-paul-leave-rand-paul-camp-116439.html" target="_blank">internal Liberty Iowa poll showed</a> that Paul was the choice of about two-thirds of Ron Paul&#8217;s Iowa convention delegates. That may seem like a lot, but if Paul wins only 70 percent of his father&#8217;s backers that puts him at 15 percent of the vote in Iowa. He&#8217;d need to build on his dad&#8217;s support by 10 percentage points from one of the <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/romney-and-the-gops-five-ring-circus/" target="_blank">GOP&#8217;s other wings</a>.</p><p>Yet, for all his shifting, Paul hasn’t seen a major payoff with the foreign policy hawks in his party. While there doesn&#8217;t seem to be as much visible hatred for Paul as there is for, say, Ted Cruz among his fellow senators, Paul is one of the few candidates who is attracting opponents to jump into the presidential race just to stop him. <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/article/398523/lindsey-graham-2016-long-shot-who-could-matter-joel-gehrke" target="_blank">Lindsey Graham</a> &#8212; and <a href="http://www.nationalreview.com/article/356423/bolton-2016-robert-costa" target="_blank">potentially John Bolton</a> &#8212; might waste half a year or more of their lives campaigning in large part because they disagree with Paul on foreign policy.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="62" href="#fn-62"><sup id="ss-62">62</sup></a></p><p>As I&#8217;ve <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/lets-be-serious-about-ted-cruz-from-the-start-hes-too-extreme-and-too-disliked-to-win/" target="_blank">noted previously</a>, it&#8217;s very difficult to win a party&#8217;s nomination when party officials don&#8217;t like you. In primaries, voters tend to take their cues from party actors because the ideological differences between candidates are significantly smaller than they are in a general election. And for the GOP establishment, it&#8217;s easy to find a deal-breaker in Paul&#8217;s portfolio.</p><table class="viz"><thead><tr><th class="first text" style="width:60%%;">CANDIDATES</th><th class="number">FOREIGN POLICY/SOCIAL ISSUES SCORE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Mitt Romney</td><td class="number">13</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Ronald Reagan</td><td class="number">20</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Gerald Ford</td><td class="number">23</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">George W. Bush</td><td class="number">23</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">George H.W. Bush</td><td class="number">33</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Bob Dole</td><td class="number">33</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Richard Nixon</td><td class="number">40</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">John McCain</td><td class="number">40</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Rand Paul</td><td class="number">53</td></tr><tr style="font-weight:bold;"><td class="first text" style="width:60%%;">Avg. of past nominees</td><td class="number">28</td></tr></tbody></table><p>According to <a href="http://www.ontheissues.org/senate/Rand_Paul.htm" target="_blank">OnTheIssues</a>,<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="63" href="#fn-63"><sup id="ss-63">63</sup></a> Paul currently scores a 53 on social/military issues. That means he is slightly more liberal than conservative on these issues (50 is the inflection point). If Paul won the nomination, he&#8217;d be more liberal than any Republican nominee since Richard Nixon.</p><p>But Paul can&#8217;t really make a play for the endorsement of moderate GOP officials either. His economic record would make him the most conservative candidate to win the Republican nomination since Barry Goldwater. Paul wants to <a href="http://www.breitbart.com/big-government/2015/02/10/sen-rand-paul-audit-the-fed/" target="_blank">audit the Federal Reserve</a> and <a href="http://thehill.com/policy/finance/232688-rand-paul-scrap-the-tax-code" target="_blank">scrap the tax code</a>, among other pet issues.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73196" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-paul-2.png?w=610&#038;h=967" alt="enten-datalab-paul-2" width="610" height="967" /></p><p>Paul&#8217;s too liberal/too conservative problem also shows up in polls of GOP voters. According to an average of two <a href="https://d25d2506sfb94s.cloudfront.net/cumulus_uploads/document/cb0cvp0quj/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank">YouGov</a> <a href="https://d25d2506sfb94s.cloudfront.net/cumulus_uploads/document/s86tdrc1vv/econTabReport.pdf" target="_blank">polls</a> in March, Paul is seen as too conservative by 14 percent of Republicans nationwide &#8212; only Cruz is seen as too far to the right by more voters. Paul is also seen as too liberal by 13 percent of voters, behind just Jeb Bush, Chris Christie and Lindsey Graham.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="64" href="#fn-64"><sup id="ss-64">64</sup></a><br /><img class="show-mobile show-tablet alignnone wp-image-56783 size-full" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-07-12-58-08.png?w=610"   /></p><table class="viz full hide-mobile hide-tablet"><thead><tr><th class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">CANDIDATE</th><th class="number">TOO CONSERVATIVE</th><th class="number">NOT CONSERVATIVE ENOUGH</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Ted Cruz</td><td class="number">16%</td><td class="number">7%</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#f0f0f0;"><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Rand Paul</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">14</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">13</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Rick Santorum</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">14</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">9</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Mike Huckabee</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">14</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">10</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Rick Perry</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">11</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">8</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Ben Carson</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">7</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Lindsey Graham</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">7</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">22</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Scott Walker</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">6</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">9</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Marco Rubio</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">6</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">11</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Jeb Bush</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">6</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">31</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Bobby Jindal</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">4</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">7</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Chris Christie</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">4</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">36</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">Carly Fiorina</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">3</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">11</td></tr><tr><td class="text" style="padding-left:4px;">John Kasich</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">2</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">9</td></tr></tbody></table><p>Indeed, Paul looks like he&#8217;ll have the problem his father had once the campaign left the early states. Over the past two months, <a href="http://cbsnews2.cbsistatic.com/hub/i/2015/03/27/650245c4-9301-464e-8cae-e948a2462c42/522e50ae276fa04e8f5497966e6a2d2c/would-you-consider-voting-for-each-for-the-republican-nomination-1.jpg" target="_blank">CBS News</a> has polled Republican primary voters to ask whom they&#8217;d consider voting for. On average, only 35 percent of Republicans say they&#8217;d consider voting for Paul, compared to 27 percent who say they wouldn&#8217;t. That small +8 percentage point difference puts Paul a good deal behind the top tier of the Republican field (Jeb Bush and Scott Walker are each +24).<br /><img class="show-mobile show-tablet alignnone wp-image-56783 size-full" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-07-12-59-57.png?w=610"   /></p><table class="viz full hide-mobile hide-tablet"><thead><tr><th class="first text">CANDIDATE</th><th class="number">CAN SUPPORT</th><th class="number" style="padding-right:4px;">CAN&#8217;T SUPPORT</th><th class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#ffffff;">DIFFERENCE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="first text">Jeb Bush</td><td class="number">50%</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;">27%</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+24</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Scott Walker</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">33</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">9</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+24</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Marco Rubio</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">38</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">17</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+22</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Mike Huckabee</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">44</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">25</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+20</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Ben Carson</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">30</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">13</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+18</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Ted Cruz</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">30</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">22</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+9</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Rand Paul</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">35</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">27</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+8</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Rick Perry</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">32</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">26</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+6</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Bobby Jindal</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">20</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">16</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+4</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Rick Santorum</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">28</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">26</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">+3</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Chris Christie</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">28</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">43</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">-15</td></tr><tr><td class="first text" style="padding-right:0;">Lindsey Graham</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">10</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:.6em;">33</td><td class="number" style="padding-right:4px;background-color:#f0f0f0;">-23</td></tr></tbody></table><p class="p1">These numbers aren&#8217;t debilitating, but they indicate that Paul has yet to figure out how to successfully burn both ends of the candlestick.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73192&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/rand-paul-is-losing-his-fathers-base/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/was8911099.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/was8911099.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">US-POLITICS-PAUL</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://1.gravatar.com/avatar/a26fad23742e906c3f881ae92c6178cb?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F1.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">poughies</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-randpaulliberalconservative.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-datalab-randpaulliberalconservative</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/enten-datalab-paul-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">enten-datalab-paul-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-07-12-58-08.png" medium="image" />

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/screenshot-2015-04-07-12-59-57.png" medium="image" />
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Huskies Are Better Than The Wildcats Ever Hoped To Be</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-huskies-are-better-than-the-wildcats-ever-hoped-to-be/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-huskies-are-better-than-the-wildcats-ever-hoped-to-be/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 19:57:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Benjamin Morris]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2015 Women's NCAA Tournament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Geno Auriemma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kaleena Mosqueda-Lewis]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[March Madness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Moriah Jefferson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[UConn Huskies]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73084</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Don’t let the UConn women’s one-loss record fool you: The Huskies are the most dominant college basketball team on Earth. Aside from that two-point November loss to Stanford, the Huskies have won every game they’ve played by double digits &#8212; since March 12, 2013. In that period, they’re 83-1 with an average margin of victory [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73084&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Don’t let the UConn women’s one-loss record fool you: The Huskies are the most dominant college basketball team on Earth. Aside from that two-point November <a href="http://espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=400590356">loss to Stanford</a>, the Huskies have won every game they’ve played by double digits &#8212; <i>since March 12, 2013.</i> In that period, they’re 83-1 with an average margin of victory of 38 points.</p><p>On Tuesday night, those Huskies take on the Notre Dame Fighting Irish, with the NCAA women’s basketball national championship up for grabs. The UConn team features three freshmen and eight players returning from last year’s championship squad, five of whom are looking for the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-HIB706Tvwo">three-peat</a>. And let’s just say, they have a <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/interactives/march-madness-predictions-2015/#womens">pretty good chance</a>.</p><p>Their biggest star and leading scorer is forward Breanna Stewart, a 6-foot-4-inch junior who, in addition to having already won the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Naismith_College_Player_of_the_Year">NCAA player of the year award</a> as a sophomore, averages 1.9 <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-hidden-value-of-the-nba-steal/">steals</a> and 2.6 blocks per 36 minutes.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="65" href="#fn-65"><sup id="ss-65">65</sup></a> Senior Kaleena Mosqueda-Lewis &#8212; the only player other than Stewart to start for both title teams &#8212; has a whopping 68.4 effective field goal percentage<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="66" href="#fn-66"><sup id="ss-66">66</sup></a> (good for <a href="http://www.wbbstate.com/stats/indiv/eFG">second-highest of 1,827 qualifying players</a>). This may be due to her nation-leading 50 percent shooting from 3-point range &#8212; on 6.6 attempts per game.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="67" href="#fn-67"><sup id="ss-67">67</sup></a> Even the Huskies’ “role-players” get it right &#8212; like<a href="http://www.wbbstate.com/teams/CONN/player/kiah-stokes/15"> Kiah Stokes</a>, a senior non-starter who averages only 4.5 points in 18.6 minutes per game but makes those minutes count by averaging 7.5 blocks and 13.3 rebounds per 36.</p><p>In other words, when the Huskies have the ball, they’re pretty good at putting it into that net hanging from the rim. And when they don’t have the ball, they’re pretty good at stopping their opponents from doing the same. No, really:</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73094 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-1.png?w=610&#038;h=681" alt="morris-uconn-1" width="610" height="681" /></p><p>That cloud in the middle is the other 348 NCAA women’s basketball teams. Teams want to be on the lower-right of the plot, and if you look deep in the lower-right area, you may be able to find Connecticut (highlighted in red so that you don’t mistake it for a flea on your monitor). Yes, that means UConn has &#8212; by far &#8212; the best offense in the country (even though many of its competitors play in weaker conferences), as well as &#8212; by far &#8212; the best defense in the country.</p><p>On average, every trip up and down the floor nets the Huskies more than half a point (0.58 points on average). That’s an insane reciprocal advantage. The next-best are Princeton (who went undefeated in the Ivy League), South Carolina and Notre Dame at +0.33, +0.32 and +0.29 points per possessions exchanged, respectively.</p><p>In sports, it’s common for the best to be relatively much better than the second-best and for the gap between the first and second-best to be bigger than the gap between the second-best and the third-best, and so on. In other words, it’s pretty normal for the best team in a league or sport to be really, really good. But this UConn team is better.</p><p>We can line up each team’s reciprocal advantage from worst to best like so:<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="68" href="#fn-68"><sup id="ss-68">68</sup></a></p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73096 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-2.png?w=610&#038;h=581" alt="morris-uconn-2" width="610" height="581" /></p><p>This kind of sideways/backwards S-shape distribution is common in sports, and you can see how the vertical distances between points get larger on the ends. This is one reason that great players and teams seem so amazing.</p><p>But this UConn team takes it to a new level. The distance between it and the next-highest team is 0.25 points, and the distance between it and Notre Dame is the same as the distance between Notre Dame and the average team. You might even say &#8212; without being hyperbolic &#8212; that UConn has been <i>twice</i> as good as its <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/uconn-and-notre-dame-could-renew-the-best-rivalry-in-womens-basketball-in-tampa/">championship rival</a>.</p><p>A few more fun facts before we look at the bigger picture:</p><ul><li>Unsurprisingly, UConn scored the most points per game overall this season (90). Normally, teams that score that much play a fast up-and-down game, so regardless of how good their defenses are, the extra possessions mean their opponents are going to score more points. But UConn isn’t normal, and still managed to allow the fewest points per game (48) of anybody.</li><li>UConn’s offense led the nation in both 2-point (60.6 percent) and 3-point (40.9 percent) shooting.</li><li>The Huskies are way down <a href="http://www.wbbstate.com/stats/team/RPG">the charts</a> in rebounds per game, but this is pretty much because they don’t miss enough shots to get enough chances. When there was a rebound to get, they nabbed it 58.2 percent of the time &#8212; good for the fourth-highest rebounding rate of all 349 teams.</li><li>They led the NCAA with 8.0 blocks per game.</li></ul><p>Oh, and the Huskies managed to win by scores in the form of 80-something to 20-something (their <a href="http://espn.go.com/ncw/recap?gameId=400597558">87-24 romp over Memphis</a>, for example) four times.</p><p>Of course, college basketball seasons are only 40ish games (including tournaments) long, which is less than half of an NBA season. So perhaps this year’s Connecticut team is just having the run of its life.</p><p>This is at least partially true. The 2014-15 Huskies are an anomaly among anomalies &#8212; this year’s squad has been more efficient both offensively and defensively than either of their championship-winning predecessors (including last year’s unbeaten team). But, taken together, this three-year run is even more amazing. If you thought Connecticut’s 2015 offense/defense chart was crazy, here’s something crazier:</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73100 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-3.png?w=610&#038;h=681" alt="morris-uconn-3" width="610" height="681" /></p><p>Each V-shaped line in that tangle shows a team’s three-year performance on offense and defense. The side with a dot is how the team did in 2014-15, the “kink” in the middle is how it did in 2013-14, and the open end is how it did in 2012-13. At the center of the chart, note the chaotic 348-team jumble &#8212; if you can’t find, say, McNeese State, that’s the point. Most teams vary a lot from year to year. And when a team strays very far from the league’s center of gravity, it is likely to come crashing back.</p><p>Except UConn. Once again, while it may look like someone accidentally took a red Sharpie to your monitor, that little red brush stroke is actually the Huskies. And not only are they nowhere near the pack, they appear to be running away from it.</p><p>Indeed, each of UConn’s points scored per possession in the past three seasons is higher than any other team’s, which means that the other teams had a combined 1,044 chances to match UConn’s worst offensive season, and none could. Similarly, no other team has ceded fewer points per possession over a season than UConn’s 0.68 in 2012-13 &#8212; its worst season of the past three by this metric (though kudos to Hampton for matching it).</p><p>Connecticut’s three-year performance is impressive not only for being extreme, but also for being extremely consistent. Sure, this year’s squad had even better efficiency stats than the previous two, but way out in space like that, such distinctions mean little. Some of their statistical improvement in the past two years may stem from their 2013 move from the Big East conference<a href="http://www.courant.com/sports/uconn-womens-basketball/hc-uconn-women-aac-follow-0311-20150310-story.html"> into the weaker American Athletic Conference</a>. For example, my homebrew-version of SRS (Simple Rating System) &#8212; a stat that adjusts team strength to account for strength of schedule &#8212; slightly prefers the 2012-13 squad.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="69" href="#fn-69"><sup id="ss-69">69</sup></a> But because UConn is so good and its games are often decided by halftime or earlier, exactly how much it’s going to dominate is practically a coaches’ decision. (<a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/most-of-uconns-games-this-season-were-over-at-halftime/">My colleague Carl Bialik found that its average lead at the half this year was 25 points</a>.)</p><p>So instead of looking at fancy small-scale possession-based stats and the like, let’s step back and look at the big picture. Here are the basic cumulative tallies of UConn’s points scored and points allowed after each game for the past three years:</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73104 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-4.png?w=610&#038;h=533" alt="morris-uconn-4" width="610" height="533" /></p><p>The dots represent where the Huskies stood after winning each championship. If you look incredibly carefully, it looks like the yellow “defense” line trends downward a tiny bit this year, but for the most part, it’s pretty remarkable how flat each is and how constant the ratio between the two lines is. Note that those lines don’t represent trends or a local regression or anything fancy &#8212; only consistency.</p><p>And this is nothing new during coach Geno Auriemma’s reign. Whether it’s his schemes, his managerial style, his training or just his uncanny ability to recruit (<a href="http://www.nhregister.com/sports/20141217/georgetown-transfer-natalie-butler-will-serve-uconn-well">or poach</a>) all the best female basketballers to the Nutmeg State, Auriemma is on the threshold of yet another amazing accomplishment.</p><p>It’s hard to believe that the great Geno toiled with this program for 10 years before it even <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1995_NCAA_Women%27s_Division_I_Basketball_Tournament">sniffed a chance</a> at a championship in 1995. But since then, wow. Connecticut has reached nine NCAA tournament finals and has won each time. This year gives Auriemma the chance to match <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Wooden">John Wooden’s</a> 10 national championships.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="70" href="#fn-70"><sup id="ss-70">70</sup></a> And to get there, all the Huskies need to do is beat <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/uconn-and-notre-dame-could-renew-the-best-rivalry-in-womens-basketball-in-tampa/">archrival Notre Dame</a>.</p><p>In this season’s only meeting between the two, the Huskies beat the Fighting Irish in South Bend by (a mere) 18 points. But while Connecticut has lost only five games in the past three seasons, three were against Notre Dame &#8212; all in early 2013. Unfortunately for Notre Dame, the fourth time was the charm that year, as the Huskies beat the Fighting Irish in the Final Four en route to the title. They’ll have to take down a juggernaut to return the favor.</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73084&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/the-huskies-are-better-than-the-wildcats-ever-hoped-to-be/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap617979652312.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap617979652312.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">NCAA Maryland UConn Final Four Basketball</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/5450c91235f14f4b3e92d31158d643ed?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">benjamindmorris</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">morris-uconn-1</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">morris-uconn-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-3.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">morris-uconn-3</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/morris-uconn-4.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">morris-uconn-4</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Out With The Caraway, In With The Ginger: 50 Years Of American Spice Consumption</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/out-with-the-caraway-in-with-the-ginger-50-years-of-american-spice-consumption/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/out-with-the-caraway-in-with-the-ginger-50-years-of-american-spice-consumption/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2015 10:01:34 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anna Maria Barry-Jester]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Flavors]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spice Availability]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spice Consumption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spice Imports]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spice World]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Turmeric]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USDA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=71026</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Each morning, Patty and Tom Erd mix a paste of turmeric and drink the wood-tasting mixture to calm their screeching joints. Their aches and pains come from years of grinding spices, but the culprit is also the cure. “It works better than ibuprofen to decrease the swelling,” Patty Erd told me by phone recently. I [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=71026&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Each morning, Patty and Tom Erd mix a paste of turmeric and drink the wood-tasting mixture to calm their screeching joints. Their aches and pains come from years of grinding spices, but the culprit is also the cure. “It works better than ibuprofen to decrease the swelling,” Patty Erd told me by phone recently.</p><p>I called Erd to ask her about a data set I found buried on the Economic Research Service of the U.S. Department of Agriculture’s website. Compiled from private and government sources, including industry surveys, it details the availability of various spices every year from 1966 to 2012, data that can serve as a proxy for consumption, according to Jeanine Bentley, the USDA analyst who put the data set together.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="71" href="#fn-71"><sup id="ss-71">71</sup></a> While it doesn&#8217;t tell us the exact amounts ingested in a year, it does provide some clues about trends over time.</p><p>Erd and her husband own <a href="http://www.thespicehouse.com/">The Spice House</a>, which was founded by her father in Milwaukee in 1957 and is among the largest and oldest spice traders in the country. I hoped she could help make sense of those trends.</p><p>According to the data, per capita spice consumption nearly tripled over the past half-century, from 1.2 pounds per year in 1966 to 3.4 in 2012. A look at the individual spices, however, shows different stories, with the use of some of the most well-known flavor contributors varying dramatically over the years.</p><p>The per capita availability of turmeric went up and down from 1966 until 2004, when it began to increase. From that point to 2011, it jumped nearly 70 percent. Before I had a chance to mention the spike to Erd, she told me about her morning ritual and how popular the spice had become at her store. “Sometimes you have to give the credit to the medical people,” she said.</p><p>Indeed, the evidence of turmeric’s health benefits is mounting. It has long been used in traditional medicine to treat everything from stomachaches to joint pain, and multiple studies in recent years seem to have verified a wide range of health benefits from the earthy orange powder. One found that it helped <a href="http://care.diabetesjournals.org/content/early/2012/07/02/dc12-0116">prevent diabetes</a>, and another found it to be <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24672232">as effective as ibuprofen</a> in treating osteoarthritis (perhaps supporting Erd&#8217;s anecdotal evidence). Most recently, it has shown potential for <a href="http://stemcellres.com/content/5/4/100">slowing the damage</a> from neurological diseases. Those studies have made headlines, and it appears those headlines are translating into consumption.</p><p>But, of course, spicy headlines shouldn&#8217;t all be believed. Look at the spice that most of us know as cinnamon, part of an unconventional treatment that was <a href="http://www.salon.com/2015/03/16/we_cant_believe_we_have_to_explain_this_diabetes_cant_be_cured_with_cinnamon_rolls/">recently touted</a> by potential presidential hopeful Mike Huckabee for its ability to reverse Type 2 diabetes. First, the cinnamon in those cinnamon rolls probably isn&#8217;t cinnamon; it&#8217;s cassia. True cinnamon, from Sri Lanka, is rarely found in the United States; what&#8217;s sold in grocery stores is almost always the bark of a plant in the same family. Second, the evidence on cinnamon&#8217;s ability to control blood sugar is <a href="http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1002.html">insufficient at best</a>. Studies conducted (mostly using cinnamon, not cassia) have shown only <a href="http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/jf9904517">short-term reductions</a> in blood glucose, or <a href="http://jn.nutrition.org/content/136/4/977.long">none at all</a>.</p><p>Health benefits aren’t the only driver of spice consumption. The vast majority is used for tantalizing taste buds, and as a nation, our appetite for spice has grown with our waistlines.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-72872 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/barryjester-feature-spices-2.png?w=610&#038;h=729" alt="barryjester-feature-spices-2" width="610" height="729" /></p><p>Pepper and paprika have seen huge increases.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="72" href="#fn-72"><sup id="ss-72">72</sup></a> Celery seed imports, on the other hand, grew through the late 1990s before starting on a steep descent (probably a welcome change for the many <a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/super-tasting-science-find-out-if-youre-a-supertaster/">supertasters</a> who find celery horribly bitter). Nutmeg peaked in the 1980s and has since declined, while mace, made from the fruit of the same plant, has seen an increase in imports in recent years after declines in the 1980s and ’90s. Ginger availability has shot up nearly 525 percent since 1990.</p><p>Then there’s the spiciest of spices: <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/rating-chili-peppers-on-a-scale-of-1-to-oh-dear-god-im-on-fire/">chile peppers</a>. On the phone with Erd, I pointed out the 2,000 to 3,000 percent increases in production from New Mexico in the 1980s and ’90s, as well as the overall increases in availability over the past half-century.</p><p>She told me that chile peppers got big in the 1970s, which is reflected in the domestic production data (though imports didn’t increase until the mid-1980s). When she and her husband opened The Spice House&#8217;s second shop &#8212; in 1992 in Evanston, Illinois &#8212; it seemed like everyone who entered had to have ancho, New Mexican and guajillo chile peppers. The Erds couldn’t figure out the obsession until one day a customer walked in with a Rick Bayless cookbook.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="73" href="#fn-73"><sup id="ss-73">73</sup></a> While the data doesn’t tell us where each chile is imported from, Erd said that what’s in vogue changes every few years. Most recently, that has included the Espelette from France, Aleppo peppers from Syria, and the merkén, a copper-colored, smoky chile from &#8230; Chile.</p><p>Laughing, Erd told me about the time that Julia Child visited her shop and declared: “I just can’t wait for that trend to go away!” Sorry to disappoint Julia, but there are no signs that chile is going out of style just yet.</p><p>The available quantity of a spice doesn’t necessarily match what people want to consume. Erd directed me to allspice (also known as pimento), which had a lower per capita availability in 2012 than any year since 1966. She told me that the best allspice comes from Jamaica but that the island nation barely grows enough even for domestic consumption, let alone export. Meanwhile, it’s a current favorite among her food-driven clientele. Similarly, the best vanilla comes from Madagascar, but cyclones in 2000 destroyed crops, causing availability to decline and prices to soar for several years afterward. Although the data shows a decline in availability in the 2000s, it was a question of supply, not demand. In fact, the continued consumption despite high market prices might be a sign of how popular vanilla was during that time.</p><p>The discussion of Madagascar made our conversation drift to one of our shared pet peeves: using the word vanilla to describe something as plain. “There is no more wrong descriptor than that,” Erd said, after telling me it was her favorite spice. “There’s no more exotic plant out there. It’s a member of the orchid family. It’s a hard plant to grow; from start to finish, it takes eight years to get a finished product.”</p><p>Then there’s the family of flavors that no one ever calls plain.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-72873 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/barry-jester-feature-spices-1.png?w=610&#038;h=475" alt="barry-jester-feature-spices-1" width="610" height="475" /></p><p>Anise, fennel, caraway and cumin all come from the same plant family and are similar in look. Although they are all often described as tasting of licorice, the flavors are quite distinct (a quick Internet search found <a href="http://chowhound.chow.com/topics/732692">dozens</a> of <a href="http://cooking.stackexchange.com/questions/16401/are-caraway-seeds-and-fennel-seeds-the-same">forums</a> <a href="http://www.thefreshloaf.com/node/12160/caraway-or-fennel">about</a> the <a href="https://answers.yahoo.com/question/index?qid=20070401093416AAxRR9F">similarities and differences</a> among them). Over the past 50 years, anise, fennel and cumin have seen 1,000, 700 and 375 percent increases in per capita availability, respectively. Meanwhile, cousin caraway has had a 50 percent decrease. Erd and I wondered if rye bread and sauerkraut were falling from grace.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-72874 aligncenter" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/ambj_spice_image_3.jpg?w=610&#038;h=226" alt="AMBJ_Spice_Image_3" width="610" height="226" /></p><p>Despite the differences among the spices, the USDA had to start combining data on fennel, anise and caraway seed availability in 2012 as a result of changes in industry reporting. It may be impossible to know just how unpopular caraway is in the future or whether it makes a comeback.</p><p>As we discussed the future, Erd also pointed me to forecasts from McCormick, the spice giant whose products are available in grocery stores across the country. The company does annual spice forecasts, and this year’s is all about spice blends that are readily available in other parts of the world (<a href="http://www.mccormick.com/Flavor-Forecast-2015">teriyaki and shawarma</a>, for example) but aren’t as well-known in the U.S. “There’s not a lot of new things on planet Earth,” Erd told me. “But there are things that we have new access to &#8230; and spices that have fallen out of favor and are ready for a comeback.”</p><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=71026&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/out-with-the-caraway-in-with-the-ginger-50-years-of-american-spice-consumption/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/538_spice_lede.jpeg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/538_spice_lede.jpeg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">538_SPICE_LEDE</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/b6082c8a493c0b257c3f0b45c803b1fb?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">annabarryjester</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/barryjester-feature-spices-2.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">barryjester-feature-spices-2</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/barry-jester-feature-spices-1.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">barry-jester-feature-spices-1</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/03/ambj_spice_image_3.jpg" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">AMBJ_Spice_Image_3</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Coach Cal Blew It</title>
		<link>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/coach-cal-blew-it/</link>
		<comments>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/coach-cal-blew-it/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2015 20:56:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nate Silver]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[2015 Men's NCAA Tournament]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Final Four]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[John Calipari]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kentucky Wildcats]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[March Madness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wisconsin Badgers]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://fivethirtyeight.com/?post_type=fte_features&#038;p=73007</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Even 38-0 teams can go through mistimed offensive slumps, and the Kentucky Wildcats went through one at a very bad time Saturday night. Kentucky went more than 5 minutes without scoring in its loss to Wisconsin on Saturday. Between Karl-Anthony Towns’ jumper with 6:37 to go in the second half, and Aaron Harrison’s layup with [&#8230;]<img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73007&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even 38-0 teams can go through mistimed offensive slumps, and the Kentucky Wildcats went through one at a very bad time Saturday night. Kentucky <a href="http://scores.espn.go.com/ncb/playbyplay?gameId=400787769">went more than 5 minutes without scoring</a> in its loss to Wisconsin on Saturday. Between Karl-Anthony Towns’ jumper with 6:37 to go in the second half, and Aaron Harrison’s layup with 56 seconds remaining, Kentucky was stuck on 60 points, while Wisconsin swung from being 4 points behind to 4 points ahead.</p><p>A lot of credit must go to Wisconsin’s stout defense, which looked a lot better than its <a href="http://kenpom.com/">Pomeroy rating</a> (just 55th best in the country). But the Wildcats didn’t help themselves Saturday night with <a href="http://www.courier-journal.com/story/sports/college/kentucky/2015/04/05/kentucky-falters-in-clutch/25324201/">three shot clock violations</a> down the stretch. Those violations were symptomatic of a larger problem: Kentucky’s torpid pace down the stretch helped doom them.</p><p>This will involve more math than the usual “hot take,” so hang tight while we take a tour of probabilities. We’re most interested in one big question: Did Kentucky increase its chance to win by slowing its pace, thereby giving each team fewer possessions?</p><p>At first blush, it seems like Kentucky was better off slowing the game down.</p><p>The <a href="http://www.covers.com/pageLoader/pageLoader.aspx?page=/data/ncb/results/2014-2015/boxscore896229.html">Las Vegas point spread and over-under line</a> projected a final score of roughly Kentucky 67, Wisconsin 62 before the game. (FiveThirtyEight’s model <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/march-madness-crib-notes-whats-likely-to-happen-in-the-final-four/">had a similar projection</a>, favoring Kentucky by 4.5 points.) In a game of 60 possessions per team, that translates into 1.12 points per possession for Kentucky and 1.04 per possession for Wisconsin.</p><p>I simulated the final six minutes of the game 100,000 times using these offensive efficiency figures and a few guesstimations.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="74" href="#fn-74"><sup id="ss-74">74</sup></a> Up by 4 in a game with 12 more possessions per team<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="75" href="#fn-75"><sup id="ss-75">75</sup></a> Kentucky won 81.9 percent of the time. That winning percentage increased to 83.3 percent in a game with 10 possessions per team instead.<a class="footnote-link" data-expandable="entry-footnotes" data-footnote-id="76" href="#fn-76"><sup id="ss-76">76</sup></a></p><p>So at a first glance, slowing the game down seems like a good idea for Kentucky &#8212; they were ahead, after all.</p><p>But there are reasons not to do it. Kentucky is the slightly better team &#8212; or at least that’s what Vegas and the FiveThirtyEight model thought before the game &#8212; and in the abstract the better team should want to play a longer game (a game with more possessions). Under our assumptions, if Kentucky and Wisconsin played an infinitely long game, Kentucky would always win. So it was slightly unusual for Kentucky, a Goliath of a basketball team, to adopt a <a href="http://grantland.com/the-triangle/thank-you-for-not-coaching-week-6/">“David strategy”</a> instead.</p><p>This alone wasn’t enough to make Calpari’s strategy a poor one, however. Even though Wisconsin was the underdog, the difference was small enough that you’d still rather give them fewer chances to catch up, according to the simulations.</p><p>But Kentucky also almost certainly made its offense less efficient by slowing the pace down. Rather than looking for good shooting opportunities in the first half of the shot clock, it tried to rush shots near the end of possessions. (Wisconsin’s defense, to reiterate, had something to do with that. But Kentucky hadn’t had much trouble finding shots earlier in the game, shooting 60 percent in the first half.)</p><p>Exactly how much less efficient is hard to say, but efficiency declines significantly as the shot clock runs down to zero. NBA teams <a href="http://www.82games.com/clock.htm">score about 1.12 points per possession</a> when they shoot in the first 10 seconds of the league’s 24-second shot clock, but that efficiency declines to 0.92 points per possession in the final four seconds of a possession. These numbers aren’t perfect for any number of reasons &#8212; not least because they’re drawn from the NBA rather than college hoops &#8212; but they give us at least some sense for the magnitude of the effect.</p><p>So that got me wondering how much Kentucky’s offensive efficiency would have to decline to render Calipari’s strategy counterproductive. The answer: Not much at all.</p><p>In the table below, I’ve used the simulation model to estimate Kentucky’s chances of winning with reduced offensive efficiency. For example, a 10 percent reduction in offensive efficiency &#8212; meaning that the Wildcats are scoring at a rate of about 1.01 points per possession instead of 1.12 &#8212; would reduce their win probability to 76.8 percent in a game with 10 more possessions per team. That’s considerably worse than the 81.9 percent chance they had by playing regular basketball, but permitting 12 possessions per team. Even a 3 percent reduction in offensive efficiency would reduce Kentucky’s winning chances.</p><p><img class="size-full wp-image-73005" src="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/silver-datalab-calipari.png?w=610&#038;h=689" alt="silver-datalab-calipari" width="610" height="689" /></p><p>There are a lot of other factors to consider in the real world, of course, like how Wisconsin might have altered its strategy in response to Kentucky. Still, Kentucky seemed to be playing into Wisconsin’s hands, especially given that the Badgers are terrific in half-court sets &#8212; but much worse than Kentucky in transition &#8212; and <a href="http://kenpom.com/">ordinarily prefer to play at one of the slowest paces in college basketball</a>. Wisconsin might have found a way to win anyway &#8212; they’re a terrific team, and the <a href="http://fivethirtyeight.com/datalab/once-duke-won-kentucky-wasnt-favored-to-go-undefeated/">game wasn’t all that much of an upset</a>. But Coach Cal made their path to the National Championship a little easier.</p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><p><strong>Podcast from Indy: The Kentucky Loss and Monday Night&#8217;s Matchup</strong></p><iframe width="100%" height="166" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="http://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Ftracks%2F199364041&color=ff5500&auto_play=false&hide_related=false&show_comments=true&show_user=true&show_reposts=false"></iframe><p><em>Subscribe to Hot Takedown on iTunes <a href="http://www.itunes/com/fivethirtyeight" target="_blank">here</a>.</em></p><div class='ornamental-rule'><hr /><span></span></div><img alt="" border="0" src="http://pixel.wp.com/b.gif?host=fivethirtyeight.com&#038;blog=64146350&#038;post=73007&#038;subd=espnfivethirtyeight&#038;ref=&#038;feed=1" width="1" height="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://fivethirtyeight.com/features/coach-cal-blew-it/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
	
		<media:thumbnail url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap13445516326.jpg?w=150" />
		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/ap13445516326.jpg?w=150" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">NCAA Kentucky Wisconsin Final Four Basketball</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="http://2.gravatar.com/avatar/ba67d4b1aeec9f6635774b8410a317ad?s=96&#38;d=http%3A%2F%2F2.gravatar.com%2Favatar%2Fad516503a11cd5ca435acc9bb6523536%3Fs%3D96&#38;r=G" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">nrsilver</media:title>
		</media:content>

		<media:content url="https://espnfivethirtyeight.files.wordpress.com/2015/04/silver-datalab-calipari.png" medium="image">
			<media:title type="html">silver-datalab-calipari</media:title>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>