<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Boing Boing</title>
	<atom:link href="http://boingboing.net/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://boingboing.net</link>
	<description>Brain candy for Happy Mutants</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 17:32:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=4.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Video: A captive Silverback Gorilla attacks some very foolish humans at the&#160;zoo</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/video-a-captive-silverback-go.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/video-a-captive-silverback-go.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 17:31:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380845</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[They're lucky he didn't crash right through and peel them like so many overripe bananas.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://youtu.be/KK67kaMWN-8--><div class="video-container"><iframe width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/KK67kaMWN-8?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>
You can see in the glass a reflection of the humans' child unknowingly thumping her chest, a provocation to the adult gorillas on the other side of the window. <span id="more-380845"></span>

The adult humans are stupid for not realizing the effect of their behavior on the gorillas, and they're lucky he didn't crash right through and peel them like so many overripe bananas.

<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/vZ18kz.gif?resize=480%2C270" alt="vZ18kz" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380853" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p>
[Thanks, RC]]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/video-a-captive-silverback-go.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>You&#039;re a slice of bread that desperately wants to toast&#160;itself</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/i-am-bread.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/i-am-bread.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 17:26:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Laura Hudson]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[i am bread]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offworld]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380804</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<a href="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Free_Roam.jpg"></a>

<p>There's a secret desire that lingers in the heart of every loaf of bread: to burn.<span id="more-380804"></span> 

</p><p>In the game <em>I Am Bread</em>, developed by the creators of the popular <em>Surgeon Simulator</em>, you are an individual slice of bread on a journey to toast itself.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<a href="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Free_Roam.jpg"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Free_Roam.jpg?resize=600%2C338" alt="Free_Roam" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-380840" data-recalc-dims="1" /></a>

<p>There's a secret desire that lingers in the heart of every loaf of bread: to burn.<span id="more-380804"></span> 

<p>In the game <em>I Am Bread</em>, developed by the creators of the popular <em>Surgeon Simulator</em>, you are an individual slice of bread on a journey to toast itself. It's not an easy path to travel; if you've ever played <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oOpJiPISO3k" target="_blank">Octodad: Dadliest Catch</a></em> and felt that it was simply too easy to navigate, this could be the game for you.</p>

<p>You control the bread by latching on to surfaces with any of its four corners, and using your momentum to walk up walls, fling yourself into the air, and even hilariously wield objects likes knives and bottles. Your ultimate goal is to make your way through various rooms to some sort of toasting element, and not make yourself too inedibly gross with obstacles like mold, ants and and en route. This is really, <em>really</em> difficult sometimes; after all, you're a floppy piece of bread, and it's a miracle that you can move at all.</p>

<p>There's a slightly dark subplot that runs through the game, as the you read updates from a therapist about the owner of the house you're exploring, Mr. Murton. As most people would, he becomes increasingly distressed by the inexplicable havoc in his home, and the single piece of toasted bread that keeps appearing, which he worries might be a "message."</p>

<p>Although the game has been available on via Early Access for a while, it's <a href="http://store.steampowered.com/app/327890/" target="_blank">finally for sale on Steam</a> itself, for $12.99. If you run into trouble, there's a slightly easier Magic Marmalade option, a rampage version where you play as a baguette that loves to break stuff, as well as a bagel race and a zero gravity playground. Are you bready?</p>

<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wk3byPNh2gA--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3Dwk3byPNh2gA&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fwk3byPNh2gA%3Ffeature%3Doembed&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fwk3byPNh2gA%2Fhqdefault.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="281" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/i-am-bread.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Millions of bees are loose on the highway oh my&#160;God</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/millions-of-bees-fly-forth-fro.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/millions-of-bees-fly-forth-fro.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 17:04:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380813</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[A truck that overturned on a major highway in Washington state was carrying 458 honeybee hives.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_380816" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/635648586712281780-bees-semi-truck.png?resize=680%2C510" alt="A semi truck carrying bees overturned on I-5 North on Friday morning. (Photo: KING 5)" class="size-full wp-image-380816" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />A semi truck carrying bees overturned on I-5 North on Friday morning. (Photo: KING 5)</p></div><p>

A truck that overturned on a major highway in Washington state was carrying 458 honeybee hives.<span id="more-380813"></span>


<!--more-->
<p>
<a href="http://www.king5.com/story/news/local/2015/04/17/semi-overturns-bees-i5/25925049/">More on the accident here</a>.
<p>
<object id="flashObj" width="680" height="350" classid="clsid:D27CDB6E-AE6D-11cf-96B8-444553540000" codebase="http://download.macromedia.com/pub/shockwave/cabs/flash/swflash.cab#version=9,0,47,0"><param name="movie" value="http://c.brightcove.com/services/viewer/federated_f9?isVid=1&#038;isUI=1" /><param name="bgcolor" value="#FFFFFF" /><param name="flashVars" value="videoId=4179601729001&#038;playerID=3657417260001&#038;playerKey=AQ~~,AAADUxzzGpk~,EBNkjIcd2Sh7s7k2yP5Vkmk0FXHQbqwK&#038;domain=embed&#038;dynamicStreaming=true" /><param name="base" value="http://admin.brightcove.com" /><param name="seamlesstabbing" value="false" /><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true" /><param name="swLiveConnect" value="true" /><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always" /><embed src="http://c.brightcove.com/services/viewer/federated_f9?isVid=1&#038;isUI=1" bgcolor="#FFFFFF" flashVars="videoId=4179601729001&#038;playerID=3657417260001&#038;playerKey=AQ~~,AAADUxzzGpk~,EBNkjIcd2Sh7s7k2yP5Vkmk0FXHQbqwK&#038;domain=embed&#038;dynamicStreaming=true" base="http://admin.brightcove.com" name="flashObj" width="680" height="350" seamlesstabbing="false" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowFullScreen="true" allowScriptAccess="always" swLiveConnect="true" pluginspage="http://www.macromedia.com/shockwave/download/index.cgi?P1_Prod_Version=ShockwaveFlash"></embed></object>
<p>
[Thanks, <a href="https://twitter.com/deanputney">Dean</a>!]]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/millions-of-bees-fly-forth-fro.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Omnom: Hand crafted Icelandic&#160;chocolate</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/omnom-hand-crafted-icelandic.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/omnom-hand-crafted-icelandic.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 16:16:52 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Heather Johanssen]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[candy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[chocolate]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380784</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Chocolate is a true joy in life. Not OTC wax like Cadbury, Milka or Hershey: the prescription-strength real thing, such as <a href="http://www.omnomchocolate.com">Omnom's</a> burned-sugar 55% milk chocolate from Reykjavik, Iceland.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Screen-Shot-2015-04-17-at-11.37.59-AM.png?resize=1212%2C704" alt="Screen Shot 2015-04-17 at 11.37.59 AM" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380788" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>Chocolate is a true joy in life. Not OTC wax like Cadbury, Milka or Hershey: the prescription-strength real thing, such as <a href="http://www.omnomchocolate.com">Omnom's</a> burned-sugar 55% milk chocolate from Reykjavik, Iceland.

<p>The taste of caramel hits you right away, subsiding to a smooth, smoky finish of buttermilk. I was able to make the 60g bar last the whole day, though, as it was quite rich and a little went a long way. 

<p>P.S. The wrapper was awesome, so I kept it. 
<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/wolfchoc1.png?resize=680%2C507" alt="wolfchoc" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380795" data-recalc-dims="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/omnom-hand-crafted-icelandic.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hereditary Republican Congressjerk who leads Transport Committee admits sleeping with airline&#160;lobbyist</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/hereditary-republican-congress.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/hereditary-republican-congress.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 16:00:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Doctorow]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Image]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aviation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[congress]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[corruption]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mayday.us]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[piketty]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[usausausa]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380716</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee Chairman Bill Shuster [R-PA] admits that he's having an affair with Shelley Rubino, vice president for global government affairs for Airlines for America, but swears that's not why he gave her industry so many awesome legislative gifts.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>
<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Bill_Shuster_113th_Congress1.jpg" class="bordered" align="right" data-recalc-dims="1">
House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee Chairman Bill Shuster [R-PA] admits that he's having an affair with Shelley Rubino, vice president for global government affairs for Airlines for America, but swears that's not why he gave her industry so many awesome legislative gifts.
<span id="more-380716"></span>
<p>
Shuster's the Congressjerk behind the <a href="http://consumerist.com/2014/07/28/congress-hates-you-votes-to-bring-back-glory-days-of-opaque-airfare-pricing/">Transparent Airfares Act of 2014</a>, which let airlines go back to their old practices of not including mandatory fees in their advertised fares. Shuster, who recently divorced his wife of more than 20 years, took in more from Rubino's employer and its members than any other politician. Rubino (who used to work for a Democratic Congressjerk) gets $400K/year to lobby Congress on behalf of the airline industry.
<p>
Shuster just hired Rubino's number two, Chris Brown, who served as vice president for legislative and regulatory policy, to be his legislative aide. He often gives public statements that are paraphrases or word-perfect quotes from A4A's press materials. 

<p>
Shuster is a hereditary Congressjerk, who got his seat eight terms ago, after his dad, Bud Shuster, was forced to resign after getting caught accepting bribes and giving out legislative favors.
<p>
Shuster says that neither his relationship nor his other actions violate House conflict of interest rules.

<blockquote>
<p>
Stan Brand, the former general counsel of the House and an ethics expert, said that as long as Rubino is a registered lobbyist — which she is — there is no apparent ethics violation by Shuster, even if he backed or advocated on behalf of legislation supported by her organization.
<p>
“Absent some exchange of gifts or things that would otherwise be a problem under the rules, I don’t think the mere fact of her relationship with [Shuster] trespasses any other rules, at least none that I know of,” Brand said. “The rules don’t automatically disqualify a spouse from being employed in a trade association that may have interests before the committee. … I don’t think that, in and of itself, is a violation.”
<p>
Bud Shuster, Bill’s father, was also a former chairman of the Transportation Committee. Following a long investigation, the Ethics Committee found Bud Shuster engaged in a “pattern and practice” of allowing his former top aide Ann Eppard — a transportation lobbyist — to appear before him on behalf of her clients after she left his staff. The CBS show “60 Minutes” filmed the elder Shuster hiding from TV cameras in the back seat of Eppard’s car in an attempt to conceal his relationship with her.
</blockquote>


<p>
<a href="http://www.politico.com/story/2015/04/bill-shuster-admits-personal-relationship-with-lobbyist-117054.html">Bill Shuster admits ‘private and personal relationship’ with airline lobbyist</a> [John Bresnahan, Anna Palmer and Jake Sherman/Politico]
<p>
(<i>via <a href="http://consumerist.com/">Consumerist</a></i>)


]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/hereditary-republican-congress.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>John Green sends uplifting message to a&#160;fan</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/john-green-sends-uplifting-mes.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/john-green-sends-uplifting-mes.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 16:00:21 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380572</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/vlogbrothers" target="_blank">Vlogbrother</a>/<em>The Fault In Our Stars</em> author John Green is one of my favorite people on the Internet (along with his brother <a href="http://edwardspoonhands.com/" target="_blank">Hank</a>, of course).</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/05-e1429219393316.jpg?resize=480%2C256" alt="0" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-380582" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/vlogbrothers" target="_blank">Vlogbrother</a>/<em>The Fault In Our Stars</em> author John Green is one of my favorite people on the Internet (along with his brother <a href="http://edwardspoonhands.com/" target="_blank">Hank</a>, of course). <span id="more-380572"></span> He not only seems to genuinely care about his fans, he also views it as his responsibility to make the world a better place.</p>

<p>A fan recently reached out <a href="http://fishingboatproceeds.tumblr.com/post/116528213858/hi-john-i-have-a-question-for-you-how-are-we-to?utm_campaign=SharedPost&amp;utm_medium=Email&amp;utm_source=TumblriOS" target="_blank">via Tumblr</a> to ask for Green’s advice on how to deal with the fact that her parents are unsupportive of her Cerebral Palsy and she fears they might reject her for her bisexual identity. Green’s response is the kind of supportive, uplifting message we could all stand to hear more. It may not be revolutionary, but it’s still heartwarming.</p>

<p>The full exchange (pulled from <a href="http://fishingboatproceeds.tumblr.com/post/116528213858/hi-john-i-have-a-question-for-you-how-are-we-to?utm_campaign=SharedPost&amp;utm_medium=Email&amp;utm_source=TumblriOS" target="_blank">Tumblr</a>) is below:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>QUESTION:</strong> Hi, John. I have a question for you. How are we to deal with prejudice that comes from within our own families? I am a 22 year-old who has Cerebral Palsy and who identifies as bisexual (that last part I have not yet told my parents). My parents often make nasty remarks about people who are LGBTQ (don't get me started on race). In addition to these kins [sic] of remarks, today my father called me a “cripple” in front of other people (we work at the same place). Any advice would be appreciated.</p>

<p><strong>JOHN GREEN:</strong> Ah, I’m so sorry. That’s hard to hear from anyone, but especially from your own dad. I’m sure your dad is not evil, but no one should ever have to feel dehumanized by someone they love.</p>

<p>I don’t know how to give advice but I just want to say that you are a human being, and you are important and cared for. Neither your disabilities nor your sexual orientation make you less human than any other person–you are complex and important and worthy of love. There are people–and I’m very sorry if such people are in your family–who seek to dehumanize the other. Maybe the are scared and maybe they are acting out systemic biases they inherited and maybe they don’t know how to include you in their overly narrow definition of personhood, but <strong>that is not about you</strong>. That is not your fault. You are not broken or wrong; the social order is.</p>

<p>I hope there might be some comfort in knowing that–that you can know it deep down inside of you even if you don’t get the kind of outside validation that we all need and deserve. But what you are going through is not easy. My wish for you is that you find people–online and off–who will honor and celebrate your beautiful and multitudinous personhood.</p></blockquote>

<p>Read more posts on <a href="http://fishingboatproceeds.tumblr.com/" target="_blank">John Green’s Tumblr</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/john-green-sends-uplifting-mes.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Explore Daredevil’s comic book origins with these simple&#160;illustrations</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/explore-daredevils-comic-bo.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/explore-daredevils-comic-bo.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 16:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380609</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>If you haven’t already seen it, I can’t recommend Marvel’s new Netflix series <em>Daredevil</em> highly enough. <span id="more-380609"></span> It’s gritty, well acted, and thematically rich, with some of the best fight choreography I’ve ever seen.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p1.jpg?resize=600%2C587" alt="drawing by Chris Haley of Let’s Be Friends Again" class="size-medium wp-image-380610" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>If you haven’t already seen it, I can’t recommend Marvel’s new Netflix series <em>Daredevil</em> highly enough. <span id="more-380609"></span> It’s gritty, well acted, and thematically rich, with some of the best fight choreography I’ve ever seen. (Be warned though, it’s pretty violent.) I’m not quite sure where exactly it falls on my <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/03/27/the-entire-marvel-cinematic-un.html" target="_blank">ranking of the Marvel Cinematic Universe</a>, but it’s definitely up there.</p>

<p>And for those like me who aren't up on their comic book history, this new <em><a href="http://comicsalliance.com/comics-everybody-the-history-of-daredevil-explained/" target="_blank">Comics, Everybody!</a></em> feature from <a href="http://comicsalliance.com/tags/chris-haley/" target="_blank">Chris Haley</a> of <em><a href="http://www.letsbefriendsagain.com/" target="_blank">Let’s Be Friends Again</a></em> does a great job of summarizing the character’s origins and condensing 50 years of comic book adventures into seven panels. </p>

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p2.jpg?resize=600%2C477" alt="p2" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380611" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p3.jpg?resize=600%2C477" alt="p3" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380612" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p4.jpg?resize=600%2C477" alt="p4" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380613" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p5.jpg?resize=600%2C477" alt="p5" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380614" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p6.jpg?resize=600%2C476" alt="p6" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380615" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<div id="attachment_380616" style="width: 610px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/p7.jpg?resize=600%2C476" alt="drawing by Chris Haley of Let’s Be Friends Again" class="size-medium wp-image-380616" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text">drawing by Chris Haley of Let’s Be Friends Again</p></div>

<p>[h/t <em><a href="http://comicsalliance.com/comics-everybody-the-history-of-daredevil-explained/" target="_blank">Comics Alliance</a></em>]</p>


]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/explore-daredevils-comic-bo.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Want to know why men fight—and why we like to&#160;watch?</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/want-to-know-why-men-fight-a.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/want-to-know-why-men-fight-a.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 15:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mike Shaughnessy]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380783</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

Jon Gottschall is a man you want at every academic dinner party. He seems to have read everything, takes interest in the work of others, and can converse for hours about anything.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>

Jon Gottschall is a man you want at every academic dinner party. He seems to have read everything, takes interest in the work of others, and can converse for hours about anything. In another world, he might have been a great professor. Instead, he was given God’s work: helping freshmen improve their written compositions.

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/The-Professor-Cage-Fight-Watch/dp/1594205639/ref=as_sl_pc_ss_til?tag=bngbng-20&#038;linkCode=w01&#038;linkId=MIPFG5W5KQ5KYFTT&#038;creativeASIN=1594205639"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/image001.png?resize=230%2C346" alt="image001" class="alignright size-full wp-image-380785" data-recalc-dims="1" /></a>He does all the right things to rise above this. He publishes, presents at conferences, networks, and even makes friends with Deans. In fact, his <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Storytelling-Animal-Stories-Human/dp/0544002342">last book</a> went beyond the expectations set for academics: it <em>sold well</em>. 

<p>This left him looking in the mirror, daily, at a failed professor. He hadn’t yet earned the academy’s golden ticket: a tenure-track job.

<p>Therefore, Jon decided to become an MMA fighter.

<p>A black eye and swollen lip would surely get him noticed at the monthly faculty meeting! His attempt at becoming a fighter was thwarted, first by films like <em><a href="http://www.sonypictures.com/movies/herecomestheboom/">Here Comes the Boom</a></em>, which seemed to usurp his idea of the teacher turned brawler, and second by his innate drive towards scientific analysis.

<p>Thus was born his newest book, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Professor-Cage-Fight-Watch/dp/1594205639">The Professor in the Cage</a>. It starts off as a memoir of another “failed” professor in American higher education, and ends up an insightful look into humanity’s long term fascination with watching two men beat the snot out of each other.

<p>It is less a story about war, bullying, and duels, and more a story about what is innate in the male version of our species, from an evolutionary perspective. Some have already said that it can be seen as a “guide to men.”

<p>Men—intellectual men—who read this can nod along with the pages in subconscious agreement. They may try to explain “smear the queer” to their equally intellectual wife, and to themselves, while gaining a disdainful glance.

<span id="more-380783"></span>



<p>The book is smart, funny, and well researched. It analyses the male “monkey dance” associated with bravado, dueling, and chest bumping that invariably leads to fists thrown (or members of the crew pulling a friend to safety). Jon looks at both the scientific and literary histories, to see what makes men crave physical dominance over one another.

<p>His conclusions are humorous, provocative, and unsettling. Cultural conservatives might pick up on the work and make it the book they have been “waiting” for. Will they use his research to show how “men are men” and “women are women”?

<p><a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Professor-Cage-Fight-Watch/dp/1594205639">The Professor in the Cage</a> takes a light-hearted approach to understanding the psychology and science surrounding man-on-man violence. Gottschall finds a way to integrate two seemingly incompatible worlds, and does it with excellent prose and the style of a grand storyteller. If you find Jon in a bar in Pittsburgh, order him a cheap bourbon, punch him in the arm, then ask him outside for a dance.

]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/want-to-know-why-men-fight-a.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>This Newsies/Oliver &amp; Company mash-up is obscure Disney&#160;gold</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/this-newsiesoliver-comp.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/this-newsiesoliver-comp.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 15:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380644</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Neither the 1992 live action musical <em>Newsies</em> (starring a young Christian Bale!), nor the 1988 animated feature <em>Oliver &#38; Company</em> Disney classics.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kFZLmUQ7IHM--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DkFZLmUQ7IHM&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FkFZLmUQ7IHM%3Ffeature%3Doembed&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FkFZLmUQ7IHM%2Fhqdefault.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="281" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Neither the 1992 live action musical <em>Newsies</em> (starring a young Christian Bale!), nor the 1988 animated feature <em>Oliver &amp; Company</em> Disney classics. <span id="more-380644"></span> Yet the former has found a new life on Broadway as an energetic dance-heavy musical. And in this delightful new music video, cast member Jacob Kemp combines the <em>Newsies</em>’s song “King Of New York” with the Billy Joel-penned “Why Should I Worry” from <em>Oliver &amp; Company</em> in order to celebrate the lesser-known side of the Disney canon.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/this-newsiesoliver-comp.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Daily Dot asks: If Apple customers can sleep outside, why can’t homeless&#160;people?</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/the-daily-dot-asks-if-apple-c.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/the-daily-dot-asks-if-apple-c.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 14:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380564</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p> 

</p><p>Writer S.E. Smith <a href="http://www.dailydot.com/opinion/apple-lines-sit-lie-laws/?fb=ss&#38;prtnr=HuffPostBlackVoices&#38;ncid=fcbklnkushpmg00000047" target="_blank">points out</a> a hypocrisy in modern American society<span id="more-380564"></span>: We find it funny, weird, or cool when Apple customers sleep outside in advance of a new product launch.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/Waiting_for_iPhones_NYC.jpg?resize=600%2C450" alt="&quot;Waiting for iPhones NYC&quot; photo by Bastique" class="size-medium wp-image-380568" data-recalc-dims="1" /> 

<p>Writer S.E. Smith <a href="http://www.dailydot.com/opinion/apple-lines-sit-lie-laws/?fb=ss&amp;prtnr=HuffPostBlackVoices&amp;ncid=fcbklnkushpmg00000047" target="_blank">points out</a> a hypocrisy in modern American society<span id="more-380564"></span>: We find it funny, weird, or cool when Apple customers sleep outside in advance of a new product launch. Yet many states are simultaneously cracking down on homeless people for simply existing in public spaces.</p> 

<p>Smith writes:</p> 

<blockquote><p>Yet there’s a deep and unavoidable social divide to address when one group of people is chuckled at for sleeping outside, while another is a source of derision—with legislation designed to actively target it. This divide falls heavily out along class lines, as those wealthy enough to buy the latest Apple product are apparently not as worrisome to civic leaders as members of the homeless community; one is welcome to bring sleeping bags and a sense of community spirit to the streets of downtown, while the other is not.</p> </blockquote>

<p>And later:</p>  

<blockquote><p>We can’t have it both ways: Either people deserve to use the sidewalk or they don’t, and laws regarding the use of the sidewalk should be enforced equally, regardless of social status. Last year alone, Apple benefited from unequal enforcement of sit/lie laws in Spokane when police declined to cite and disperse those waiting for new iPhones, though it likely would have been irked if homeless people without funds for new phones had joined the throng. In 2012, similarly unequal enforcement also marked the release of a new iPhone model.</p>

<p>If you’re going to revel in the spectacle of huge crowds mobbing your doors in anticipation of a product release, you’d better be prepared for police officers coming to break up the crowd. After all, they’re loitering and blocking the sidewalk.</p> </blockquote>

<p>Read the full article—which explores a lot of the anti-homeless sentiment being codified in law across the country—over on <em><a href="http://www.dailydot.com/opinion/apple-lines-sit-lie-laws/?fb=ss&amp;prtnr=HuffPostBlackVoices&amp;ncid=fcbklnkushpmg00000047" target="_blank">The Daily Dot</a></em>.</p> 

<p> <em>(Image: Waiting for iPhones NY, <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Bastique" target="_blank">Bastique</a>, CC BY-SA 3.0)</em> </p>

<p><i>Top photo: "Waiting for iPhones NYC," by Bastique</i>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/the-daily-dot-asks-if-apple-c.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Watch Catherine Tate try to guess who David Tennant played in Harry&#160;Potter</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/watch-catherine-tate-try-to-gu.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/watch-catherine-tate-try-to-gu.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 14:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380653</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Apropos of absolutely nothing, here’s one of my all-time favorite videos<span id="more-380653"></span>.

</p><p>While on the British chat show <em>The Justin Lee Collins Show</em>, Catherine Tate was asked to name the character her former <em>Doctor Who</em> co-star David Tennant played in <em>Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire</em>.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wvrHsbQaFKY--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DwvrHsbQaFKY&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FwvrHsbQaFKY%3Ffeature%3Doembed&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FwvrHsbQaFKY%2Fhqdefault.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="375" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Apropos of absolutely nothing, here’s one of my all-time favorite videos<span id="more-380653"></span>.

<p>While on the British chat show <em>The Justin Lee Collins Show</em>, Catherine Tate was asked to name the character her former <em>Doctor Who</em> co-star David Tennant played in <em>Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire</em>. (It’s Barty Crouch, Jr., which by <em>Harry Potter </em>standards is a pretty normal name). The famously forgetful comedian struggles just a bit to come up with the right answer, but you have to give her points for trying.</p> ]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/watch-catherine-tate-try-to-gu.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hunger Games star Amandla Stand explains the nuances of cultural&#160;appropriation</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/hunger-games-star-amandla-stan.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/hunger-games-star-amandla-stan.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 13:47:35 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380557</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

“Cultural appropriation” is a tricky concept to understand. When does appreciating another culture’s traditions cross over into usurping and/or disrespecting them?</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_static_9glvmbwa1w084440ksgcgsggk.jpg?resize=650%2C650" alt="tumblr_static_9glvmbwa1w084440ksgcgsggk" class="alignright size-full wp-image-380770" data-recalc-dims="1" />

“Cultural appropriation” is a tricky concept to understand. When does appreciating another culture’s traditions cross over into usurping and/or disrespecting them? <span id="more-380557"></span> 

<p>Amandla Stenberg, the young actress who got her start as Rue in <em>The Hunger Games</em>, does <a href="http://clandesteen.tumblr.com/post/107484511963/dont-cash-crop-my-cornrows-a-crash-discourse-on">a brilliant job of explaining the complex concept in this video</a>.


<p>She created the clip for a history class project, and after posting it to her <a href="http://clandesteen.tumblr.com/post/107484511963/dont-cash-crop-my-cornrows-a-crash-discourse-on" target="_blank">Tumblr</a> a few months ago it’s recently gained traction.</p>

<div style="width:680;clear:both;padding:1em;background-color:black;">
<center>

<!--http://clandesteen.tumblr.com/post/107484511963/dont-cash-crop-my-cornrows-a-crash-discourse-on--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=http%3A%2F%2Fclandesteen.tumblr.com%2Fpost%2F107484511963%2Fdont-cash-crop-my-cornrows-a-crash-discourse-on&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fclandesteen.tumblr.com%2Fvideo_file%2F107484511963%2Ftumblr_nhuiw6DxZY1rp0fth&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fmedia.tumblr.com%2Ftumblr_nhuiw6DxZY1rp0fth_frame1.jpg&#038;type=video%2Fmp4&#038;schema=tumblr" width="400" height="225" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

</center>
</div>

<p>She explains, “The line between cultural appropriation and cultural exchange is always going to be blurred. But here’s the thing: Appropriation occurs when a style leads to racist generalizations or stereotypes where it originated, but is deemed as high fashion, cool, or funny when the privileged take it for themselves. Appropriation occurs when the appropriator is not aware of the deep significance of the culture that they are partaking in.”</p>

<p>She also talks about the recent “Black Lives Matter” movement and criticizes the way in which many of the white celebrities who pull from black culture aesthetically refused to speak out against the racism that accompanies black identity.</p>

<p>She ends her video with a simple question: “What would America be like if we loved black people as much as we loved black culture?”</p>

<p>[h/t <em><a href="http://www.ew.com/article/2015/04/16/hunger-games-amandla-stenberg-cultural-appropriation?hootPostID=50b80c1cd6eacecfc5f883349feb4194" target="_blank">Entertainment Weekly</a></em>]</p>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/hunger-games-star-amandla-stan.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Podcast recommendation: The Empire Film&#160;Podcast</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/podcast-recommendation-the-em.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/podcast-recommendation-the-em.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 13:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380681</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>I’m going to go ahead and declare <em><a href="http://www.empireonline.com/podcast/" target="_blank">The Empire Film Podcast</a></em> my all time favorite film podcast <span id="more-380681"></span> (with <em><a href="http://www.filmspotting.net/" target="_blank">Filmspotting</a></em> a close second).</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/empire.jpg?resize=600%2C600" alt="empire" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380682" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>I’m going to go ahead and declare <em><a href="http://www.empireonline.com/podcast/" target="_blank">The Empire Film Podcast</a></em> my all time favorite film podcast <span id="more-380681"></span> (with <em><a href="http://www.filmspotting.net/" target="_blank">Filmspotting</a></em> a close second). The official "pod" of <em>Empire Magazine </em>features host Chris Hewitt along with a rotating panel that usually includes the likes of Helen O’Hara, Phil de Semlyen, Nick de Semlyen, James Dyer, and Ali Plumb. </p>

<p> The crew is equally comfortable whether they're discussing arthouse fare or mega blockbusters, and their encyclopedic knowledge of all things nerdy is second to none. The podcast features movie news, reviews, and interviews with big name players in the film industry, but the real draw is the chemistry among the British hosts as well as their whip smart senses of humor.</p>

<p>Find <em>The Empire Film Podcast</em> on <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/gb/podcast/the-empire-podcast/id507987292?v0=WWW-EUUK-ITUHOME-TOPPODCASTS&amp;ign-mpt=uo%3D2" target="_blank">iTunes</a> and <a href="http://www.empireonline.com/podcast/" target="_blank">online</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/podcast-recommendation-the-em.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Historic win for police torture survivors in&#160;Chicago</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/historic-win-for-police-tortur.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/historic-win-for-police-tortur.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 13:38:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[memorials]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380694</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

</p><p>Earlier this year <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/03/09/chicagoans-fight-for-police-to.html" target="_blank">I shared the story</a> of a group of police torture survivors and their supporters who have been fighting for reparations from the City of Chicago.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DSC_0527.jpg?resize=600%2C400" alt="Memorial outside Mayor Rahm Emanuel&#039;s Office [photo by Caroline Siede]" class="size-medium wp-image-380695" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>Earlier this year <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/03/09/chicagoans-fight-for-police-to.html" target="_blank">I shared the story</a> of a group of police torture survivors and their supporters who have been fighting for reparations from the City of Chicago. <span id="more-380694"></span> Over 100 black men and women were tortured by police interrogators during the reign of police commander Jon Burge in the 1970s, 80s, and 90s. Some spent decades in prison based on these coerced confessions.</p>

<p>And now after years of fighting for justice, there is good news to report: The City of Chicago has settled on a reparations package for survivors. That means Chicago will become the first city in the country to provide reparations for law enforcement conduct.</p>

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/CCmqixmW0AAuVP-.png?resize=600%2C617" alt="CCmqixmW0AAuVP-" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-380696" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>The reparations packages was based on an ordinance created by The Chicago Torture Justice Memorial Project. According to <a href="http://chicagotorture.org/project/#blog-torture-reparations-historic-hearing" target="_blank">their website</a>:</p>

<blockquote> <p>The package.. provides concrete redress to the torture survivors and their family members, which includes: a formal apology for the torture; specialized counseling services to the Burge torture survivors and their family members on the South side; free enrollment and job training in City Colleges for survivors and family members; a history lesson about the Burge torture cases taught in Chicago Public schools; a permanent public memorial to the survivors; and it sets aside $5.5 million for a Reparations Fund for Burge Torture Victims that will allow the Burge torture survivors with us today to receive financial compensation for the torture they endured.</p>

<p>…</p>

<p>The reparations package, rooted in a restorative justice framework, acknowledges the torture of Black people under former police commander Jon Burge, and begins to make amends by providing financial compensation and services to the torture survivors and their families. Beyond the financial compensation, the legislation is an important acknowledgment by the city of its responsibility to make amends for the torture, and the decades of denials and cover-ups. It is a significant step towards justice and healing, although nothing can erase the unconscionable human rights violations committed by Burge and his fellow officers.</p></blockquote> 

<p>Although it provides less than the $20 million the ordinance originally requested, it’s still a historic win for activist groups like <a href="http://chicagotorture.org/" target="_blank">CTJM</a>, <a href="http://www.project-nia.org/" target="_blank">Project NIA</a>, <a href="http://www.amnestyusa.org/" target="_blank">Amnesty International</a>, <a href="http://wechargegenocide.org/" target="_blank">We Charge Genocide</a>, <a href="http://byp100.org/" target="_blank">Black Youth Project 100</a>, <a href="http://www.chicagolightbrigade.org/" target="_blank">Chicago Light Brigade</a>, and the <a href="http://naarpr.org/" target="_blank">Chicago Alliance Against Racism and Political Repression</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://thinkprogress.org/justice/2015/04/16/3647515/chicago-torture-victims-see-compensation-first-ever-police-misconduct-fund/" target="_blank"><em>ThinkProgress</em></a> shared the news as well as some thoughts from torture survivor Darrell Cannon:</p>

<blockquote><p>Cannon said the settlement, which provides up to $100,000 for each victim, isn’t enough for him to feel like justice has been served, but it’s a step in the right direction.</p>

<p>“Until I can get Burge’s pension taken away from him, justice can never be fully done,” Cannon said, referring to the $4,000-a-month pension Burge continues to collect. “But what they’re doing today is in fact a very good start… For too long now, this nasty, ugly, vicious secret has been swept under the rug but now it’s time to come to grips with the whole thing and to do something that would give us a measure of justice. Everything in the reparations does just that.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Activists hope this Chicago ordinance will inspire other cities to follow suit and push for meaningful reform throughout the country.</p>

<!--https://twitter.com/ChicagoTorture/status/588189283401527297--><div class="video-container"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" width="500"><p>The fight is not over because police torture continues today. We must keep pressing forward &amp; build on this historic moment.</p>&mdash; JusticeMemorials (@ChicagoTorture) <a href="https://twitter.com/ChicagoTorture/status/588189283401527297">April 15, 2015</a></blockquote><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>

<p><i>Top photo: Caroline Siede</i>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/historic-win-for-police-tortur.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Annotated &quot;Eyes on the&#160;Prize&quot;</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/annotated-eyes-on-the-prize.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/annotated-eyes-on-the-prize.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 13:00:02 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Doctorow]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[civil rights]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Copyfight]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[documentaries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[History]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[movies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[race]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[videos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[youtube]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380711</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>
Glen Chiacchieri's produced a heavily annotated version of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0031WNYHK">Eyes on the Prize</a>, the brilliant video documentary series on the history of the Civil Rights movement that was <a href="http://boingboing.net/2014/01/21/eyes-on-the-prize-famed-civil.html">rescued</a> from copyright oblivion by a <a href="http://boingboing.net/2005/02/01/eyes-on-the-prize-ri.html">civil disobedience campaign</a>.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=92p-gCfYRyE--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3D92p-gCfYRyE&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2F92p-gCfYRyE%3Ffeature%3Doembed&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2F92p-gCfYRyE%2Fhqdefault.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="375" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>
Glen Chiacchieri's produced a heavily annotated version of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0031WNYHK">Eyes on the Prize</a>, the brilliant video documentary series on the history of the Civil Rights movement that was <a href="http://boingboing.net/2014/01/21/eyes-on-the-prize-famed-civil.html">rescued</a> from copyright oblivion by a <a href="http://boingboing.net/2005/02/01/eyes-on-the-prize-ri.html">civil disobedience campaign</a>.
<span id="more-380711"></span>
<p>
Chiacchieri's annotations lets you navigate the video with a timeline, and automatically scrolls through supplementary materials with links to further reading as you watch. It's a fantastic way to build upon a crucial documentary.
<p>
<a href="http://glench.com/EyesOnThePrize/">Eyes on the Prize — Exploring active video by Glen Chiacchieri</a>
<p>
(<i>Thanks, <a href="https://twitter.com/swartzcr">Noah</a>!</i>)



]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/annotated-eyes-on-the-prize.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>I can&#039;t wait for this Finnish summer death car&#160;game</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/i-cant-wait-for-this-finnish.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/i-cant-wait-for-this-finnish.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 12:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Leigh Alexander]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[boring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[farming simulator]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[my summer car]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offworld]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sims]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380759</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p><i>My Summer Car</i> is an upcoming game about building your own vehicle in the reputedly "hot, hot, hot" Finnish summer. It also promises absurd difficulty, lots of death, and all-important physics bugs.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/summercar.jpg?resize=1200%2C750" alt="summercar" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380760" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p><i>My Summer Car</i> is an upcoming game about building your own vehicle in the reputedly "hot, hot, hot" Finnish summer. It also promises absurd difficulty, lots of death, and all-important physics bugs. Listen to a man with a wonderful accent show you a weirdly-compelling experience:<span id="more-380759"></span>

<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?t=559&#038;v=r0IZ_TEzg7M--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Ft%3D559%26v%3Dr0IZ_TEzg7M&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fr0IZ_TEzg7M%3Ffeature%3Doembed%26start%3D559%26start%3D559&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fr0IZ_TEzg7M%2Fhqdefault.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="375" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>I've only been to Finland in the winter. I thought I got lost beside a field on my jog through the snow to the ocean, but it turns out the field <i>was</i> the ocean, frozen solid. I was there for a talk, and I was warned in advance not to worry about any jokes I might be telling, as Finns do not laugh in public. 

<p>But lead developer Johannes Rohola's <a href="http://www.johannesrojola.com/msc/"><i>My Summer Car</i></a> site is funny, or at least I think it is -- in a world of <i>user-friendliness</i>, anything that looks like an ancient Geocities website injects joy into my stuttering heart. Maybe it's the bright-red ticker promising "Never seen before true car building and driving simulator!", or the nostalgic UNDER CONSTRUCTION banner. The animated chicken, exploding again and again. 

<p>The list of implemented features promises <i>My Summer Car</i> "does have graphics of some sort" as well as "fully functional dashboard similar to flight simulator." But the list of features the developer is <i>considering</i> implementing is even better:
<blockquote><b>PLANS, BUT NOT PROMISED!</b>
<p>Radio channel
<p>Window stickers, like "More beer"
<p>Extensive damage system, for parts dropping off and wear and tear
<p>Drivable cargo van and rowing boat
<p>Ability to make kilju and sell it to get some cash
<p>Suomi KP/-31 to shoot fishes, cans, or something else
<p>Rallycross-style dirt track
<p>Drunk NPC's
<p>Drag strip and local drag racing events
<p>Able to go to sauna, drink alcohol beverages and get wasted
<p>Lively environment with houses, nature and animals</blockquote>

<p>There are actually a number of ponderous, intensely-detailed (and often budget-constrained) vehicle and machine simulations floating around. Often, the character in these "boring" vehicle simulations comes from the glitches and weirdness that arise when a game with high-level detail is marketed at a niche audience with minimal resources -- and the thriving mod community attracted to that weirdness. <a href="http://www.hopesandfears.com/hopes/culture/video-games/168323-why-simulator-games">This piece my friend Joe Bernardi did on games like <i>Euro Truck Simulator, Farming Simulator</i> and <i>Train Simulator</i></a> is an awesome and fascinating look inside that experience. 

<p>Even better: When you are forced to attend a video game trade show abroad and discover the booth for, say, <i>Farming Simulator</i> - it'll have a life-like, hulking tractor, hopeful-looking staffers, and no attendees (they are instead queuing for flashier things). 
<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/farmsim15.jpg?resize=1000%2C563" alt="farmsim15" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380761" data-recalc-dims="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/i-cant-wait-for-this-finnish.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Who doesn&#039;t miss &#039;90s horror&#160;games?</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/who-doesnt-miss-90s-horror.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/who-doesnt-miss-90s-horror.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 10:55:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Leigh Alexander]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[back in 1995]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[horror games]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[offworld]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380747</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Ah, the tech and the aesthetics of 1990s games. The terrible framerates, indistinct faces and rough edges seem eerie today, perfectly recalling the horror games of a bygone age.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/yD45Ja.gif?resize=480%2C270" alt="yD45Ja" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380752" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>Ah, the tech and the aesthetics of 1990s games. The terrible framerates, indistinct faces and rough edges seem eerie today, perfectly recalling the horror games of a bygone age. If you miss it too, you really need to watch this:<span id="more-380747"></span>

<p>This is the trailer for Takaaki Ichijou's <i>Back in 1995</i>, a horror title set to debut at the Tokyo Indie Fest in early May, <a href="http://www.relyonhorror.com/latest-news/revisit-early-horror-games-with-back-in-1995/">according to Rely on Horror's Andrea Shearon</a>: 

<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nx2ZK_CpGS8--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3Dnx2ZK_CpGS8&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fnx2ZK_CpGS8%3Ffeature%3Doembed&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="281" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<P>The creator intentionally summons long nights spent muscling bluntly around the worlds of <i>Resident Evil, Silent Hill, Parasite EVE</i> and things like that til your palms were sweating and your heart is pounding. Wasn't that fun? Of course it was. Feel free to share your favorite memories by hitting that DISCUSS button right below.

<p>I mean, your memories might be 'everyone said the bad graphics and player's poor sense of control added to the fear environment but bad design is never intentional so let's stop celebrating an era of junk software' but then I also might <i>permanently delete you</i>, so take care. Good memories. It was fun. So good.  

<p>(<a href="http://www.kotaku.co.uk/2015/04/16/horror-game-looks-straight-1995">Thanks to Patrick Klepek for discovering this!</a>) ]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/17/who-doesnt-miss-90s-horror.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chess grandmaster accused of cheating with iPhone in&#160;toilet</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/chess-grandmaster-accused-of-c.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/chess-grandmaster-accused-of-c.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 03:44:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Beschizza]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380706</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Raising suspicions with his frequent trips to the bathroom, Gaioz Nigalidze was searched to no avail. But when they checked the stalls, they found a hidden iPhone.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/black_white_checked_iphone_4_4s_case-r5ab51b7ac2ca4e78bc92e2f6c98f7050_a4643_8byvr_324.jpg?resize=324%2C324" alt="black_white_checked_iphone_4_4s_case-r5ab51b7ac2ca4e78bc92e2f6c98f7050_a4643_8byvr_324" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380708" data-recalc-dims="1" />


<p>Raising suspicions with his frequent trips to the bathroom, Gaioz Nigalidze was searched to no avail. But when they checked the stalls, they found a hidden iPhone. Running a chess app. With his current game set up. <a href="http://www.ksl.com/?sid=34247554">Logged into his Facebook account</a>. 

<blockquote><p>Abdul Rahim removed Nigalidze from the tournament and is sending a report to the International Chess Federation. It has had to create a commission to deal with the growing problems with cheating. In fact, this is not the first time cheating has been attempted.

<p>An American player in 2002 tried the same approach in checking a chess simulation during trips to the bathroom. Indian player Umakant Sharma was caught cheating in 2006 using a small Bluetooth headpiece hidden inside his cloth cap. In 2008, the Dubai Chess Club banned an Iranian player after it was discovered he was receiving text messages from a friend watching a live stream of the game, according to Endgadget's [sic] Mariella Moon.</blockquote>

<p>A three-year suspension from international competition awaits Nigalidze if the accusations are confirmed.]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/chess-grandmaster-accused-of-c.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Haunted Mansion&#160;Lego!</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/haunted-mansion-lego.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/haunted-mansion-lego.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 01:00:57 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Doctorow]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Disney]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fanac]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[happy mutants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haunted mansion]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lego]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380415</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

This Haunted Mansion Lego set is up for your votes -- it's got mine!
<span id="more-380415"></span>


</p><p>

The set includes:
The Disneyland Version of the Haunted Mansion
with 6 (possibly 7) minifigs included.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>
<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/hmlego21.jpg?w=100%25" class="bordered"  data-recalc-dims="1"><br />
This Haunted Mansion Lego set is up for your votes -- it's got mine!
<span id="more-380415"></span>

<blockquote>
<p>
<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/hmlego11.jpg?w=100%25" class="bordered"  data-recalc-dims="1"><br />
The set includes:<br />
The Disneyland Version of the Haunted Mansion<br />
with 6 (possibly 7) minifigs included. (Unfortunately, 999 is just not possible!)
<br /><br />
The Mansion is set on a 32x32 base, (the traditional size for a modular build) which folds open for added playability!
<br /><br />
The inside of the mansion includes memorable scenes such as:<br />*
The Foyer - Contains full versions of the infamous "stretching portraits"<br />*
The Library with it's ever-watchful busts<br />*
The Corridor of Doors<br />*
Madame Leota's Seance Room - Complete with Madame Leota<br />*
The Grand Ballroom - Includes spinning dance platform, organ, and dueling portraits<br />*
The Attic - Has goodies including a piano and several pictures of Constance and her dearly departed(s)
</blockquote>
<p>
<a href="https://ideas.lego.com/projects/61715">
Walt Disney Presents: The Haunted Mansion
</a>
<p>
(<i>Thanks, Sarah!</i>)

]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/haunted-mansion-lego.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Skyglow: Timelapse film dedicated to the need for light-pollution-free skies for&#160;stargazing</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/skyglow-timelapse-film-dedica.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/skyglow-timelapse-film-dedica.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 23:25:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380670</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Imagining an incredible night sky of stars and star trails over the light polluted city of Los Angeles.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://vimeo.com/125108525--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fvimeo.com%2F125108525&#038;src=https%3A%2F%2Fplayer.vimeo.com%2Fvideo%2F125108525&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.vimeocdn.com%2Fvideo%2F515088904_1280.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=vimeo" width="500" height="281" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>
<a href="http://skyglowproject.com/">Gavin Heffernan</a> tells Boing Boing,
<p>



<blockquote><p>
My shooting partner Harun and I just released a wild new experimental timelapse for International Dark Sky Week -- imagining an incredible night sky of stars and star trails over the light polluted city of Los Angeles.<span id="more-380670"></span>


<p>

We're trying to raise awareness for part of a <a href="http://skyglowproject.com/">bigger Kickstarter project we're running until May 9th</a>. Here's <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/50014474@N05/sets/72157649665162693/">an album of stills and behind the scenes pics</a> with captions.<p></blockquote><p>

<div id="attachment_380672" style="width: 1610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/16975445828_982b8e6f1f_h.jpg?resize=1600%2C879" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380672" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380674" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/17137189516_807f12a607_b.jpg?resize=1024%2C575" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380674" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380679" style="width: 1610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/16975591650_bebef94dad_h.jpg?resize=1600%2C1071" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380679" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380678" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/16976960819_b44dd29b91_b.jpg?resize=1024%2C674" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380678" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380677" style="width: 1610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/16975583670_7b13c34e7e_h.jpg?resize=1600%2C1080" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380677" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380676" style="width: 1610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/16975679020_cb7d8891a7_h.jpg?resize=1600%2C885" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380676" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380675" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/16975355898_47983520cf_b.jpg?resize=1024%2C572" alt="Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures" class="size-full wp-image-380675" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Photo: Gavin Heffernan/Sunchaser Pictures</p></div>
<p>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/skyglow-timelapse-film-dedica.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Insane &#039;Star Wars: The Force Awakens&#039; promo: ANA Dreamliner jet painted like&#160;R2-D2</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/ana-sw.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/ana-sw.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 23:11:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380654</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ “Star Wars” fans and aviation geeks, hold on to your butts.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/design01.jpg?resize=1000%2C563" alt="design01" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380659" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<p>

 “Star Wars” fans and aviation geeks, hold on to your butts: Japan’s All Nippon Airways and Disney's “Star Wars” franchise are joining forces, and painting a Boeing 787-9 Dreamliner to look like R2-D2.
<span id="more-380654"></span><p>

<!--https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g70eqOT0LPU--><div class="video-container"><iframe class="embedly-embed" src="//cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3Dg70eqOT0LPU&#038;src=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2Fg70eqOT0LPU%3Ffeature%3Doembed&#038;image=http%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2Fg70eqOT0LPU%2Fhqdefault.jpg&#038;type=text%2Fhtml&#038;schema=youtube" width="500" height="281" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>
<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/design05.jpg?resize=1000%2C563" alt="design05" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380661" data-recalc-dims="1" />
<p>
Jon Ostrower in the WSJ:

<p>

<blockquote><p>The announcement Thursday of the cross-promotion came as “Star Wars” fans gathered in Anaheim, Calif., to hear about the latest developments from cast and crew ahead of the December release of the sequel “Star Wars: The Force Awakens.” Fans were treated to a newly released trailer for the film, which is the first to be released under the ownership of Disney, which purchased Lucasfilm Ltd. in 2012 for $4 billion.
<p>
This isn’t the first time a blockbuster movie franchise has teamed with an airline for a flying billboard. Air New Zealand Ltd. painted several Boeing 777s and 747s for director Peter Jackson’s “Lord of the Rings” and “The Hobbit” trilogies.<p></blockquote>

<p>
This is serious, people. <a href="http://ana-sw.com/detail/index.html">They've launched a website</a>.<p>
"<a href="http://blogs.wsj.com/corporate-intelligence/2015/04/16/all-nippon-dreamliner-to-fly-as-r2-d2-in-star-wars-promotion/?mod=wsj_nview_latest">All Nippon Dreamliner to Fly as R2-D2 in ‘Star Wars’ Promotion</a>" [WSJ.com]

<p><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/design02.jpg?resize=1000%2C563" alt="design02" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380663" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/design04.jpg?resize=1000%2C563" alt="design04" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380664" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/design03.jpg?resize=1000%2C563" alt="design03" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380665" data-recalc-dims="1" />

]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/ana-sw.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hand-painted portraits of famous musicians, on vinyl&#160;records</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/hand-painted-portraits-of-famo.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/hand-painted-portraits-of-famo.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 22:24:28 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380633</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p class="wp-caption-text">David Bowie. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p>

<p>

Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen is hand-painted portraiture of musicians on vinyl records.<span id="more-380633"></span>

 More: <a href="http://vaontherecord.tumblr.com/">vaontherecord.tumblr.com</a>.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_380634" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nmnfyoKqJL1tsf0e9o1_1280.jpg?w=680" alt="David Bowie. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380634" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />David Bowie. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<p>

Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen is hand-painted portraiture of musicians on vinyl records.<span id="more-380633"></span>

 More: <a href="http://vaontherecord.tumblr.com/">vaontherecord.tumblr.com</a>. Here's a video that shows how it's done. Buy one for <a href="http://vinylart.info/">$280 plus shipping</a>.<p>

<!--https://youtu.be/_o7zdo8_Aw0--><div class="video-container"><iframe width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/_o7zdo8_Aw0?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>

<div id="attachment_380635" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_ngpro2KP141tsf0e9o1_500.jpg?w=680" alt="John Lee Hooker. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380635" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />John Lee Hooker. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380636" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nidekeGESC1tsf0e9o1_1280.jpg?w=680" alt="Johnny Cash. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380636" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Johnny Cash. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380637" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nj1hd2K9jE1tsf0e9o1_500.jpg?w=680" alt="Tom Waits. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380637" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Tom Waits. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380638" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nipdedQMwl1tsf0e9o1_500.jpg?w=680" alt="Neil Young. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen."  class="size-full wp-image-380638" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Neil Young. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380639" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nkm8g802Eh1tsf0e9o1_1280.jpg?w=680" alt="Jam Master Jay. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen."  class="size-full wp-image-380639" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Jam Master Jay. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380640" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nl7ph8YtY11tsf0e9o1_1280.jpg?w=680" alt="Mick Jagger. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380640" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Mick Jagger. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380641" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nlitwbHJdV1tsf0e9o1_500.jpg?w=680" alt="Stevie Nicks. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380641" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Stevie Nicks. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380642" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nm7mxsvcGY1tsf0e9o1_500.jpg?w=680" alt="Snoop Dogg. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen."  class="size-full wp-image-380642" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Snoop Dogg. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>

<div id="attachment_380643" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/tumblr_nmc6ruJnJQ1tsf0e9o1_1280.jpg?w=680" alt="Kurt Cobain. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen." class="size-full wp-image-380643" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text"><br />Kurt Cobain. Vinyl Art by Daniel Edlen.</p></div>
<p>


 [via <a href="http://www.crossconnectmag.com/post/116587653028">crossconnectmag.com</a>]]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/hand-painted-portraits-of-famo.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Exotic bird does a great job of imitating video game&#160;sounds</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/exotic-bird-does-a-great-job-o.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/exotic-bird-does-a-great-job-o.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 22:04:49 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380621</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This Curl-crested Jay, a bird in the same family as crows, lives at the Criadouro Onca Pintada breeding center in Brazil.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://youtu.be/jUp6TuYPvbY--><div class="video-container"><iframe width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jUp6TuYPvbY?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

This Curl-crested Jay, a bird in the same family as crows, lives at the Criadouro Onca Pintada breeding center in Brazil.<span id="more-380621"></span>

 He is native to South America and has a great skill: the ability to mimic other birds. And man-made sounds, like the video game he picked up here.
<p>
The action gets intense around 30 seconds in. It is possible that he is a Decepticon.<p>
<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/276C83DA00000578-3033525-image-a-38_1428668386311.jpg?resize=634%2C355" alt="276C83DA00000578-3033525-image-a-38_1428668386311" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380627" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/276C83DE00000578-3033525-image-a-37_1428668377476.jpg?resize=634%2C358" alt="276C83DE00000578-3033525-image-a-37_1428668377476" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380628" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/276C83E200000578-3033525-image-a-36_1428668369912.jpg?resize=634%2C357" alt="276C83E200000578-3033525-image-a-36_1428668369912" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380629" data-recalc-dims="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/exotic-bird-does-a-great-job-o.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Humble Last Gasp&#160;Bundle!</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/humble-last-gasp-bundle.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/humble-last-gasp-bundle.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 22:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Doctorow]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[art]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Book]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Comics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[comix]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ebooks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[happy mutants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[humble bundle]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[publishing]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380406</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

<a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/books">Pay what you like</a> for DRM-free ebooks featuring Basil Wolverton, pop surrealism, Hi-Fructose, Ron English and many more quality titles from our favorite underground press, Last Gasp.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>
<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/s6_ww561.jpg?w=100%25" class="bordered"  data-recalc-dims="1"><br />
<a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/books">Pay what you like</a> for DRM-free ebooks featuring Basil Wolverton, pop surrealism, Hi-Fructose, Ron English and many more quality titles from our favorite underground press, Last Gasp.

<span id="more-380406"></span>

<p>
This sale's nominated charities are EFF and the Comic Book Legal Defense Fund (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_Pirates">fittingly enough</a>!).

<p>
<a href="https://www.humblebundle.com/books">Humble Underground Book Bundle Presented by Last Gasp (pay what you want and help charity)</a>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/humble-last-gasp-bundle.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Star Wars &#039;The Force Awakens&#039; desktop wallpaper-able stills from new teaser&#160;trailer</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/star-wars-the-force-awakens.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/star-wars-the-force-awakens.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 21:41:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Image]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380586</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[STAR WARS: THE FORCE AWAKENS will be in theaters December 18, 2015.
]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DES0095_jpeg_4K_PUB.v02.1114.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380589" data-recalc-dims="1" />


<p>
A handful of stills to sweeten your wallpaper with, from that <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/new-episode-vii-trailer.html">new Episode VII trailer</a> that came out today. <span id="more-380586"></span>

<p>These images are 2,000 pixels wide or larger. <a href="http://www.starwars.com/the-force-awakens/">STAR WARS: THE FORCE AWAKENS</a> will be in theaters December 18, 2015.
<p><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/des0100.4k.PNTfix.v2.1079.jpg?resize=2000%2C838" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380590" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/des0135.PUB_.ana_.final_.1267.jpg?resize=2500%2C1064" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380591" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/des0190.4k_PUB_STILL_PNT.1080.2.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380592" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/des1000.PNT_.1203.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380593" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/des1010.4k.v4.1193.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380594" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/des1020.4k_PUB_STILL_PNT.1179.2.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380595" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DES1040_jpeg_4K_PUB.v01.1171.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380596" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DES1050_jpeg_4K_PUB.v01.1141.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380597" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DES1070_jpeg_4K_PUB.v01.1078.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380598" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DES1080_jpeg_4K_PUB.v01.1074.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380599" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/DEX0020_jpeg_4K_PUB.v01.1117.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380600" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/fc0700.4k_2_35_CROP_PUB_STILL_PNT.1101.4.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380601" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/fc0700.4k_PUB_STILL_PNT.1101.4.jpg?resize=2000%2C1398" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380602" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/fc0710.4k_2_35_CROP_PUB_STILL_PNT.1101.2.jpg?resize=2500%2C1047" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380603" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/fc0710.4k_PUB_STILL_PNT.1101.2.jpg?resize=2500%2C1748" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380604" data-recalc-dims="1" />

<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/pj0010.prstill4k_halfBlur.v097.1170.jpg?resize=2000%2C838" alt="Star Wars: The Force Awakens Ph: Film Frame ©Lucasfilm 2015" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380605" data-recalc-dims="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/star-wars-the-force-awakens.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Probably the best cat GIF&#160;ever</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/probably-the-best-cat-gif-ever.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/probably-the-best-cat-gif-ever.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 21:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380576</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Cat goes on car ride to outer space, mind is blown.<p><span id="more-380576"></span>



Source video, or an umpteenth generation of that source video, is below.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/QLdCnh.gif?resize=200%2C141" alt="QLdCnh" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380577" data-recalc-dims="1" />
Cat goes on car ride to outer space, mind is blown.<p><span id="more-380576"></span>



Source video, or an umpteenth generation of that source video, is below. 

<p>
<img src="http://i0.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/yNM7Xr.gif?resize=483%2C270" alt="yNM7Xr" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380578" data-recalc-dims="1" />
<p>

<!--https://youtu.be/Lc20PKkUAEU--><div class="video-container"><iframe width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Lc20PKkUAEU?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/probably-the-best-cat-gif-ever.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Scythe vs.&#160;Weedwhacker</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/scythe-vs-weedwhacker.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/scythe-vs-weedwhacker.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 21:00:44 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Video]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380566</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>

“This is the British Scythe Champion against an experienced agricultural worker with a three-tine brushcutter, working flat-out.” <span id="more-380566"></span>



</p><p>“Held at the Annual Green Fair and South West Scythe Festival in Somerset, UK, on 13th June, 2010.</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://youtu.be/gsfIHiBB6xE--><div class="video-container"><iframe width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gsfIHiBB6xE?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>

“This is the British Scythe Champion against an experienced agricultural worker with a three-tine brushcutter, working flat-out.” <span id="more-380566"></span>



<p>“Held at the Annual Green Fair and South West Scythe Festival in Somerset, UK, on 13th June, 2010. No trick photography here - he really is that fast.”<p>


<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/ezgif-2716133588.gif?resize=480%2C270" alt="ezgif-2716133588" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380573" data-recalc-dims="1" />
<p>
[via <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/videos">reddit.com/r/videos</a>]]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/scythe-vs-weedwhacker.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ian McKellen pens lovely essay about Beauty and the Beast table&#160;read</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/ian-mckellen-pens-lovely-essay.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/ian-mckellen-pens-lovely-essay.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 20:43:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380367</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The actor is signed on to voice the grumpy clock Cogsworth.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_380371" style="width: 610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/writing.jpg?resize=600%2C233" alt="via Ian McKellen&#039;s website" class="size-medium wp-image-380371" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text">via Ian McKellen's website</p></div>

<p>Disney is adapting <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/04/09/disney-developing-a-live-actio.html" target="_blank">a ton of its classic cartoons</a> into live action movies, including 1991’s Oscar nominated <em>Beauty and the Beast</em>. <span id="more-380367"></span> Sir Ian McKellen is signed on to voice the grumpy clock Cogsworth, and the social media-savvy septuagenarian posted a lovely <a href="https://twitter.com/IanMcKellen/status/588373607618842625" target="_blank">essay to Twitter</a> about the film’s magical table read.</p> 

<!--https://twitter.com/IanMcKellen/status/588373607618842625--><div class="video-container"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet" width="500"><p>&quot;Beauty and the Beast&quot; starts! <a href="http://t.co/nOZ7Nk0KVf">pic.twitter.com/nOZ7Nk0KVf</a></p>&mdash; Ian McKellen (@IanMcKellen) <a href="https://twitter.com/IanMcKellen/status/588373607618842625">April 15, 2015</a></blockquote><script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>

While this particularly piece was posted to Twitter, McKellen also shares his writing on <a href="http://www.mckellen.com/writings/index.htm" target="_blank">his blog</a>. ]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/ian-mckellen-pens-lovely-essay.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bow down to this collection of strong female&#160;characters</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/bow-down-to-this-collection-of.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/bow-down-to-this-collection-of.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 19:43:45 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Caroline Siede]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380385</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[ This basically reads as a checklist of our favorite fictional ladies.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_380387" style="width: 559px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/11478689_1496368_pm-1-e1429162735794.jpg?resize=549%2C226" alt="drawings by Heymonster" class="size-full wp-image-380387" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text">drawings by Heymonster</p></div>

<p>This collection of strong female characters by artist <a href="http://society6.com/heymonster" target="_blank">Heymonster</a> is one of the best things I’ve ever seen. <span id="more-380385"></span> This basically reads as a checklist of my favorite fictional ladies. Personally I'd add C.J. Cregg, Joan Watson, Peggy Carter, Nyota Uhura, B'Elanna Torres, Black Widow, Arwen, Storm, Cristina Yang, Princess Leia, and all the <em>Doctor Who</em> companions to the list, but it's hard to argue with this current line-up.</p>

<div id="attachment_380386" style="width: 560px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="http://i2.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/11478689_1496368_pm.jpg?resize=550%2C670" alt="drawings by Heymonster" class="size-full wp-image-380386" data-recalc-dims="1" /><p class="wp-caption-text">drawings by Heymonster</p></div>

<p>You can see more of Heymonster's work on <a href="http://heymonster.tumblr.com/" target="_blank">Tumblr</a> and order prints (and coffee mugs, phone covers, t-shirts and more!) over on <a href="http://society6.com/heymonster" target="_blank">Society6</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/bow-down-to-this-collection-of.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Parody video: Star Wars + Louie CK =&#160;CHEWIE</title>
		<link>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/parody-video-star-wars-loui.html</link>
		<comments>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/parody-video-star-wars-loui.html#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2015 19:24:24 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Xeni Jardin]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Post]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://boingboing.net/?p=380549</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[<p>Thank you, Nerdist, for making this highly necessary parody happen.<span id="more-380549"></span>

 Story at <a href="http://www.hitfix.com/harpy/247-days-until-star-wars-chewie-is-the-louis-ck-parody-you-didnt-know-you-needed?utm_content=buffer5afaf&#038;utm_medium=social&#038;utm_source=plus.google.com&#038;utm_campaign=buffer">HitFix</a>.</p><p>
</p>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<!--https://youtu.be/cqiPsVlZrl4--><div class="video-container"><iframe width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/cqiPsVlZrl4?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>

<p>Thank you, Nerdist, for making this highly necessary parody happen.<span id="more-380549"></span>

 Story at <a href="http://www.hitfix.com/harpy/247-days-until-star-wars-chewie-is-the-louis-ck-parody-you-didnt-know-you-needed?utm_content=buffer5afaf&#038;utm_medium=social&#038;utm_source=plus.google.com&#038;utm_campaign=buffer">HitFix</a>.<p>
<img src="http://i1.wp.com/boingboing.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/04/KR8ZPX.gif?resize=480%2C270" alt="KR8ZPX" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-380551" data-recalc-dims="1" />]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://boingboing.net/2015/04/16/parody-video-star-wars-loui.html/feed</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

<!-- Dynamic page generated in 0.498 seconds. -->
<!-- Cached page generated by WP-Super-Cache on 2015-04-17 10:34:22 -->
