<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">     
    <channel>      
        <title>Voice of America</title>     
        <link>http://www.voanews.com</link>
        <description>Voice of America is an international news and broadcast organization serving Central and Eastern Europe, the Caucasus, Central Asia, Russia, the Middle East and Balkan countries</description>
        <image>
            <url>http://www.voanews.com/img/voa/rssLogo_VOA.gif</url>
            <title>Voice of America</title>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com</link>
        </image>
        <language>en-US</language>
        <copyright>2012 - VOA</copyright>   
        <ttl>60</ttl>        
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 04:10:37 -0500</lastBuildDate> 
        <generator>Pangea CMS – VOA</generator>        
        <atom:link href="http://www.voanews.com/api/epiqq" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    		<item>
            <title>Philippines Fines Chinese Fishermen $102,000 Each for Poaching</title>
            <description>A Philippine court on Monday fined nine Chinese fishermen $102,000 each after they were caught with hundreds of sea turtles in a disputed shoal in the South China Sea amid a festering territorial standoff between the two sides.


China claims almost all of the South China Sea, believed to be rich with minerals and oil-and-gas deposits. The sea is one of Asia&#39;s biggest possible flashpoints. Brunei, Malaysia, the Philippines, Vietnam and Taiwan also have claims.


Philippine police arrested the fishermen and seized their boat off Half Moon Shoal, a disputed territory in the Spratly Islands within the Philippines&#39; 200-mile exclusive economic zone, in May. Two of the fishermen were sent home because they were minors.


After three months of trial, Judge Ambrosio de Luna found the fishermen guilty of poaching in Philippine waters and of illegal possession of endangered green sea turtles.


It was not immediately clear how the fishermen would find the funds to pay the fines, but they face six months&#39; jail if they fail to pay up, time already served, suggesting they could even be released.


“We&#39;re merely imposing our laws,” Foreign Secretary Albert del Rosario told reporters. “We tried to look for ways to be lenient. I think they will credit whatever time has been served already.”


China protested against the arrests and does not recognize the trial, saying the nine were detained in China&#39;s territorial waters.


IHS Jane&#39;s, a leading defense publication, said on Friday satellite images show China is building an island on a reef elsewhere in the Spratlys large enough to accommodate what could be its first offshore airstrip in the South China Sea.


Del Rosario said the military had been asked to investigate.


The building work, if confirmed, would fly in the face of U.S. calls for a freeze in provocative activity in the South China Sea. Concern is growing about an escalation in disputes even as claimants work to establish a code of conduct to resolve them.


Two Vietnamese frigates were due to arrive in the Philippines on Monday on a goodwill visit, the first time Hanoi has sent warships to the archipelago.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-philippines-fines-chinese-fishermen-102000-each-for-poaching/2531841.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-philippines-fines-chinese-fishermen-102000-each-for-poaching/2531841.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 03:35:11 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Asia</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Reuters)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-philippines-fines-chinese-fishermen-102000-each-for-poaching/2531841.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Cambodian PM Defends Australia Refugee Deal</title>
            <description>Cambodian Prime Minister Hun Sen is trying to ease concerns over the social and economic costs of the country&#39;s plan with Australia to receive refugees. U.S.-based Human Rights Watch has called for the deal to be halted until Cambodia improves its refugee support system.


Hun Sen spoke out in defense of the refugee resettlement program in a letter he wrote last week to opposition politician Kem Sokha, the National Assembly’s first deputy president.


Cambodia’s Phnom Penh Post newspaper published details of the letter Monday, reporting the prime minister defended Cambodia’s ability to host the refugees, saying some 85 asylum seekers in a 2009 program from countries including Pakistan, Sudan, Myanmar and Vietnam have already been resettled.


He said services for the new arrivals would all be paid for by Australia through the $35 million resettlement program.


The agreement signed in September has been widely criticized by rights groups and the U.N. high commissioner for refugees, who have said that refugees in Cambodia already face steep financial and logistical hardships in the impoverished country.


Elaine Pearson, Australian director at Human Rights Watch, said Cambodia needs to reform its refugee resettlement program before people arrive under the Australian deal.


&quot;The experience in Cambodia has been quite bad for these existing refugees. I mean they faced all sorts of problems. None of them have been offered proper residency documents and as a result at every step of the get-go they have to pay petty corruption and fines. A lot of them are unemployed, they are just staying at home. They don&#39;t want to be at risk of having to pay money to the Cambodian authorities,&quot; said Pearson.


Refugees that qualify for the Cambodia resettlement are presently housed on the Pacific island Nauru. They were already rejected for asylum status by Canberra under the Australian government&#39;s tougher policy towards people who arrive via boat.


Australia has been working in recent years to make it more difficult for asylum-seekers to reach its shores, arguing that many of the boat arrivals are economic migrants, not people in need of asylum. Authorities have also said that by cracking down on boat arrivals, they are discouraging human smugglers from making dangerous sea voyages.


Australia is planning to fund temporary accommodation and resettlement services for those refugees who voluntarily go to Cambodia, for at least one year, and then support on a case-by-case basis. Australia says it will also provide health insurance over five years.


But refugees in Cambodia have only an interim document - a prakas - confirming a right to stay in Cambodia, but insufficient for other official purposes, including opening a bank account.


Senator Sarah Hanson-Young, a member of the Green Party in Australia&#39;s parliament, conducted a week-long assessment in Cambodia this month and said the country is ill-equipped to deal with the needs of another group of vulnerable people.


&quot;No matter whether they are legally here on the government books they won&#39;t be given jobs, they won&#39;t have access to local services without any type of formal recognized community ID card, they won&#39;t even be able to buy a sim card, buy a motorbike, open a bank account so someone could send them some money. They&#39;re being set up to fail,&quot; said Hanson-Young.


An Australian Catholic nun, Sister Denise Coghlan, who has worked in Cambodia since 1990, said the refugees will need trauma counseling, given the impact of detention in the Nauru camp and adjustment to Cambodia. Sister Coghlan fears Australia is setting a precedent in its dealings with refugees.


&quot;I am really ashamed of Australia for offloading its responsibilities anywhere, but it&#39;s difficult to understand why they choose some of the poorest countries with a lot of poor people, to provide another group of people who will struggle in the beginning. I feel badly about that.&#160; Australia is setting an incredibly dangerous precedent if it starts selling off refugees,&quot; she said.


The Human Rights Watch report called on Australia to closely monitor implementation of the scheme and for the Cambodian government to work with relevant U.N. agencies and non-government groups to ensure the refugees are treated fairly and provide official assistance.&#160;
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/cambodian-pm-defends-australia-refugee-deal/2531839.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/cambodian-pm-defends-australia-refugee-deal/2531839.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 03:28:30 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Asia</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Ron Corben)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/cambodian-pm-defends-australia-refugee-deal/2531839.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/411E3DF7-21F3-440E-BF78-05B71CE1875B_cx0_cy37_cw0_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>World Powers, Iran Make Final Push at Nuclear Talks Deadline</title>
            <description>The foreign ministers of Iran and a group of six world powers have reached the final day of their self-imposed, year-long period to agree on a comprehensive deal to ensure Iran&#39;s nuclear program is peaceful.


Officials from both sides said Sunday they are considering the idea of extending the talks in Vienna beyond Monday, just as they did in July when their original six-month deadline came with no deal.


U.S. Secretary of State John Kerry said Monday morning he will meet with Chinese Foreign Minister Wang Yi to discuss the status of the negotiations, and would be holding other meetings later.


Their so-called P5+1 counterparts from Britain, France, Russia and Germany are also in Vienna, as is Iranian Foreign Minister Javad Zarif. The diplomats have held various sideline meetings as they try to finalize the long-sought goal of ensuring Iran is not developing nuclear weapons in exchange for lifting sanctions that have hurt the country&#39;s economy.


Iran has insisted its nuclear program is solely for peaceful, civilian purposes, such as medical research and generating power.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/world-powers-iran-make-final-push-nuclear-talks-deadline/2531836.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/world-powers-iran-make-final-push-nuclear-talks-deadline/2531836.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 03:22:44 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Middle East</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/world-powers-iran-make-final-push-nuclear-talks-deadline/2531836.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/6A778F3A-BB24-4202-8EDD-95BFE070C36F_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>British Banker Fit to Stand Trial in Hong Kong Murders</title>
            <description>A Hong Kong court has ruled that a British banker accused of killing two Indonesian women is fit to stand trial after he underwent a psychiatric examination.


The judge also adjourned the pre-trial hearing in Rurik Jutting&#39;s case until July 6 to give prosecutors more time to examine evidence.


Jutting, who had worked for Bank of America in Hong Kong, was arrested earlier this month after police found the bodies of two women in his apartment.&#160; One was stuffed into a suitcase on his balcony.


Jutting has yet to enter a plea.&#160; He will remain in custody until his next hearing in July.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/british-banker-fit-to-stand-trial-in-hong-kong-murders/2531822.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/british-banker-fit-to-stand-trial-in-hong-kong-murders/2531822.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 01:56:07 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Asia</category><category>Europe</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/british-banker-fit-to-stand-trial-in-hong-kong-murders/2531822.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/EC3ABF33-BE59-4635-9FAF-A29D187F4C87_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Oil Price Seen Falling to $60 if OPEC Output Not Cut</title>
            <description>Oil prices could plunge to $60 a barrel if OPEC does not agree a significant output cut when it meets in Vienna this week, market players say.


Brent crude futures have fallen 34 percent since June to touch a four-year low of $76.76 a barrel on Nov. 14, and could tumble further if OPEC does not agree to cut at least 1 million barrels per day (bpd), commodity fund managers say.


“The market would question the credibility of OPEC and its influence on global oil markets if there was no cut,” said Daniel Bathe, of Lupus alpha Commodity Invest Fund.


That could send Brent down to around $60, Bathe said.


“Herding behavior and a shift to net negative speculative positions should accelerate the price plunge,” he added.


Fund managers are divided over whether OPEC will reach an agreement on cutting output. Bathe put the likelihood at no more than 50 percent.


The oil price has been falling since the summer due to abundant supply -- partly from U.S. shale oil -- and low demand growth, particularly in Europe and Asia.


As a result, some investors believe a small cut -- of around 500,000 bpd -- would not be enough to calm the markets.


Doug King, chief investment officer of RCMA Capital, sees Brent falling to $70, even with a cut of 1 million bpd.


If OPEC fails to agree a cut, prices will drop “further and quite quickly,” with U.S. crude possibly sliding to $60, he said. U.S. crude closed at $76.51 on Friday, with Brent just above $80.


‘Oil war’


With member states struggling to balance budgets, many OPEC countries will be pushing for an output cut.


“Prices below $80 are putting significant strain on the cartel&#39;s weakest members such as Venezuela,” said Nicolas Robin, a commodities fund manager at Threadneedle.


He said a bigger cut -- of 1 million bpd or more -- was an “outlier scenario,” but such a move would rapidly push prices above $85.


“A move higher would likely be accelerated by the lack of liquidity owing to the U.S. [Thanksgiving] holiday next week,” Robin added.


Doug Hepworth of Gresham Investment Management said: “A surprise significant cut, say of 2 million bpd, is needed to push prices back up to $80. And that would have to be accompanied by some new-found discipline in the non-Saudi members.”


The market has been awash with conspiracy theories as to why Saudi Arabia has not already intervened. New York Times columnist Thomas Friedman hinted at “a global oil war under way pitting the United States and Saudi Arabia on one side against Russia and Iran on the other.”


Tom Nelson, of Investec Global Energy Fund, said Saudi Arabia had allowed the price to fall to incentivize the smaller OPEC producers, which often rely on the biggest producer to intervene, to join Riyadh in cutting output.


“They (the Saudis) want to cut but they don&#39;t want to cut alone,” Nelson said, adding that a cut of between 1 million and 1.5 million bpd should be sufficient to balance the market.


“The market really wants to see that OPEC is still functioning... if there is a small cut, with an accompanying statement of coherence from OPEC that presents a united front, and talks about seeing demand recovery, and some moderation of supply growth, then Brent could move up to $80-$90.”
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-oil-price-seen-falling-to-60-is-opec-output-not-cut/2531810.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-oil-price-seen-falling-to-60-is-opec-output-not-cut/2531810.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 01:16:34 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Economy</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Reuters)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-oil-price-seen-falling-to-60-is-opec-output-not-cut/2531810.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/F6E53316-68E5-4DB9-AA74-12C8D1B444A3_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Nigeria’s Opposition APC Implicates Ruling Party in Office Raid</title>
            <description>Nigeria’s main opposition All Progressives Congress (APC) party said security forces raided its Lagos offices Saturday, destroying more than a dozen party computers and documents.


The Nigerian State Security Service (SSS) reportedly confirmed the raid, but said it was investigating an alleged duplication of voters’ cards currently being issued by the independent Electoral Commission for next year’s general elections.&#160;


APC spokesman Lai Mohammed likened the invasion to the Watergate scandal leading to the resignation of U.S.&#160;President Richard Nixon in 1974.


He accused the ruling Peoples Democratic Party (PDP) of ordering the raid to “illegally” get hold of APC voter registration strength.


“You may wish to remember that, a couple of months ago, our party embarked on a nationwide registration exercise in which several millions of Nigerians were registered as members of our party. &#160;We subsequently set up six centers all over the country to input and gather all the information, so that we can have the data base. It is one of these data offices in Lagos that the security agents invaded,” he said.


Mohammed said that&#160;if the government had any information of illegal activities, it should have obtained a court order to search the premises.


“The official explanation by the government is that they had information that we were using that office to print illegal voters’ card[s].&#160;And, I questioned it and said, ‘Why didn’t you go to court and get a court order to make a search? Why would you come in the middle of the night armed to the teeth, intimidating and harassing our staff and carting our information?’” Mohammed said.


He said the APC will sue the federal government for damages. &#160;He also called for an independent investigation.


Olisa Metuh, national publicity secretary of the PDP, said the APC is crying wolf because it has no winnable message for the people of Nigeria ahead of the 2015 general elections.


“The APC has not been able to get its message across to Nigerians on what they stand for and what they want to change, and they’ve engaged in the past few months [in]&#160;diversionary tactics, crying wolf and making imaginary cases,” Metuh said.


Mohammed described as unfortunate last Thursday’s incident when Speaker Aminu Tambuwal of Nigeria’s parliament was tear gassed as police tried to stop him and other members from entering the parliament.


He accused President Goodluck Jonathan of ordering security forces to arrest the speaker.


“The president is so desperate for re-election that he would stop at nothing to be re-elected.&#160;He was the one who asked the speaker of the House [of Representatives]&#160;to reconvene to debate his own request for extension of the state of emergency in three northeastern states. &#160;Yet, it was his own police that ambushed the speaker and prevented him from getting access into chambers until the members forced their way into the national assembly,” Mohammed said.




&#160;




&#160;
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/nigeria-opposition-apc-implicates-ruling-party-in-office-raid/2531807.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/nigeria-opposition-apc-implicates-ruling-party-in-office-raid/2531807.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 01:03:57 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Africa</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (James Butty)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/nigeria-opposition-apc-implicates-ruling-party-in-office-raid/2531807.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/157E0FB1-EB41-41C0-8A4F-78C1130CC77E_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Astronauts Dock at International Space Station</title>
            <description>A Russian Soyuz spacecraft carrying Italy&#39;s first female astronaut has safely docked with the International Space Station.


The U.S. space agency NASA said Samantha Cristoforetti, along with Russians Anton Shkaplerov and American Terry Virts, arrived at the space station Monday nearly six hours after taking off from Russia&#39;s space facility in Kazakhstan. They will remain on the station until May.


The Russian news agency Itar Tass says the astronauts brought 15 cans of caviar to the station to use in the New Year&#39;s celebration on the station.


The newly arrived astronauts are joining three other astronauts, one American and two Russians, already on the space station - Barry Wilmore, Alexander Samoukutyaev and Elena Serova.


Since the retirement of the U.S. space shuttle fleet in 2011, Russian Soyuz spacecraft have served as the only means to ferry crew to and from the space outpost.&#160;
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/astronauts-dock-at-international-space-station/2531796.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/astronauts-dock-at-international-space-station/2531796.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 23:38:48 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Science &amp; Technology</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/astronauts-dock-at-international-space-station/2531796.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/D0CDC705-60D3-4A04-9D02-96F1B429FC6B_cx0_cy6_cw0_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>With Federer, Switzerland Wins First Davis Cup</title>
            <description>He has won all the Grand Slam tennis titles, the ATP Tour finals multiple times, an Olympic gold medal - and during his career spent 302 weeks as the No. 1 ranked player in the world. But until Sunday, 33-year-old Roger Federer of Switzerland had never won a Davis Cup championship. Federer scored the decisive point in the best-of-five match Davis Cup by beating Richard Gasquest of host France in straight sets.


On the indoor red clay court in Lille, tennis history was made as Switzerland became the 14th different nation to win the Davis Cup.


Roger Federer played a match of stunning proportions to beat Richard Gasquet in the first reverse singles, 6-4, 6-2, 6-2, and that was the third point the Swiss needed, having come into the final day with a 2-1 advantage over France.&#160; Gasquet was not scheduled for the reverse singles, but an injured Jo-Wilfried Tsonga was not able to play.


But the way Federer played, even if the Frenchman had been fit, it would have been like climbing the Swiss Alps. Federer never faced a break point in the match. He was so dominating.


&quot;Everything feels a bit slightly different, but at the end it&#39;s a tennis match. You feel great emotions. You&#39;re unbelievably happy and relieved. It&#39;s definitely one of the better feelings in my career, no doubt about it, and it&#39;s so much nicer to celebrate it all together,&quot; said Federer.


On a personal point, this was the only major trophy that had eluded Federer.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/federer-switzerland-davis-cup-win/2531739.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/federer-switzerland-davis-cup-win/2531739.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 21:07:15 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Europe</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Craig Gabriel)</author><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/8B889649-F681-401F-8D8E-46C1DF464D21_cx0_cy2_cw0_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Military Gets Key Posts in Burkina Faso&#39;s New Cabinet</title>
            <description>Burkina Faso&#39;s military has held on to powerful posts in a new Cabinet unveiled Sunday, three weeks after the army took over following a popular revolt.


Lieutenant Colonel Isaac Zida will remain prime minister and also take over as defense minister. The military likewise will have control of four other ministries: Interior and Territorial Administration, Sports, Environment, and Mines.


Interim civilian President Michel Kafando also will serve as foreign minister.


Burkina Faso&#39;s former president, Blaise Compaore, was forced from power by mass protests in October, after he sought to amend the constitution to prolong his 27-year rule.


The military, led by Colonel Zida, assumed control of the country but was pressured by the African Union to cede power to a civilian president who will rule until elections in 2015.


Under the terms of a transitional charter agreed earlier this month, neither Colonel Zida nor Kafando is eligible to run for president next year.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/military-gets-key-posts-in-burkina-faso-new-cabinet/2531727.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/military-gets-key-posts-in-burkina-faso-new-cabinet/2531727.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 20:31:02 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Africa</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/military-gets-key-posts-in-burkina-faso-new-cabinet/2531727.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/3F0C1481-3FFB-429D-AFB1-1A1C1A9B477C_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Obama Resolute on Immigration Executive Order</title>
            <description>Once again, President Barack Obama is defending his executive order shielding millions of undocumented immigrants from deportation, as Republican lawmakers decry the move but have yet to specify what, if anything, they plan to do in response. VOA’s Michael Bowman reports from Washington.</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/media/video/obama-resolute-on-immigration-executive-order/2531698.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/media/video/obama-resolute-on-immigration-executive-order/2531698.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 19:27:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>USA</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Michael Bowman)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/media/video/obama-resolute-on-immigration-executive-order/2531698.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/171db530-f1c5-462f-9879-7d646072a2ff_tv_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Aung San Suu Kyi: Myanmar Opposition to Keep Pushing for Constitutional Change</title>
            <description>Myanmar opposition leader Aung San Suu Kyi says she and her supporters will continue pushing to amend a constitutional clause that bars her from running for president next year.


In an exclusive interview with the VOA&#39;s Burmese Service Sunday, the Nobel laureate said it is vital that she and her supporters continue to lobby for change.


&quot;We never expected it to be easy but believed it to be possible. The question is when. If we can change the constitution earlier, it is better for the country. We need the courage and ability to change whatever needs to be changed for the betterment of the country,&quot; said pro-democracy icon Aung San Suu Kyi.


She also said her National League for Democracy (NLD) is ready for all the people of Myanmar, also known as Burma, to have a say on the matter.


&quot;Then why don’t you call for a nationwide referendum? We are more than ready for that. In that way, you can find out others’ opinions as well,&quot; she added.


Aung San Suu Kyi was responding to Myanmar Army Chief Min Aung Hlaing, who was dismissive of an NLD effort that collected five million signatures in support of amending the constitution.




In an exclusive and rare interview with VOA Saturday, General Min Aung Hlaing said the constitutional clause in question is not aimed specifically at Aung San Suu Kyi.


&quot;This limitation does not aim at one particular individual or one group or one ethnic group, but covers the whole nation. Another problem is - we have to consider the situations that existed since the pre-independence period, and we have lots of immigration problems as we are a country between extremely populated countries,&quot; said he.


The clause in question bars anyone from becoming president if they have a spouse or child that is a citizen of a foreign country. Aung San Suu Kyi is banned because her two sons are British. Her late husband was also a British citizen.


Official push-back


When asked whether he might meet one-on-one with Aung San Suu Kyi, General&#160;Min Aung Hlaing called such a discussion with the National League for Democracy leader &quot;difficult,&quot; saying her political intentions may not be the same as his. But he said he would not rule out the possibility of a meeting, saying they may hold one if necessary.


The powerful armed forces chief reportedly held discussions with Aung San Suu Kyi for the first time late last month during unprecedented talks among 14 of Myanmar&#39;s political rivals and military leaders. The talks led to commitments to discuss political reforms and peace negotiations.


But many opposition figures criticized the meeting as a means of avoiding meaningful dialogue.


Aung San Suu Kyi later demanded four-party talks with President Thein Sein, General Hlaing and the speaker of the House.


But President Thein Sein appeared to dismiss the idea in an interview with VOA Thursday at the presidential residence.


&quot;Discussion is the right way [to find a political solution], but only among the four of us is not inclusive enough,&quot; he said.


Thein Sein, a 69-year-old retired army general, has been president of Myanmar since 2011, following a four-year stint as prime minister. Before that, Myanmar had been under absolute military control for nearly five decades - from 1962 until 2010.


Thein Sein told VOA he has not decided whether to run for a second term next year.


This report was produced in collaboration with VOA’s Burmese Service.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/aung-san-suu-kyi-says-myanmar-opposition-to-keep-pushing-for-constitutional-change/2531605.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/aung-san-suu-kyi-says-myanmar-opposition-to-keep-pushing-for-constitutional-change/2531605.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 18:32:38 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Asia</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Than Lwin Htun)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/aung-san-suu-kyi-says-myanmar-opposition-to-keep-pushing-for-constitutional-change/2531605.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/E2DA81FB-B479-4CC9-9B61-81A8A8919738_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Iranian-British Woman Volleyball Protester Released on Bail</title>
            <description>Iranian authorities have granted bail to a British-Iranian woman jailed earlier this month for trying to attend a men&#39;s volleyball match despite laws banning women from men&#39;s sporting events.


Family members of 25-year-old Ghoncheh Ghavami say she was released on bail Sunday ahead of an appeal.


Ghavami was detained in June after trying to attend a men&#39;s volleyball match between Iran and Italy.


On November 2, a Tehran court sentenced her to one year in jail for propagating against the ruling system.


Ghavami is reported to be staying with her family in Tehran until the court of appeal rules on her sentence.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/iranian-british-woman-volleyball-protester-released-on-bail/2531515.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/iranian-british-woman-volleyball-protester-released-on-bail/2531515.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 18:04:11 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Middle East</category><category>Europe</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/iranian-british-woman-volleyball-protester-released-on-bail/2531515.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/75039647-60A8-44C4-B1B9-9D7CAF27EC43_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Last Parts of MH17 Wreckage Cleared From E. Ukraine</title>
            <description>Dutch air crash investigators have completed their recovery of the wreckage of a Malaysia Airlines passenger jet that was downed over rebel-held territory in eastern Ukraine four months ago.


Workers sent the last pieces of the airliner on a train Sunday from the area controlled by pro-Russian separatists to the Ukrainian government-held city of Kharkiv. From there, the pieces will be transported to the Netherlands, where authorities are reconstructing the aircraft as part of their investigation.


All 298 people aboard the July 17 flight from Amsterdam to Kuala Lumpur – two-thirds of them from the Netherlands – were killed in the crash.


Authorities believe the aircraft was downed by a surface-to-air missile supplied by Russia and fired from rebel-held territory. Moscow has blamed Ukraine&#39;s air force for shooting down the jet.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/malaysia-jet-wreckage-cleared-from-ukraine/2531467.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/malaysia-jet-wreckage-cleared-from-ukraine/2531467.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 15:15:15 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Asia</category><category>Europe</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/1E428C6F-2112-48CC-AE8B-78446B2FCD9E_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Biden Wraps Up Visit to Turkey</title>
            <description>U.S. Vice President Joe Biden and his wife met Sunday with Ecumenical Patriarch Bartholomew, spiritual leader of the world&#39;s Orthodox Christians, during the last day of his visit to Turkey.


The Bidens visited the Church of St. George, a Greek-Orthodox cathedral in Istanbul, known as Constantinople during the Byzantine era, before heading to the historic Suleymaniye Mosque, the largest in the city.






Biden arrived in Istanbul on Friday for talks with Turkish leaders on the crisis in Syria.


Biden said Saturday that he and Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan discussed a Syrian transition of power away from the Bashar al-Assad regime during a four-hour meeting earlier in the day.


He said they also talked about denying Islamic State militants a safe haven in Iraq and Syria.


In the past, Erdogan has insisted if the U.S. wants Turkish help, it must focus less on fighting IS extremists and more on toppling the Assad regime. On Saturday, he said Turkey will continue working closely with the United States, and he called Biden&#39;s visit &quot;very meaningful.&quot;


Biden said the United States will continue to help Turkey cope with the humanitarian crisis created by 1.6 million Syrian refugees flooding into Turkish refugee camps.


Meanwhile the White House announced the U.S. will give $135 million in additional humanitarian assistance to help Turkey and other nations care for refugees fleeing violence in Syria.


Most of that funding is slated for the World Food Program, to be used for household food rations and food vouchers for refugees. Nearly $11 million of the funds will go to support the World Food Program in Turkey.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/biden-wraps-up-visit-to-turkey/2531409.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/biden-wraps-up-visit-to-turkey/2531409.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 13:47:15 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>USA</category><category>Europe</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/biden-wraps-up-visit-to-turkey/2531409.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/D7A9CF52-F675-4822-9269-AF4091295DC9_cx0_cy10_cw0_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>November 23, 2014</title>
            <description>A look at the best news photos from around the world.</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/media/photogallery/november-23-2014-day-in-photos/2531391.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/media/photogallery/november-23-2014-day-in-photos/2531391.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 13:23:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Day in Photos</category><comments>http://www.voanews.com/media/photogallery/november-23-2014-day-in-photos/2531391.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/3BCD2063-9141-445C-A5C8-077BB6223A92_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Kenya Security Kills Over 100 Attackers Behind Bus Ambush</title>
            <description>Kenyan security forces have pursued and killed more than 100 militants and destroyed their camp in Somalia after the ambush of a Nairobi-bound bus that killed 28 people, Deputy President William Ruto said on Sunday.


Somalia&#39;s Islamist al-Shabab militants have claimed responsibility for the attack on Saturday, when gunmen ordered passengers on the bus to recite Koran verses and shot dead non-Muslims - 19 men and nine women - who could not.


The group said the killing outside Mandera, a town in the far northeast near the Somali and Ethiopian borders, was in retaliation for raids on mosques in the southern port city of Mombasa.


Kenyan police said on Saturday that security forces pursued the attackers as they fled to Somalia after the ambush.


“Two successful operations were carried out against the perpetrators of these murderous executions across the border. Our retaliatory action left in its trail more than 100 fatalities,” Ruto told a news conference in Nairobi.


Ruto said a camp used by the attackers and four “technicals” - pick-up trucks mounted with guns - were also destroyed.


“Our message to them is clear - you may sneak and attack innocent civilians. But for any attack on Kenya and its people, we shall pursue you wherever you go,” Ruto said.


Saturday&#39;s attacks drew international condemnation from Somalia, Britain, the United States and the United Nations.


Former prime minister Raila Odinga called on the government to do more to counter the country&#39;s deteriorating security.


“When can we expect an end to this desperate state of affairs? Where is the bottom?” Odinga, now an opposition leader, asked in a statement.


Last week, police in Mombasa shot dead one man and arrested almost 400 others when they raided four mosques that they said were being used to recruit militants and store weapons.


Al-Shababkilled at least 67 people in a gun and grenade raid on a Nairobi shopping mall last September, saying it was revenge for attacks on its fighters by Kenyan troops in Somalia.


That and other attacks in the past year on the coast and in Nairobi have prompted Western nations to issue travel warnings, hitting the tourism industry.


Experts have blamed poor command structures andintelligence sharing for Kenya&#39;s problems fighting the militants in the past, but Ruto said improved coordination had assured the success of the weekend raid against the attackers.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-kenya-security-kills-over-100-attakers-behind-bus-ambush/2531399.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-kenya-security-kills-over-100-attakers-behind-bus-ambush/2531399.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 13:18:04 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Africa</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Reuters)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/reu-kenya-security-kills-over-100-attakers-behind-bus-ambush/2531399.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/91D77CCB-52FF-4AD0-8FFD-4E0A10BE2D77_cx0_cy5_cw0_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Obama&#39;s Immigration Moves Debated on TV Talk Shows</title>
            <description>U.S. President Barack Obama has dismissed criticism of his executive order changing how the country deals with some undocumented immigrants, urging Republican lawmakers to pass a bill if they are not satisfied with his unilateral action.


Opponents of the president&#39;s actions joined Obama in taking to the Sunday-morning television talk shows to make their respective cases.


In an interview on ABC&#39;s &quot;This Week,&quot; the president said it was important to prioritize the deportation of felons, criminals and recent arrivals over people who have lived here illegally more than five years.


Watch related video by VOA&#39;s Michael Bowman:






Asked about criticism by House Speaker John Boehner, Obama said his response is &quot;pass a bill.&quot;


And in his weekly address Saturday, Obama repeated points he made in announcing the immigration plan Thursday. He said it will &quot;bring more undocumented immigrants out of the shadows so they can play by the rules, pay their full share of taxes, pass a criminal background check and get right with the law.&quot;


Obama criticized


On &quot;Fox News Sunday,&quot; Republican Senator Ted Cruz of Texas objected to Obama&#39;s unilateral move.&#160;


&quot;Essentially, he&#39;s gotten [into] the job of counterfeiting immigration papers, because there&#39;s no legal authority to do what he&#39;s doing,&quot; Cruz said. Later, he called the action &quot;a stunning and sad display of a president declining to honor his constitutional obligation to take care that the laws be faithfully executed.&quot;


On CNN&#39;s &quot;State of the Nation,&quot; Republican Senator Lindsey Graham of South Carolina acknowledged his party was also responsible for failing to prod immigration legislation in the House of Representatives.


&quot;I&#39;m disappointed in my country, my party and my president&quot; on immigration, Graham said.


And on CBS&#39; &quot;Face the Nation,&quot; Obama found a strong ally in Representative Luis Gutierrez, an Illinois Democrat.


He said Republicans opposed to the newly approved reforms &quot;have 180 days, starting January 1, before the first person applies for a work permit under the president&#39;s executive authority. What I&#39;d say to them: Roll up your sleeves.&quot;


The president has said he was forced to act because the Republican-controlled House of Representatives would not take up legislation that had passed the Democrat-controlled Senate more than a year ago.


It became even more unlikely that Congress would pass a comprehensive immigration reform bill after this month&#39;s midterm elections, which saw Republicans strengthen their control of the House and gain a majority in the Senate. The new Congress takes office in January.


Orders begin reforms


The two executive orders, signed Friday, will begin the process of offering temporary work permits and lift the threat of deportation for nearly 5 million undocumented immigrants.&#160;




Boehner has said Obama &quot;is damaging the presidency&quot; by bypassing Congress to take executive action on immigration.&#160;


Obama said Saturday his order is not amnesty, &quot;no matter how often&quot; critics say it is. Amnesty, he said, is &quot;the immigration system we have today: millions of people living here without paying their taxes or playing by the rules.&quot;


Mexican President Enrique Pena Nieto praised Obama&#39;s executive orders Friday, calling them &quot;an act of justice.&quot;
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/obama-defends-immigration-action/2531367.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/obama-defends-immigration-action/2531367.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 12:58:55 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>USA</category><category>Americas</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/obama-defends-immigration-action/2531367.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/71C4DB58-7A5E-4868-BCCE-6CFF61A3F212_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Israeli Cabinet Declares Country Nation-State of Jewish People</title>
            <description>The Israeli Cabinet has approved a contentious legislative proposal declaring Israel as the nation-state of the Jewish people.


A divided Cabinet approved the measure Sunday, but it still must be approved by parliament to become law. The bill calls for recognizing Israel&#39;s Jewish character and would institutionalize Jewish law, while removing Arabic as an official language.


Critics say the legislation would undermine the democratic character of Israel, where Arabs comprise about 20 percent of the population. They have strongly opposed the bill.


Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu favors the measure. He says it would &quot;uphold the individual rights of all of Israel&#39;s citizens,&quot; but that only Jews would have the right of self-determination in the country.


He said only Jews would have the right to immigrate to the country, which he described as their &quot;one and only state.&quot;


Material for this report came from AP, AFP, and Reuters.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/israeli-cabinet-declares-the-country-the-nation-state-of-the-jewish-people/2531356.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/israeli-cabinet-declares-the-country-the-nation-state-of-the-jewish-people/2531356.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 12:29:32 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Middle East</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/israeli-cabinet-declares-the-country-the-nation-state-of-the-jewish-people/2531356.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/3B5E9054-55D7-477C-BC74-E56CFBA0CB8E_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Ukraine Marks Anniversary of Deadly 1930s Famine</title>
            <description>During a commemoration for millions who died of starvation in Ukraine in the early 1930s, President Petro Poroshenko lashed out at Soviet-era totalitarianism for causing the deaths and accused today’s Russian-backed rebels in the east of using similar tactics. VOA’s Daniel Shearf reports from Kyiv.</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/media/video/ukraine-marks-anniversary-of-deadly-1930s-famine/2531321.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/media/video/ukraine-marks-anniversary-of-deadly-1930s-famine/2531321.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 11:32:00 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Europe</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (Daniel Schearf)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/media/video/ukraine-marks-anniversary-of-deadly-1930s-famine/2531321.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/f0463a85-440c-424a-989b-a61be5461a1a_tv_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        <item>
            <title>Iraqi Forces Defend Ramadi from IS</title>
            <description>Arab media say Iraqi government forces are resisting an offensive by Islamic State militants in the Anbar provincial capital of Ramadi Sunday, while making gains in nearby Diyala Province.&#160; As the bitter conflict goes on, Sunni tribesmen are calling for more arms and air support from the government.


Iraqi government aircraft fired on Islamic State attackers in the Anbar provincial capital of Ramadi Sunday, as Sunni tribesmen battled to defeat a multi-pronged attack by the militants.


Tribal leaders claim to be holding off the militants who are trying to infiltrate government-held parts of the city.


Anbar Provincial Council Head Sabah al-Karhout said Islamic State is waging a bitter battle for the city.


He says the security threat against Ramadi Sunday is dire. He indicated that Sunni tribesmen were fighting the militants and have received four plane-loads of arms from the government, but need still more.


Al Arabiya TV reported Prime Minister Haidar al-Abadi discussed the issue of arming Sunni tribesmen with Anbar officials Sunday.


Parliament Speaker Selim al-Jabouri, a Sunni, demanded the government arm Anbar&#39;s Sunni tribesmen during a press conference in the Jordanian capital Amman on Sunday.


He says the tribes have all helped to defend Anbar province against Islamic State terrorists, and there has been a running dispute with the Iraqi government leaders on how to arm these tribes and pay them. He adds that some arms have come, but not enough and that more are needed.


James Denselow, research associate at the London-based Foreign Policy Center, tells VOA that with government forces making progress in parts of the country, the dilemma now centers on how to arm the military without having those weapons fall into the hands of Islamic State.


“You&#39;ve got the Iraqi prime minister leading the way with a Christmas shopping list to the Americans,&quot; he said. &quot;I think he&#39;s asked for 175 MA1 Abrams tanks, 146 Stryker vehicles, 50 Bradley fighting [vehicles]. It&#39;s a long, long list now, which all comes into this notion that the time now as [President] Obama said last week is for the offensive to begin, and for any offensive to begin there needs to be weapons.”


&#160;US plans to arm Sunni tribesmen


A Pentagon document prepared for Congress calls for the U.S. to buy arms for the tribesmen, including AK-47s, rocket-propelled grenade launchers, grenades and mortars, if the spending request is approved. The U.S. has launched hundreds of airstrikes against the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria, while deploying more than 3,000 advisers to assist Iraqi troops. But it has not dispatched ground troops and says it has no plans to.


In other developments Sunday, Iraqi forces reported success against Islamic State fighters in Diyala province.&#160; Kurdish peshmerga captured the town of Jalawla while the Iraqi army and Shi&#39;ite militiamen said they have retaken the town of Saadiya.&#160; A reporter for VOA&#39;s Kurdish service said 19 peshmerga were killed and 60 wounded in Jalawla.&#160; Iraqi state TV said security forces also reopened the main road from Baghdad to Samarra.


Germans fighting with IS 


Meanwhile, Germany says it believes about 550 of its countrymen have been or are fighting with Islamic State forces, with about 180 of them already returning to Germany.



Berlin said about 60 Germans have been killed or killed themselves in fighting in Iraq and Syria, including nine suicide bombers.
</description>
            <link>http://www.voanews.com/content/us-plans-to-arm-sunni-tribesmen-in-iraq/2531289.html</link> 
            <guid>http://www.voanews.com/content/us-plans-to-arm-sunni-tribesmen-in-iraq/2531289.html</guid>            
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 11:08:48 -0500</pubDate>
            <category>Middle East</category><author>webdesk@voanews.com (VOA News, Edward Yeranian)</author><comments>http://www.voanews.com/content/us-plans-to-arm-sunni-tribesmen-in-iraq/2531289.html#relatedInfoContainer</comments><enclosure url="http://gdb.voanews.com/AD810DDF-2012-42F6-9401-EC6AE4CD1FAD_w800_h450.jpg" length="3123" type="image/jpeg"/>
        </item>		
        </channel></rss>